<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0003</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2000-05-04">2000-05-04</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Patricia ni Ivor and Rosemary Francis</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0003b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Canberra Women's Liberation Group</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1970-01-01">1970</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1976-12-31">1976</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Social action organisation</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Canberra Women's Liberation Group was formed in June 1970 after two women from Sydney Women's Liberation spoke to eight female anti-Vietnam War activists, who decided to meet on a weekly basis on Wednesday evenings, to discuss their own form of oppression. The weekly meetings continued until 1976. One of its founding members was Julia Ryan. Their meetings were held in different houses in Canberra suburbs until 1975, when they shared Canberra Women's House with the Women's Electoral Lobby and the Abortion Counselling Service.</abstract>
<p>Meeting venues were initially at Canning Street, Ainslie, then in the living rooms of various women's homes. The group grew quickly to more than twenty, with recruits mainly being students, junior academics, or teachers in their twenties and thirties. They rented a house in Bremer Street from 1972 to 1974. In 1975 it moved to Lobelia Street, O'Connor to Canberra Women's House and shared that house with the Women's Electoral Lobby, (WEL) which was formed in 1972 and the Abortion Counselling Service There was no formal membership, hierarchy or structure, although minutes of meetings were kept. Women enrolled on a mailing list and volunteered for jobs. They had a monthly newsletter, which ceased in 1976 as original members moved on to other activities.<br />
Members undertook research into topics such as education, psychology, the nuclear family, and femininity and led the weekly meetings.<br />
The group was invited to address organizations such as the Humanists, Rotary, schools and women's service clubs. Other activities included running information stalls, celebrating International Women's Day, consciousness raising and organizing conferences.<br />
Julia Ryan has argued that 'Canberra WL did not die. It changed our lives, and the ideology spread so wide that those of us who had known every feminist in Canberra now did not know every feminist in our suburb. The movement had grown, not in the way we imagined, but beyond our dreams.'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0002b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Ryan, Julia (1937 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-764071">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Canberra Women's Liberation Group', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Canberra Women's Liberation Group</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0003b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005041.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Canberra Women's Liberation</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Wollstonecraft, Shulasmith</name>
<title render="quoted">Canberra Women's Liberation</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
<date>1998</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian feminism : a companion</title>
<name type="author">Caine, Barbara; Gatens, Moira; Grahame, Emma; Larbalestier, Jan; Watson, Sophie and Webby Elizabeth</name>
<num type="pages">395-96</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000003.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Julia Ryan</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Private Hands (contact Australian Women's Archive Project)</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Julia Ryan</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1970 - c. 1990</unitdate>
<abstract>11 boxes of papers and associated records pertaining to feminist activities in Canberra, including a typed copy of the minutes of the Canberra Women's Liberation movement 1970-1973.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.2 m, 11 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Julia Ryan, feminist. Interviewer, Sara Dowse</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Oral History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Julia Ryan, feminist. Interviewer, Sara Dowse</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 2651</unitid>
<unitdate>c. 1970 - 1990</unitdate>
<abstract>Ryan speaks of the National Foundation for Australian Women, its history and aim to promote feminist ideas into the far future, how the composition of members has changed over the years, the changes to home-based women, the advent of "second-wave" feminism, the history of the women's movement in Canberra starting formally in June 1978, previously operated informally from 1969 as an off-shoot from the Sydney group lead by Lyndal Ryan, how the movement grew through networking, why their meetings were closed to men, how 1972 saw an increase in political involvement with their support of the Aboriginal Embassy tent and the establishment of the Women's Electoral Lobby, their resistance to takeovers by both moderate and extreme political groups, the opportunity feminists had during the Whitlam years to gain influence in the bureaucracy with the appointment of Elizabeth Reid in 1973 as Whitlam's adviser on women's issues, how the group engaged in consciousness-raising, the emergence of femocrats like Mary Menange and Anne Somers threatened to depower women by transferring too much responsibility to government bodies, the highlights of 1975 as International Women's Year and its contribution to the Labour Government dismissal, how feminism eventually influenced the right-wing of politics, the relationship between gender and class in social oppression, the move from Marxist politics to post-modern Foucault models for change and the emergence of women's studies as a discipline.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.02 m, 1 tape</extent>
<physfacet>Audio</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>