<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0822</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2004-04-02">2004-04-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Anne Heywood and Robin Secomb</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-12-02">2013-12-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0822b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (South Australian Branch)</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Social action organisation</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF) began in Australia in 1915 as The Sisterhood of International Peace, with the motto 'Justice, Friendship and Arbitration'. In 1919 the sisterhood heard of the WILPF and became the Australian Section of the League after sending a delegate to the 1919 conference in Zurich. The League 'aims at bringing together women of different political and philosophical tendencies united in their determination to study, make known and help abolish the political, social, economic and psychological causes of war, and to work for a constructive peace'. (from 'Aims, Principles and Policies' a pamphlet printed to celebrate the 50th anniversary of the Australian Section in 1965.) The League also maintained ties with other organizations such as the Women's Christian Temperance Union, the Society of Friends and Save the Children Fund. Ellinor Walker was one of the early secretaries of the League but unfortunately most of the papers pertaining to that time are missing. The WILPF operated as a study group in the 1950s and went into recess in 1965, before being revitalised in response to the Vietnam War. The League vigorously protested against the war and conscription, and used means such as preparing submissions to parliamentary inquiries, sending out pamphlets and organising rallies. Margaret Forte was one of the more active members during the latter period being at various times Secretary, Section Liaison, Junior Media Peace Project convenor and representing the WILPF on other committees such as United Nations Association of Australia (UNAA) (South Australia), Status of Women Committee, People for Nuclear Disarmament, and Time for Peace.</abstract>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4909b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom - ACT branch (1982 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0665b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Walker, Ellinor Gertrude (1893 - 1990)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>One of the early secretaries</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="hierarchical-parent" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0184b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Australia Section) (1919 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-762052">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (South Australian Branch)', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (South Australian Branch)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0822b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003446.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal: Peace and Freedom</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Peace and Freedom</title>
<imprint>
<date>1962-</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Journal of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Australian Section</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001173.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Margaret Forte [sound recording] Interviewer: Helen Chryssides</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Margaret Forte [sound recording] Interviewer: Helen Chryssides</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 250/23</unitid>
<abstract>Kathleen Margaret Forte, nee Johnston, was born in London, England. Her widowed mother emigrated to Wellington, New Zealand when Margaret was seven and supported her three children working as a teacher. Margaret's education included three years boarding at a Friends' School. Margaret worked as a journalist in Sydney and Vancouver before settling and marrying in Adelaide. She gave up working with the News in 1950 after the birth of her second child. Margaret quickly became involved in many voluntary activities, including the South Australian Peace Council. Seeking an organisation with a commitment to total pacifism, she became Secretary of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom in the early 1960s. She describes their energetic opposition to the Vietnam War and the suspicion with which WILPF was viewed at the time. She also discusses WILPF's changing role from being the women's voice in the peace movement to the peace voice in the women's movement.

Recorded on 10 August 1994, 1 hour 32 minutes.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 tapes</extent>
<physfacet>Sound cassette</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001150.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Cathy Picone [sound recording] Interviewer: Helen Chryssides</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Cathy Picone [sound recording] Interviewer: Helen Chryssides</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 250/2</unitid>
<abstract>Catherine Picone was born in Moree, New South Wales. Cathy was brought up as a Catholic, her Italian/Irish father's faith, and her parents' different religious practices were a source of tension in her youth. Cathy's father was a successful bookmaker and Cathy did her secondary schooling at a Catholic college in Armidale. After false starts in Medicine and Science courses, she studied Arts at Sydney University and graduated with a DipEd. With her husband, Cathy moved to South Australia in 1973 and worked in suburban high schools. In the early 1980s she became determined to do community service that was 'change-oriented'. She became involved in People for Nuclear Disarmament. Through this she was invited to join the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom. Cathy explains the origins of WILPF, her perceptions of the ageing local branch, and her aims and tactics 'to bring in new populations'. Cathy also discusses her positive philosophy of life.

Recorded on 14 January 1994. 1 hour 56 minutes.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 cassette tapes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001907.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Australian Section, Records</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of Victoria, Australian Manuscripts Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, Australian Section, Records</unittitle>
<unitid>MS 9377</unitid>
<unitdate>1915 - 1973</unitdate>
<abstract>Correspondence, minutes, annual reports, newsletters, photographs and printed items related to Australian and international peace movements. Also includes papers of Anna Vroland and Eleanor Moore and documents concerning WILPF International, Australian Aborigines, conscription and women's rights. Also, correspondence between the New Zealand section of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom and the Australian section of the same League, 1 July 1958-8 January 1967.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>38 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001376.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Women's International League for Peace &amp; Freedom</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Women's International League for Peace &amp; Freedom</unittitle>
<unitid>SRG 382</unitid>
<unitdate>1958 - 1973</unitdate>
<abstract>Records include a brief history of the South Australian branch from the 1950s to 1988; seminars and speeches given by Senator Coleman, Judith Roberts and Diana Maddocks; as well as resolutions passed. No series list available. For details of the League and its aims refer also to 'Oral History of Women's Political Activity: Interview with Cathy Picone' [sound recording] Interviewer: Helen Chryssides, J.D. Somerville Oral History Collection, State Library of South Australia, OH 250/2 and 'Oral History of Women's Political Activity: Interview with Margaret Forte [sound recording]' Interviewer: Helen Chryssides, J.D. Somerville Oral History Collection, State Library of South Australia, OH 250/23</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.1 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>