<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0792</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2004-03-19">2004-03-19</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Jane Carey and Anne Heywood</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-08-28">2015-08-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0792b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>The Country Women's Association of Western Australia (Inc)</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1924-01-01">1924</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Western Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Lobby group</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Country Women's Association of the Western is a non-sectarian, non-party-political, non-profit lobby group and service association working in the interests of women and children in rural areas. Although ostensibly non-party-political, in practice the group has tended to bolster conservative politics and has supported traditional family roles for women. Historically, it was, however, also a progressive force in many ways, particularly in its encouragement of country women to take an active part in public affairs, and also in its lobby for and provision of services to rural areas.

Given its size and scope, it was arguably the most influential women's organisation in Western Australia in the twentieth century.</abstract>
<p>The formation of a country women's association in Western Australia was first proposed in 1923 by Lady Forster (wife of the then Governor General). While visiting Perth she addressed a meeting of the National Council of Women at the Karrakatta Club about the recently formed New South Wales Association. A provisional committee was formed to set about establishing a Western Australian Association. Mabel Craven-Griffith sent hundreds of letters and travelled extensively to arouse interest in the proposal. The first meeting was held in Perth in early 1924 and by the end of the year four branches were operating. The first conference was held in March 1925, attended by the four founding branches, at which Craven-Griffiths was elected as the first state president. The original motto, 'Honour to God, Loyalty to the Throne and Empire, Service to the Country, Through Countrywomen, for Countrywomen, by Countrywomen' was also adopted.</p>
<p>The first objective of most branches was to establish a Rest Room, where children could be fed and tea made when women from rural areas had to visit town, and as a space for meetings. By 1934 the Association claimed 124 branches, of which 24 already had Rest Rooms. Many were also used for a wide array of other purposes, for example: baby clinics and kindergartens; card evening and other social events; meeting rooms for Guides, Scouts and other groups; wartime canteens; polling booths; and some also provide accommodation. From 1933 into the 1940s the CWA arranged for the distribution of free fruit to children in outback areas where it was not grown and was too expensive to purchase. They also arranged holiday camps for outback children.</p>
<p>From 1934 they produced their own newsletter, the Countrywoman of Western Australia, which became a formal monthly publication in 1940. They have also produced numerous cookbooks and local histories.</p>
<p>Membership reached a peak of 12,000 across about 250 branches in the mid 1950s, declining to 9,000 by 1970, although the number of branches had increased. From 1928, Younger Sets (for girls and young women) were also established, reaching a peak of 50 'Sets' by 1942, but these steadily declined and were eventually disbanded in the early 1960s.</p>
<p>During the war years, as in other states, much of the Association's energy was directed towards supporting the war effort. They initiated a War Relief Fund, which purchased materials that were made up into various garments for those in war-devastated areas by members of local branches. Some Rest Rooms were used as 'spotting stations' for Japanese attacks, often manned by CWA members during the day. They arranged accommodation, meals and entertainment for soldiers who were in training or transit. They launched a training scheme for girls to undertake work in rural areas where male labour was in short supply. They contributed to the CWA's nationwide camouflage net making contract, as well as making up various woolen garments and other items, as well as sheepskin vests .After the war they continued to send food parcels and clothing to Britain.</p>
<p>They assisted particularly with the Women's Land Army, the nationwide CWA camouflage net making contract (of which 20,000 were made). Thousand of pounds were raised and donated to purchase medical equipment for the army, a trainer plane for the RAAF and to provide meals and other 'comforts' for soldiers in training camps, as well as large donations to the Red Cross. Almost every branch had an Emergency World Circle which made up various woolen garments and other items, as well as sheepskin vests. They also supported 'Food for Britain<br />
Nationwide, CWA memebers made over 150,000 camouflage nets, as well as sheepskin vests for flight crews, and numerous ohther woollen garments. They also established a 'Comforts Fund' for soldiers and sent clothing and bedding to women and children in London.</p>
<p>In the postwar years the Association's activities expanded considerably. In 1946 a Club House was rented in Perth to provide both meeting rooms and accommodation, and in 1953 separate headquarter were built. Numerous holiday homes were also purchased and since the 1960s it has also established aged care homes for members. Handicrafts had been a strong feature of the Association since the 1930s, with numerous statewide exhibitions being held. In the 1940s and 1950s various handicraft schools were organised and the central Handicraft Committee sent out numerous packages of materials and instructions to outlying branches. In the 1950s numerous Association choirs were established, and from 1953 statewide drama contests were held. In 1974, to celebrate the Association's golden jubilee, over two hundred histories of local branches were written and sent to the central office.</p>
<p>A variety of welfare activities were also undertaken, with a welfare fund having being established in 1934, to assist members in need or times of emergencies and natural disasters. Various funds have also assisted rural children to attend high school, and have been donated to causes both in Australia and abroad. In 1935 an Emergency Housekeeper Scheme was established. This became a separate in 1937, but in 1969 was taken over again by the Association. From the 1930s it established and ran several hostels for country school students who needed to live away from home in regional centres in order to attend high school. Most of these were transferred to government control in the 1960s.</p>
<p>The Association has also worked closely with numerous other organisations, particularly the Travellers' Aid Service. It has also had representatives a diverse range of groups, including, for example, the State Housing Authority, the Good Neighbour Council, the Keep Australia Beautiful Council, the Health Education Council, the Royal Flying Doctor Service, the WA Association for Children's Films and Television.</p>
<p>As of 2004 the Association's aim is: 'To improve the well being of all people especially those in country areas by promoting courtesy, co-operation, community effort, ethical standards and the wise use of resources.' It maintains holiday accommodation and retirement units; welfare and education funds; and an emergency home help service. Recently it has focussed particularly on the issue of aged care. Since 1988 it has run a rural information service, which monitors and disseminates information on rural services and assistance particularly relating to health, education and aged care.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4911b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Country Women's Association of New South Wales, Canberra Branch (1946 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0166b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Spencer, Ida May (1900 - 1982)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1955-01-01">1955</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1958-12-31">1958</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0050b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Roe, Raigh Edith (1922 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1967-01-01">1967</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1970-12-31">1970</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0789b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The South Australian Country Women's Association Inc. (1929 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0788b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Queensland Country Women's Association (1922 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0791b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Country Women's Association of Victoria Inc. (1928 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0787b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Country Women's Association of the Northern Territory (1961 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0790b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Country Women's Association of Tasmania (1936 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0786b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Country Women's Association of New South Wales (1922 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0209b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Country Women's Association of Australia (1945 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-595736">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'The Country Women's Association of Western Australia (Inc)', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">The Country Women's Association of Western Australia (Inc)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0792b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002801.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Country Women's Association of WA Inc., Wubin Branch History, 1974-1984</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Wubin Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Country Women's Association of WA Inc., Wubin Branch History, 1974-1984</title>
<imprint>
<date>1984?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002622.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: 60 years of the Countrywoman of Western Australia : official publication of the Country Women's Association of W.A. (Inc.), 1934-1994.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">60 years of the Countrywoman of Western Australia : official publication of the Country Women's Association of W.A. (Inc.), 1934-1994.</title>
<imprint>
<place>[Perth, W.A.]</place>
<publisher>The Association</publisher>
<date>[1994?]</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002796.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newsletter: The Countrywoman of  Western Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">The Countrywoman of  Western Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>1940-</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002797.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal: South Coast Calling/CWA WA</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Albany Branch</name>
<title render="italic">South Coast Calling/CWA WA</title>
<imprint>
<date>1981?-1998</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002798.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: A History of the South Eastern Division CWA, 1953-1996</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Money, Louie</name>
<title render="italic">A History of the South Eastern Division CWA, 1953-1996</title>
<imprint>
<place>Corrigin</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia, South Eastern Division</publisher>
<date>199?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002800.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Salmon Gums CWA, 1938-1978</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Salmon Gums Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Salmon Gums CWA, 1938-1978</title>
<imprint>
<date>1979?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002810.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Silver Years in the Golden West, 1924-1949</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Silver Years in the Golden West, 1924-1949</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>1949</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002802.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: A History of the Jibberding Branch of Country-woman's Association of Western Australia, 1974-1984</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Bowen, Rose</name>
<title render="italic">A History of the Jibberding Branch of Country-woman's Association of Western Australia, 1974-1984</title>
<imprint>
<date>1984?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002803.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Country Women's Association, Buntine Branch History - 1974 to 1984</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Buntine Branch History</name>
<title render="italic">Country Women's Association, Buntine Branch History - 1974 to 1984</title>
<imprint>
<date>1984?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002804.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Pithara Branch, 1974-1984</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Pithara Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Pithara Branch, 1974-1984</title>
<imprint>
<date>1984?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002805.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Carnarvon, November 1938- / C.W.A, W.A.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Carnarvon Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Carnarvon, November 1938- / C.W.A, W.A.</title>
<imprint>
<place>Carnarvon</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Carnarvon Branch
 Carnarvon Branch,</publisher>
<date>1993?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002806.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: A Continuing Story</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Kelly, Barbara [et. al.].</name>
<title render="italic">A Continuing Story</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>1999</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002807.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Her Name is Woman</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Erickson, Rica, Gibbings, Beatrice, Higgins, Lilian</name>
<title render="italic">Her Name is Woman</title>
<imprint>
<place>Perth</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia</publisher>
<date>1974</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002808.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Grass Patch, 1952-2002</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Grass Patch Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Grass Patch, 1952-2002</title>
<imprint>
<place>Grass Patch</place>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Grass Patch Branch</publisher>
<date>2002</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002809.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: History of Southern Cross Branch of C.W.A., 1934-1971</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Forrester, Erna L.</name>
<title render="italic">History of Southern Cross Branch of C.W.A., 1934-1971</title>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002799.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Dalwallinu Branch History, 1974-1983</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Western Australia, Dalwallinu Branch</name>
<title render="italic">Dalwallinu Branch History, 1974-1983</title>
<imprint>
<date>1984?</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002621.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal Article: CWA : celebrating 75 years.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">CWA : celebrating 75 years.</title>
<imprint>
<date>1998</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Countryman</title>
<num type="issue">6 August</num>
<num type="pages">27-40</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP001435.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Many Hats of Country Women: The Jubilee History of the Country Women's Association of Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Stevens-Chambers, Brenda</name>
<title render="italic">The Many Hats of Country Women: The Jubilee History of the Country Women's Association of Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Country Women's Association of Australia</publisher>
<date>1997</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002624.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: She's no milkmaid : a biography of Dame Raigh Roe, D.B.E.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Erickson, Rica, Haywood, Rona and Oldham, Jan (sketches by)</name>
<title render="italic">She's no milkmaid : a biography of Dame Raigh Roe, D.B.E.</title>
<imprint>
<place>Carlisle, W.A.</place>
<publisher>Hesperian Press</publisher>
<date>[1991?]</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002619.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Getting things done : the Country Women's Association of Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Country Women's Association of Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Getting things done : the Country Women's Association of Australia</title>
<imprint>
<place>[Cheerybrook, N.S.W.]</place>
<publisher>The Association</publisher>
<date>1986</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001886.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Yerecoin Branch Records</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Yerecoin Branch Records</unittitle>
<unitid>MN 1047</unitid>
<unitdate>1950 - 1983</unitdate>
<abstract>Summary of aims, events, branch officers (1950-1971); summary of events (1974-1983).</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.01 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001551.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Collection of material relating to the various branches of the Country Women's Association of Western Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Collection of material relating to the various branches of the Country Women's Association of Western Australia</unittitle>
<unitid>PR8984  - 0/11</unitid>
<unitdate>1928 - 1989</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001553.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Country Womens Association Of Western Australia, Caron-Bunjil Branch, Minute Books</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Country Womens Association Of Western Australia, Caron-Bunjil Branch, Minute Books</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 1365A</unitid>
<unitdate>1937 - 1954</unitdate>
<abstract>Minute books, 1937-1954 [microform]</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 microfilm reel</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001554.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Winifred Kastner [sound recording]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Winifred Kastner [sound recording]</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 54</unitid>
<abstract>2 sound cassettes (90 min.) Transcript (32 p.) 
Born England 1903, arrived Western Australia in 1930; volunteer work with YWCA during the Depression; handicraft classes; Country Women's Association; tours to group settlements in the South West; radio talks on 6WF; work with Women's Service Guilds; formation of the Civilian Widows Association; League of Home Help; the Red Cross; work with handicapped children; association with Princess Margaret Hospital; Marriage Guidance Council; appointment as a Justice of the Peace; work with Citizens Advice Bureau; Council for the Ageing; Telephone Samaritan Service.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 Cassettes</extent>
<physfacet>Audio</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001552.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Mabel Craven-Griffiths</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Mabel Craven-Griffiths</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 4560A</unitid>
<unitdate>1882 - 1966</unitdate>
<abstract>Autograph album (1886-1963); cards; certificates; diaries (including diary of voyage from England to Australia in 1882); invitations and letters (1919-1959); programmes; scrapbook, etc. relating to her private life as well as her involvement with various organisations such as Country Women's Association, Australian Red Cross Society, Silver Chain Nursing Association, Young Women's Christian Association, West Australian Symphony Orchestra, National Council of Women Business and Professional Women's Club of Perth.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.32 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001550.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">McLarty Family Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>McLarty Family Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 1260A-1261A, 3484A, 1870A</unitid>
<unitdate>1887 - 1969</unitdate>
<abstract>Miscellaneous records relating to John Pollard McLarty, Ernest McLarty, Sir Ross and Lady McLarty and others, including diaries, correspondence, notebooks, invitations, cards etc. dealing with political, station, farming and local Pinjara matters, Country Women's Association (1941-1954), Pinjara Infants Health Centre (1944-1959). Lady McLarty was an active member of the Country Women's Association and became state president in 1953.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.49 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001315.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">History of Yerecoin Branch of the Country Women's Association</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>History of Yerecoin Branch of the Country Women's Association</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 3281A</unitid>
<abstract>Summary of aims, events, branch officers (1950-1971); summary of events (1974-1983)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.01 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001314.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Great Southern Division Records</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Country Women's Association of Western Australia. Great Southern Division Records</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 4555A</unitid>
<unitdate>1948 - 1980</unitdate>
<abstract>Largely correspondence, including letterbooks, 1958-1961; also history of the Gnowangerup CWA, pictorial history of ACWW, register of members (1979)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.32 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001313.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Roe, Raigh Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Roe, Raigh Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 5108A</unitid>
<unitdate>1990</unitdate>
<abstract>Letter regarding proceeds of sale of "She's no milkmaid"; corrected typescript of "She's no milkmaid".</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.02 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000819.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Dame Raigh Roe, Past President, Associated Country Women of the World (sound recording), interviewer: Gail O'Hanlon.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Dame Raigh Roe, Past President, Associated Country Women of the World (sound recording), interviewer: Gail O'Hanlon.</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 3410</unitid>
<unitdate>1995</unitdate>
<abstract>24 sound tape reels, 11 hours and 40 mininute, and 165 page transcript. Speaks of family background, childhood, early jobs, marriage during WWII, brother Alwyn, moving to the farm at Piawaning, primitive conditions she lived &amp; raised her family in, becoming involved in the local CWA, importance of farming diversification, help from Italian POWs and local aboriginals, importance of radio, role of the CWA in the country, her increasing involvement in the CWA, CWA's concern with education, catering &amp; crafts, Frances Craig, Lilian Higgins, Ida Spencer, the "heartbeat of the CWA", involvement in administration (incl. State International Officer, State and National President), the structure of the WA CWA.
Being a Justice of the Peace and sitting in the Summary Relief Court, public speaking, achievements during State Presidency (incl. financial and voting reform, raising the CWA profile, fighting anti-women advertising, residential schools for Aboriginal girls, migrant aid), help provided during WWII, relationship with media, nature of volunteer work, health problems, leaving farm and moving to city, 1974 WA CWA Golden Jubilee and hosting ACWW Conference, assistance given after Cyclone Tracy, awards, period as World President of ACWW, Social Issues Finding Team and research into in vitro fertilisation, prostitution, Bill of Rights and CWA's own membership and preoccupations, recent work with CWA archives, revision of constitution, and membership of various Boards.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001312.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Ivan Bird</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>JS Battye Library of West Australian History, State Library of Western Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Ivan Bird</unittitle>
<unitid>ACC 758A, 5491A</unitid>
<unitdate>1906 - 1966</unitdate>
<abstract>Papers mostly concerned with the history of Albany and its surrounds, and ships and shipwrecks along the WA coast. Includes letters re old farm at Strawberry Hill; histories of islands of Amsterdam and St Paul, Pyrmont House (headquarters of the Albany CWA), and fortifications of Albany; notes on the coastline of WA, including charts of coast and index to ships and shipwrecks, with photographs of ships; scrapbooks re Albany and Strawberry Hill; shipping papers of Bethell Gwyn &amp; Co., Hungry Goose Line, Trinder, Anderson &amp; Co. with photographs of ships and emigrants arriving in Fremantle and Albany.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.2 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001309.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Gairdner Country Women's Association</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Australian Historic Records Register</repository>
<unittitle>Gairdner Country Women's Association</unittitle>
<unitid>2112</unitid>
<unitdate>1961 - 1987</unitdate>
<abstract>Minute books, 1961-1987 (6 vols). 
Cash books recording income and expenditure, 1961-1987 (4 vols). 
Correspondence books recording outward correspondence, 1961-1987 (13 vols). 
Miscellaneous drama and concert records, c1970 (1 file). 
Annual reports from Western Australian state conferences, 1970-1986 (1 file). 
Albums containing photographs of members and functions, 1976 and 1985 (2 albums).</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>