<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0042</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2001-02-02">2001-02-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Elle Morrell, Nikki Henningham and Marie Coleman</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-01-12">2016-01-12</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0042b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Coleman</part>
<part localType="givenname">Marie Yvonne</part>
<part localType="honorific title">AO, PSM</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="maiden name"><part>Burns, Marie</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Dubbo, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Social activist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Educator</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Researcher</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Public servant</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Medical social worker</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Statutory office holder</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Marie Coleman was the first woman to head a Commonwealth Government statutory agency, and the first woman to hold the powers of Permanent Head under the Public Service Act. She was founding Secretary of the National Foundation for Australian Women, one of the NFAW Board of Directors who worked to establish the Australian Women's Archives Project (AWAP), and remains active in community organisations and public life in her retirement. She was awarded the Public Service Medal in 1989 for contributions to public administration. In 2001 she was awarded the Centenary Medal. In 2011 she was appointed Officer of the Order of Australia.</abstract>
<p>Marie Burns was an only child, born in Dubbo, New South Wales (NSW) in March 1933. Her father John Alexander Burns (Alex) was at that time a porter with the Railways Commission of NSW, and the family lived at Nevertire, a small railhead west of Dubbo. Her mother, Kathleen (Nunan) Burns was a former shop assistant with Western Stores, Dubbo ( where she had been apprenticed), and her maternal grandmother, Annie Klintworth (formerly Nunan, nee Manners) lived in Dubbo with her second husband Samuel Klintworth.</p>
<p>The small family moved around remote and rural NSW as Alex pursued promotion. Marie's initial experience with education came through boarding at the small Hunter Valley town of Singleton for six months, to attend pre-primary school; thereafter until a move to Nimmitabel on the Monaro of Southern NSW in 1940 she was educated by correspondence through the NSW Government Education Department's Blackfriars Correspondence School. She was subsequently educated at Dubbo Primary School, Orange Primary School, Orange High School, and Lithgow High School.</p>
<p>She entered the University of Sydney in 1950. She studied Economics and Philosophy for an Arts degree, followed by a Diploma in Social Studies. From 1950-1952 she was a resident of the Women's College, University of Sydney. During her University career she was a member of the Student Representative Council, the Board of Manning Clark House, and editor of the student newspaper <span style="font-style:italic">Honi Soit</span>- at that time only the second woman to hold that position. She represented the University in district women's cricket and Inter-Varsity women's cricket; she represented the University in Inter-Varsity and international debating.</p>
<p>After leaving University she worked briefly as a society page reporter for the <span style="font-style:italic">Sydney Daily Telegraph</span> and for the Royal Empire Society as publicist. In January 1954 she travelled to the USA and then the United Kingdom where, after a period teaching for the London County Council, she married James Harry Coleman, of Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, in 1956. The couple returned to live in Melbourne. She became a scriptwriter for the Australian Broadcasting Commission, in both radio and early television, and then established her own public relations business.<br />
Three daughters were born, Carolyn Margaret Coleman, Susan Dinah Coleman, and Elizabeth Burns Coleman.</p>
<p>In 1964 Coleman became medical social worker at the Preston and Northcote Community Hospital and subsequently Social worker for the Asthma Foundation of Victoria, before joining the Victorian Council of Social Service as Director. Following the (Federal) election in 1972 of the Whitlam Labor Government she was invited to head the newly created Social Welfare Commission.</p>
<p>In 1976, following the election of the Fraser Liberal-National Coalition Government, she was appointed Director of the Office of Child Care. During this period the Commonwealth commenced support for Aboriginal Child agencies, expanded provision of full day care services, before and after school care and school holidays programs, and created a system of child care in women's refuges, and of youth refuges. In 1982 she became Special Adviser in the Social Welfare Policy Secretariat. This entity was subsequently re-formulated and renamed several times.</p>
<p>In 1983, at the invitation of the Government of South Australia, she carried out a review of Early Childhood Services in that state, which was followed by the re-structure of public administrative arrangements in that field. In 1989 she became a foundation member of the National Foundation for Australian Women. In 1990 she accepted a posting as Senior Visiting Fellow at the Australia New Zealand Studies Centre at Pennsylvania State University in the United States of America. During this period she represented the Australian Government at the meeting of the United Nations final Preparatory Committee for the 1993 Rio "Earth Conference". In 1994 she returned to Australia as Acting Director of the Australian Institute of Family Studies in Melbourne, Victoria. In 1994-5 she returned as First Assistant Secretary to the Commonwealth Department of Health and Community Services to review funding for family planning services.</p>
<p>She retired from the Australian Public Service in 1995, recommencing journalism as a regular columnist with the Canberra Times. This continued through to 2003.</p>
<p>She was a consultant and subsequently Director of the Indigenous Social Development Institute, working in Cape York communities in Far North Queensland on adolescent indigenous family development. This continued until 2003. She was appointed as first Chair of the Management Assessment Panel for the Australian Capital Territory, and subsequently in addition as the Alternate Chair of the Care Coordination Panel.</p>
<p>During the celebrations marking the Centenary of Federation of the Commonwealth of Australia, she was awarded the Commonwealth Honors System's Centenary Medal for services to public administration, the Centenary Medal of the Australian Institute of Public Administration for services to public administration, and placed on the Victorian Parliament's Honor Roll of Women, in recognition of services to Victoria and the Nation. In 2006 she was placed on the ACT Honour Roll of Women and awarded an EDNA. This award was created in 1998 to honour the life and work of Edna Ryan and is awarded to feminists whose activity has advanced the cause of women.</p>
<p>In 2003 she became Chair of the Advisory Board to the Hindmarsh Education Centre, at the Quamby Youth Detention Centre, Australian Capital Territory. She retired in 2007.</p>
<p>In 2011 she was appointed ACT Senior Australian of the year and appointed Officer in the General Division of the Order of Australia 'for distinguished service to the advancement of women, particularly through the National Foundation for Women and the Australian Women's Archives Project'.</p>
<p>In 2012 she continues to work for the Australian Women's Archives Project and for the Social Policy Committee of the National Council for Australian Women. She is also Chair of the Management Assessment Panel and the Care Cooordination Panel of the ACT.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0009b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Foundation for Australian Women (1989 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1997-01-01">1997</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2002-12-31">2002</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Re-appointed as Director and Secretary of NFAW in 2000 and then Director in 2001. Assisted in the formalisation of the NFAW Preferred Donor arrangements, edited newsletter, and assisted with development of Australian Women's Archives Project.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0070b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Social Welfare Commission (1972 - 1975)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1972-01-01">1972</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1975-12-31">1975</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Following the election of Whitlam Labor Government in 1972 Marie Coleman was invited by Minister William Hayden and PM Edward Gough Whitlam to Chair the newly created National Social Welfare Commission.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0073b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Child Accident Prevention Foundation of Australia (c. 1980 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman assisted in development of plans for Child Accident Prevention Foundation of Australia, and was appointed Director, during her tenure at the Office of Child Care.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0068b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Manning House Women's Union, Sydney University
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1953-01-01">1953</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1954-12-31">1954</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0069b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Victorian Council of Social Service (1946 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1969-01-01">1969</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0071b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Office of Child Care, Commonwealth Department of Social Security
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1975-01-01">1975</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1982-12-31">1982</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman was invited by Minister Senator Margaret Guilfoyle and PM Malcolm Fraser to accept appointment as Director of the Office of Child Care in the Department of Social Security.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0079b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Institute of Family Studies
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1994-01-01">1994</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1995-12-31">1995</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman was Acting Director pending the arrival from the UK of the Director-elect. She oversaw re-structuring at AIFS and assisted in the organization of national conferences for International Year of the Family.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0077b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Sexual Health and Family Planning Australia
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1969-01-01">c. 1969</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1970-12-31">c. 1970</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman was a committee member of the planning group which established FPA Vic.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0009b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Foundation for Australian Women (1989 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1989-01-01">1989</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0076b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Reproductive Health Alliance, Australian Reproductive Health Foundation (1995 - 2011)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1995-01-01">1995</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2011-12-31">2011</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0076b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Reproductive Health Alliance, Australian Reproductive Health Foundation (1995 - 2011)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1995-01-01">1995</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2011-12-31">2011</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0078b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Canberra Mothercraft Society Inc (1929 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1995-01-01">1995</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1995-12-31">1995</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>She was president for one year.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2186b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
Revolution and Reform - 1975 and Beyond (2006 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman was an NFAW organiser of the August 6 2005 'Day of Celebration'.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1246b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Dyer, Mollie (1927 - 1998)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Worked together to establish a network of Aboriginal and Islander child care agencies throughout Australia</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0075b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Guilfoyle, Margaret Georgina (1926 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>In 1975, Marie was invited by Minister Senator Margaret Guilfoyle and Prime Minister Malcolm Fraser to accept appointment as Director of the Office of Child Care in the Department of Social Security.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4779b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Bilney, Elizabeth (1943 - 2010)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>As Chair of the Social Welfare Commission in 1973 Coleman advised Bilney and others from the ACT WEL on how to pursue their ideas about expanding childcare.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0072b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Family Support Program (c. 1975 - c. 1982)
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1975-01-01">c. 1975</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1982-12-31">c. 1982</toDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman introduced the Family Support Program when she was Director of the Office of Child Care</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0074b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
National Women's Conference
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1990-01-01">1990</fromDate>
</dateRange>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marie Coleman assisted with the organization of the first National Women's Conference in Canberra in 1990 for the NFAW.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-461460">
<relationEntry>
Coleman, Marie (1933-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Coleman, Marie Yvonne', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Coleman, Marie Yvonne</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0042b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002238.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Web-Savvy and wired into the women's movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Coleman, Marie</name>
<title render="quoted">Web-Savvy and wired into the women's movement</title>
<imprint>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</title>
<num type="pages">46</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002236.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Tireless activist for women's movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Coleman, Marie</name>
<title render="quoted">Tireless activist for women's movement</title>
<imprint>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian</title>
<num type="pages">18</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003533.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Black Grapevine: Aboriginal Activism and the Stolen Generations</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Briskman, Linda</name>
<title render="italic">The Black Grapevine: Aboriginal Activism and the Stolen Generations</title>
<imprint>
<place>Annandale, NSW</place>
<publisher>The Federation</publisher>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP000147.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who of Australian Women</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Lofthouse, Andrea</name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who of Australian Women</title>
<imprint>
<place>North Ryde (NSW)</place>
<publisher>Methuen Australia</publisher>
<date>1982</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP000092.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who in Australia 1999</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who in Australia 1999</title>
<edition>34th</edition>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Information Australia Group Pty Ltd</publisher>
<date>1998</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000063.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Marie Coleman</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Private Hands (contact Australian Women's Archive Project)</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Marie Coleman</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1960 - 2001</unitdate>
<abstract>Currently all held privately. In early discussions with the National Library of Ausralia.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00013.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Records created and maintained by Marie Coleman as Director, Office of Child Care</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Archives of Australia, National Office</repository>
<unittitle>Records created and maintained by Marie Coleman as Director, Office of Child Care</unittitle>
<unitid>M4697</unitid>
<unitdate>December 1976  - January 1982</unitdate>
<abstract>This series comprises records created and maintained by Marie Coleman as Director, Office of Child Care for the period December 1976 to April 1979. Correspondence, publications and VHS video titled <span style="font-style:italic">Woman in Question</span> produced by ABC Television are included in the series.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.180000007152557 m</extent>
<physfacet>Correspondence, video</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001965.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Burns Family Portraits and Early Scenes from Roseby Park and Brewarrina</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>AIATSIS Pictorial Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Burns Family Portraits and Early Scenes from Roseby Park and Brewarrina</unittitle>
<unitid>COLEMAN M1/M2.CD</unitid>
<unitdate>1915 - 1929</unitdate>
<abstract>14 TIFF photo files</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Photographs</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00003.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Celebrating Marie Coleman's paternal aunt's 100th birthday.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Celebrating Marie Coleman's paternal aunt's 100th birthday.</unittitle>
<abstract>L-R: Jessie Wardman, Elaine Johnson,  (Aunt) Elizabeth Morralee Wardman, Marie Coleman, January 13 2001.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>