<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0592</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2003-10-10">2003-10-10</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Anne Heywood</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0592b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Board</part>
<part localType="givenname">Ruby Willmet</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1880-10-15">15 October 1880</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1963-12-25">25 December 1963</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Gunning, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Social welfare</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Women's rights activist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Women's rights organiser</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Community worker</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Following her education in Sydney, Berlin and Paris, Ruby Board devoted her time to social welfare issues. She became a Member of the Board of the Rachael Forster Hospital and for a period was President of the National Council of Women of New South Wales. During World War II, Board was president of the Women's Voluntary National Register, a member of the executive of the Australian Comforts Fund and Defence Director of the Women's Auxiliary National Service.</abstract>
<p>Ruby Board was the third president of the National Council of Women of Australia, assuming office in November 1942 in the depths of World War II. With her long experience in the organisation, she provided a steady hand during the two years of her NCWA leadership, focusing on issues relating particularly to treatment and pay of women in the services, postwar reconstruction (especially housing), and the perennial matters of uniform marriage and divorce laws and the nationality of married women (now made urgent by wartime marriages between Australian women and American soldiers). She had earlier led the Australian delegation to the International Council of Women in Washington in 1925 and served as treasurer of the Federal Council of the National Councils of Women of Australia and as interim treasurer of the new National Council of Women of Australia until the first board was elected in October 1931. Ruby Board also filled a number of offices in the NSW Council from before World War I, culminating in the presidency from 1938 to 1948.</p>
<p>The daughter of the renowned progressive NSW director of education, Peter Board, Ruby was educated in Sydney, Berlin and Paris, and, with no need to work for a living, devoted her adult life to social welfare and issues relating to justice for women. In addition to her NCW work during World War II, Board played a leading in NSW war support as president of the Women's Voluntary National Register, a member of the executive of the Australian Comforts Fund, Defence Director of the Women's Auxiliary National Service and president of the Housekeepers' Emergency Service. Board's other significant organisational work included membership of the Board of the Rachel Forster Hospital, local leadership of the Country Women's Association in the 1930s, and leading roles in the Diabetic Association of New South Wales from 1949-61.</p>
<p>Ruby Board was born on 15 October 1880, at Gunning, New South Wales, the only child of Peter Board and his wife Jessie Allen, née Bowes. Her social conscience was moulded by childhood happiness in 'this small and closely linked family' and by the progressive ideals of her father, who served as the first NSW director of education from 1905-22. Reform ideals and issues concerning justice for women (including suffrage) were also instilled by her maternal grandmother, Euphemia Bowes, who was a founder and early president of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union in NSW. Ruby also received a broad education, owing to her father's travels during periods of leave; she attended schools in Sydney, Berlin and Paris. Having independent means, Ruby was free to combine her aptitude for language with an interest in welfare. She published pamphlets on <span style="font-style:italic">Australian Pronunciation: A Handbook for the Teaching of English in Australia</span> (1927) and the <span style="font-style:italic">Pupils' Practice Book for Vowel Sounds </span>(1928).</p>
<p>In the early 1920s, Ruby Board moved with her parents to Leura, where she nursed her mother until her death in 1932. There she became a leading figure in the Country Women's Association and was president of the Blue Mountains branch from 1930 to 1938. A member of the National Council of Women of New South Wales for 50 years, she was honorary general secretary 1914-1918, interstate secretary 1919, president 1938-1948, and state delegate to the national conferences in 1946 and 1948. She led the Australian delegates to the sixth quinquennial convention of the International Council of Women in Washington in 1925. In 1931, she was interim honorary treasurer of the National Council of Women of Australia, president from 1942 to 1944 and Australian convenor for home economics for the period from 1944 up to 1952. As national president, she focused on war work but with an emphasis on the issues of importance to women-treatment and pay of women in the services, postwar reconstruction (especially housing), and uniform marriage and divorce laws and the nationality of married women, an issue of particular moment because of wartime marriages between Australian women and American soldiers. She was particularly proud to preside over the women's reception to Eleanor Roosevelt, the wife and emissary of the US president, in Sydney Town Hall in 1943.</p>
<p>Board's period in office also saw the establishment of the Australian Women's Charter movement and conference by Jessie Street, a challenge to the claims of the NCWA to speak for Australian women. Board made it clear to the Australian government that this conference did not have the support of the Councils or speak for the majority of women's organisations, while also encouraging state Councils to hold their own conferences to demonstrate they were not necessarily opposing the main points of the Charter. Many of the same issues were considered and approved at the 1944 national conference, which Board chaired.</p>
<p>Though Ruby Board served as NSW president from 1938 to 1948, she refused appointment as MBE because she believed that her office, reflecting the work of the Council, deserved higher recognition.</p>
<p>From 1939 to 1958, Ruby Board was also a vice-president of the Rachel Forster Hospital for Women and Children. During World War II, she was a member of the NSW executive of the Australian Comforts Fund and founding president of the state Women's Voluntary National Register in 1940, as well as defence director of the Women's Auxiliary National Service, helping to co-ordinate the work of women's organisations for the war effort. In 1943, she was a founder and first president of the Housekeepers' Emergency Service of NSW.</p>
<p>A diabetic from the 1930s, she demonstrated effectively how little this condition need interfere with a busy and productive life. She was an office-bearer of the Diabetic Association of New South Wales from 1949 and served as president from 1951 to 1960. Anxious to inform the public of the problems associated with the disease, she organised a lecture tour in 1953 by two world authorities and, in 1955 and 1958, attended congresses of the International Diabetes Federation at Cambridge, England, and Düsseldorf, Germany. In 1957, she was founding president of the Diabetic Association of Australia and chaired its first conference held in Sydney.</p>
<p>From 1960, Ruby Board lived at the Mowll Memorial Village, Castle Hill, until she had a fall in December 1963; she died on Christmas Day in the Rachel Forster Hospital.</p>
<p>Selfless and generous, with boundless energy, she inspired those around her to similar enthusiasm and commitment. She was not interested in power for its own sake, or in office for its prestige, and always sought to provide opportunities for individual expansion and development. Her obituarist in the NSW NCW newsletter judged her to be 'balanced, judicious, tolerant, serene' and to have 'the saving grace of humour'. Her work for diabetics was commemorated by the naming of the diabetic wing of the Rachel Forster Hospital after her in 1966.</p>
<p>Prepared by: <span class="uppercase">Jan Hipgrave, Marian Quartly and Judith Smart</span></p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1940-01-01">1940</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1940-12-31">1940</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Presided - Women's Voluntary National Register</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0209b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Country Women's Association of Australia (1945 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0555b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Council of Women of New South Wales (1896 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1938-01-01">1938</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1948-12-31">1948</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0067b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Council of Women of Australia (1931 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1942-01-01">1942</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1944-12-31">1944</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4902b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Organisation">
Emergency Housekeeper Service (1947 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1943-01-01">1943</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1943-12-31">1943</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4933b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Metcalfe, Thelma Constance (1898 - 1984)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0013b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Street, Jessie Mary Grey (1889 - 1970)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-720066">
<relationEntry>
Board, Ruby Willmet (1880-1963)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Board, Ruby Willmet', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Board, Ruby Willmet</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0592b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005535.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newsletter: NCW News (NCW NSW)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">NCW News (NCW NSW)</title>
<imprint>
<date>February 1964</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002911.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Pupil's practice book for vowel sounds</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Board, Ruby W</name>
<title render="italic">Pupil's practice book for vowel sounds</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Govt. Printer</publisher>
<date>1928</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002910.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Australian pronunciation : a handbook for the teaching of English in Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Board, Ruby W</name>
<title render="italic">Australian pronunciation : a handbook for the teaching of English in Australia</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Teachers' College Press</publisher>
<date>1927</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005528.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Stirrers with Style! Presidents of the National Council of Women of Australia and its predecessors</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">National Council of Women of Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Stirrers with Style! Presidents of the National Council of Women of Australia and its predecessors</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ncwa"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002143.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who in Australia, 1947</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Chisholm, Alec H</name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who in Australia, 1947</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>The Herald and Weekly Times</publisher>
<date>1947</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/ADB100119.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Board, Ruby Willmet (1881-1963)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Wright, Andrée</name>
<title render="quoted">Board, Ruby Willmet (1881-1963)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian National University</publisher>
<date>2006</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian Dictionary of Biography Online</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.adb.online.anu.edu.au/biogs/A070335b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001865.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">National Council of Women Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>National Council of Women Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>ML MSS 3739 and ML MSS 3739 ADD-ON 2061</unitid>
<unitdate>1895 - 1990</unitdate>
<abstract>Minutes of executive meetings, including half yearly and quarterly general meetings, 1895-1928; minutes of executive meetings 1928-85; minutes of general meetings, 1921-1955; tape recordings of various events in 1976; general council meetings minutes, 1955-1988; financial records, 1926-1990.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002731.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1924-1990 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1924-1990 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS7583</unitid>
<unitdate>1924 - 1990</unitdate>
<abstract>MS 7583 comprises correspondence, board minutes, executive records, conference records and papers relating to submissions and campaigns. There are also papers relating to the International Council of Women (24 boxes).

The Acc GB 1993/1502 instalment comprises records of the National Council of Women of the Australian Capital Territory and includes minutes, correspondence, membership lists, reports, including annual reports for 1952-1990, photographs, cuttings and financial records (4 cartons, 1 small carton).

The Acc07/96 instalment comprises records relating to seminars and conferences, policy and the history of the National Council of Women of Australia, correspondence, publications, submission papers and meeting minutes (35 boxes).
The National Council of Women of Australia originated with various state councils, the first being formed in 1896 in New South Wales. In 1931 the Australian National Council of Women was founded as a non-profit organisation promoting women's issues and social welfare. In 1970 the Council's name was changed to the National Council of Women of Australia. The Council is an affiliated member of the International Council of Women, a federation of non-government organisations in many countries.
Manuscript reference no.: MS 7583, MS Acc GB 1993/­1502, MS Acc07/­96.

Associated materials: Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1936-1972 MS 5193.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>10.25 m, 59 Boxes + 4 cartons + 1 small carton.</extent>
<physfacet>manuscript</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001597.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">[Biographical cuttings on Ruby Board, public servant]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Newspaper Microcopy Reading Room</repository>
<unittitle>[Biographical cuttings on Ruby Board, public servant]</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Press cuttings</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000441.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Fleming Arnot - personal and professional papers, 1890-1995</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Fleming Arnot - personal and professional papers, 1890-1995</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 3147 ADD-ON 2070/1-15</unitid>
<unitdate>1890 - 1995</unitdate>
<abstract>1948-1949; Diaries (3): 8 Apr.-1 Aug. 1948, 2 Aug.-26 Nov. 1948, and 27 Nov. 1948-15 Feb. 1949, concerning study trip of American and British libraries (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
5 Sep.-15 Dec. 1961; Diary mainly concerning trip to IFLA International Conference on Cataloguing Principles, Paris, 9-18 Oct. 1961 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
1963-1994; Pocket appointments' diaries, being one for each year, except two for 1989, and excluding 1983 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
1983-1988; A4 and quarto appointments' diaries (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/2)

ca. 1913, 1933-1989; Correspondence, with enclosures including Future Projection for Women at Work, being her paper at the Victorian Employers' Federation Women at Work Conference, Melbourne, 21 July 1969, and copy of Public Aministration, vol. 5 no. 8, Dec. 1945, featuring her article, ' Employment of Women in the Civil Service'. Correspondents include Australian Congress for International Co-operation and Disarmament, Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Division of New South Wales, Australian Freedom from Hunger Campaign. New South Wales Committee, Ruby W. Board, Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, R. F. Doust, Mary Fairfax, Sir Vincent Fairfax, Eileen Furley, Irene Greenwood, Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper, Noel L. Lamidey, Andrea Lofthouse, Norman Mackenzie, National Council of Women of New South Wales, Ted Noffs, Fanny Reading, Bessie Mabel Rischbieth, Jessie Street, Nancy Bird Walton and Margaret Woodhouse (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1934-1990; 'Letters of Library Interest and Documents', being correspondence, with enclosures including her paper, Cataloguing and Classification of Special and Private Collections, delivered at the Library Association of Australia Conference, Melbourne, 27 Aug. 1975. Correspondents include Henry and Leo Berkelouw, Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, Carnegie Corporation of New York, Jim Cleary, Gerald Fischer, Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper, Eleanor M. Hinder, W. H. Ifould, Phyllis Mander-Jones, John Andrew Osborn, Barrett Reid, G. D. Richardson and the State Library of New South Wales (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1948-1949; Letters received from her mother, Jane Arnot, Alison McPherson and a nephew. See also letters from Jean Arnot to family and friends, 1948-1949, 1961, at ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1959-1992; Postcards received and drafts not sent (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, AAD ON 2070/3)
1961-1975; 'Vice Regal &amp; Official Christmas Cards' (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1964-1965; Correspondence concerning her nomination for MBE and congratulatory letters received (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1965-1991; References and testimonials for others (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)

1916-1969; Papers concerning her secondary education and employment with the Public Library of New South Wales (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1933-1994; Papers mainly concerning friends, colleagues and interests, including letters received, newscuttings and obituaries. Correspondents and/or subjects include James Allison, Zoe Emma Bertles, Freda Milicent Bryant, Flo Cluff, Alison Crook, Sir Vincent Fairfax, Film Australia, L. F. Fitzhardinge, Muriel A. Heagney, Theodora Hobbs, Millie Hoy, Marie V. Hurley, W. H. Ifould, Jessie Street Women's Library, Beatrice Anne Stewart Instone, Bee Miles, Museum of Australian Childhood, Molly Newman, Wilma Radford, Barrett Reid, Edith Alice Sims, Jocelynne A. Scutt, H. L. White and Margaret Woodhouse (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1948-1949; Papers concerning overseas study trip. Includes correspondence with the British Council and the Carnegie Corporation of New York; professional itinerary and copies of her report, Visit to Libraries in Britain and America 1948-9; theatre programs; and menus from the ship, RMS Queen Elizabeth (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1959-1961; Papers mainly concerning the International Federation of Library Associations' International Conference on Cataloguing Principles, Paris, 9-18 Oct. 1961 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1961-1962; Papers concerning 'Committee on Cataloguing Paris Conference - LAA File' (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1961-1967; Papers concerning Cataloguing Code Revision, including Australian working papers on 1961 IFLA Conference agenda items (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1962, 1972-1995; Papers concerning the Nita B. Kibble Literary Award and the Nita May Dobbie Award (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1962-1965, 1981-1993; Papers concerning her entries submitted to the Australian Dictionary of Biography, being the Reverend John McGarvie (1795-1853), W. H. Ifould (1877-1969), Nita Bernice Kibble (1879-1962) and Margaret MacPherson (1875-1956) (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968; Papers concerning her retirement from the Public Library of New South Wales on 19 Apr. 1968, including testimonial under seal issued by the Library Trustees; letter received from G. D. Richardson, Principal Librarian, 26 Apr. 1968; farewell cards, invitations and tributes from outside the Library; letter received from Mollie Thomson, co-host of the afternoon tea party held in Jean Arnot's honour; and papers concerning universal party organised by Wilma Radford at the University of NSW, 27 Apr. 1968, with letters of appreciation received (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968-1971; Papers concerning her indexing the reprint volumes of The Sydney Gazette 1810-1811 for the Library of NSW, including correspondence with Frank Dunn, Dixson Librarian (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968-1992; Papers mainly concerning her oral history interview by Anne Robertson for the State Library of New South Wales' sesquicentenary and the Library's acquisition of her papers. Includes her notebook compiled for the interview with details of her career and campaign for equal pay. (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1969-1991; Papers concerning her cataloguing of the Library of Camden Park, Menangle, N.S.W., including correspondence with the owners, Quentin and Antonia Macarthur Stanham, 1969-1971 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1980-1992; Papers mainly concerning the State Library of New South Wales and its Library Society and the Australian Library and Information Association, including correspondence, newscuttings and invitations (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1987; Papers concerning the Library Association of Australia's 50th anniversary celebrations, Canberra, 2-4 Sep. 1987, including her talk on her first visit to Canberra for the launching of the Australian Institute of Librarians, 1937 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1993-1995; Papers concerning luncheons in honour of her 90th birthday, celebrated chiefly at Parliament House, Sydney, 19 Apr. 1993. Includes presentation album with letters received from, among others, Alison Crook, State Librarian; Jean M. Elliston, President, National Council of Women of N.S.W. Inc.; Premier John Fahey; Warren Horton, Director-General, National Library of Australia; Prime Minister Paul Keating; Kaye Loder, Convenor, National Women's Consultative Committee; Di Manning, President, Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women; and G. D. Richardson; with a copy of Congratulations Miss Arnot (State Library of NSW Press, 1993), being augmented reprint of her 1946 ABC broadcast, Should Both Sexes Receive Equal Pay for Equal Work ? (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/6)
1994; Papers concerning Jocelynne A. Scutt's book, Taking a Stand - Women in Politics and Society (Artemus Publishing Pty Ltd, 1994), including letters received from Jocelynne A. Scutt, 15 May 1994, concerning her essay on Jean Arnot in the book (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/6)

1950-1951, 1964-1965, 1979; Certificates concerning her appointment to MBE, 1965; her election to Fellow of the Library Association of Australia, 1964; her Honorary Membership of the Royal Australian Historical Society, 1979; and copy of her report, Library Facilities in New South Wales Government Institutions, 1950, with note, 1951 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/7X)

1976-1994; File concerning British Empire Association, including circular leters received and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1948-1989; Files (2) concerning the Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, including correspondence, membership lists, constitution and by-laws, material concerning the 40th anniversary of the Club, 1979; and the Club's study tour of Papua-New Guinea, 15-29 July 1968 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1985-1995; File concerning the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women Inc. Division of New South Wales, including correspondence, news bulletins, and constitution and by-laws (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1982-1995; File concerning the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women Inc., including correspondence and copies of Federation News (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1933-1937; File of Kooroora Literary and Debating Society magazine, being five volumes: 1932-33, 1933-34, 1934-35, 1935-36, 1936-37 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1980-1994; File concerning the National Council of Women Inc., including correspondence, circular letters received, material concerning Margaret Windeyer and report of the Womanhood Suffrage League of New South Wales, 1892 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1990-1995; File concerning National Council of Women of New South Wales Inc., being printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1978-1995; File concerning Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association, including circular letters received, reports and proceedings of the Association's 9th (Canberra, 1961), 13th (Seoul, 1975) and 15th (Saratoga Springs and New York, 1981) international conferences (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1955-1985; File concerning the Royal Australian Historical Society, including letters received from John Bennett, 1985, and D. I. McDonald, 1983; talks; copy of obituary of Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper by Hazel King; and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1967-1995; File concerning the Royal Australian Historical Society and its Library and Library Committee, including correspondence, newscuttings and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1960-1965; File concerning the Women's club, including correspondence, circular letters recived and annual reports (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/11)

ca. 1937-1991; Literary papers, being mainly notes and drafts of talks and speeches, with related correspondence and newscuttings. Topics and themes: Travel, ca. 1949-1972, date unknown; National Council of Women, 1963-1966, date unknown; Public Service, ca. 1942-1945; Internationalism, 1966-1967; Old Sydney, 1979-1991; Bibliotherapy - Libraries, ca. 1937-1971, including New Anglo-American Code for Australian Libraries, 1967; Dedications in Books, 1946, 1988, date unknown; Local History, 1970-1978 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/12)
1937-1990; Literary papers continued. Topics and themes: Status of Women in the Christian Church, 1968-1980; Women in Australia - Norman Mackenzie - Status of Women etc., 1945-1975, 1990; Australia Day &amp; Victoria League Coronation day, 1957-1984; 'Articles, etc &amp; Speeches ... Not Library', 1937-1975, 1989, including 'Equal Pay for Equal Work', 1937, Conference on Unemployment, 1961, Ruby Board, with prisoners' Christmas cards, 1949, and pamphlet on the opening of Berrima Training Centre, 1949; Reminiscences of a Cataloguer, 1981; The Australian Subscription Library and the Royal Australian Historical Society Library, 197--1982, date unknown; Early Australian Newspapers, Sydney Gazette, Hobart Town Gazette, 1989, date unknown; 'Speeches Miscellaneous' concerning, among other topics, Christmas, retirement, missionary work, the Big Sister Movement, Sydney Harbour, Captain Cook Bi-Centenary, BPW Club of Sydney study tour of Papua-New Guinea, 1968, and Soroptismy (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/13)

1926-1989, date unknown; Newscuttings concerning librarians and libraries, including obituary of Edith Alice Sims (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1934-1994; Newscuttings mainly concerning Jean Arnot, being four folders: no. 1, 1934-1953, with letter received from Lorelei booker; no. 2, 1953-1961; no. 3, 1961-1967; no. 4, 1968-1994 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1952-1995; Newscuttings on a range of topics, with letters received from Irina Dunn, 1990; Irene Greenwood, 1978, 1990; W. Boyd Rayward, 1992; and the Australian Stockman's Hall of Fame and Outback Heritage Centre, Longreach, Qld, 1990-1991 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1968-1994; Newscuttings mainly concerning librarians and libraries, with letters received from, among others, Alison Crook and Wilma radford; list of Kooroora Club members, 1968-1969; invitations; and copy of speech, 'Australia's Cultural Heritage', by Sir David Smith to the A.C.T. Branch of the Royal Commonwealth Society, 5 June 1992 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1988-1990; Newscuttings concerning the property, Belltrees, at Scone, N.S.W., owned by the Michael and Judy White (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)

192--197-; Miscellaneous papers, including letters received from Jean Arnot to family and friends, 9 Apr. 1948-7 Feb. 1949, and to her sisters, Gillian and Mary Arnot, and Alison McPherson, 6 Sep.-7 Dec. 1961; photocopied specimens of handwriting of Library staff who have contributed to entries in the card catalogues, 192--193-; passports (2), 1948 and 1961-1966, with enclosed identity card, 1942,; travel documents for Paris trip, 1961, and New Zealand trip, 1973; and unused postcards, 194--197- (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15)

1938-1990; Printed material, including order of proceedings of memorial ceremony for Emeritus Professor John Ward, AO, Patricia Ward, AM, Jennifer Ward and Moira Jennings at the Great Hall, University of Sydney, 21 June 1990, and of evening of tribute to Patricia Bruce Ward, AM, BA, DipED, FLAA, held at the State Library of NSW, 28 June 1990; and travel maps, 1938-198-, date unknown, including New South Wales Tourist Bureau regional maps, 1938 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Correspondence, diaries, Paper files and documents, Speeches, Printed material, Press cuttings</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00861.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Ruby Board</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Women's Column, <span style="font-style:italic">The Sydney Morning Herald</span>, 19 March 1925, p.5; <citation xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article16205434">http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article16205434</citation>.</repository>
<unittitle>Ruby Board</unittitle>
<unitdate>1925</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of the Sydney Morning Herald.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>