<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0945</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2004-05-04">2004-05-04</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Anne Heywood and Robin Secomb</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-08-14">2015-08-14</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0945b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Christian</part>
<part localType="givenname">Margaret Enid</part>
<part localType="honorific title">OAM</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1920-01-01">1920</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2012-07-14">14 July 2012</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Veterinarian</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Peg Christian was the first veterinarian to establish a private small animal practice in the Northern Territory; she practiced part-time in Alice Springs from 1948-1951. Later she helped pioneer the development of Wombaroo, a replacement milk formula for orphaned marsupials.</abstract>
<p>Peg Christian grew up on a sheep property near Yass. For her, an only child, the animals, especially horses, were her friends. She became a boarder, first at Frensham and then at Abbotsleigh independent girls schools. She was nineteen and studying Veterinary Science at Sydney University when her father died and the property was sold. Although her mother strongly believed in the education of girls, she did not consider that her nineteen year old daughter could run a sheep property. She was the twelfth woman in Australia to graduate in veterinary science. After graduation and before her marriage, she worked in a small animal practice on the North Shore. When her husband took up an appointment as a government laboratory veterinarian in Alice Springs, Christian opened her own private practice in the family home. In 1952, the family moved to Adelaide and again she started her private practice in the family home. Christian is best known for her work with native animals, especially joeys, wombats and kangaroos. She learnt by trial and error because care of native animals was not included in her studies at Sydney University. She was awarded the Medal of the Order of Australia on 26 January 1984. Voluntary work has always been important to Christian, from being a an air raid warden at Sydney University (during World War II), through the Country Women's Association (CWA) in Alice Springs, to the Girl Guides, the RSPCA, and Cleland Reserve in Adelaide. She retired from private practice when arthritis caused her to lose the feeling in her fingers. Peg Christian's philosophy is that humans are responsible for animals. They do not have dominion over them. She also believes strongly that if you want to change something you must become involved with it, without being too aggressive.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0787b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Country Women's Association of the Northern Territory (1961 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0762b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Girl Guides Australia (1926 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4284b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Abbotsleigh (1885 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Margaret Christian attended Abbotsleigh school</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-775063">
<relationEntry>
Christian, Margaret Enid (1920-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Christian, Margaret Enid (Peg)', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Christian, Margaret Enid (Peg)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0945b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001541.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Peg Christian [sound recording] Interviewer: Karen George</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Peg Christian [sound recording] Interviewer: Karen George</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 593/1</unitid>
<abstract>The Honoured Women Oral History Project Part II 

Peg Christian grew up on a sheep property near Yass. For her, an only child, the animals, especially horses, were her friends. Peg was nineteen and studying Veterinary Science at Sydney University when her father died and the property was sold. Although her mother strongly believed in the education of girls, she did not consider that her nineteen year old daughter could run a sheep property. Indeed, Peg Christian speculated that her mother always thought that her daughter' s veterinary work 'wasn't anything terribly important'. Peg Christian was a boarder, first at Frensham and then at Abbotsleigh independent girls schools. She reflected on the advantages of single sex schools and the Headmistress' support for her ambition to be a vet. Peg Christian recounts in detail the veterinary science curriculum, its strengths and weaknesses, the impact of World War II and the social life at Sydney University between 1938 and 1943. She was the twelfth woman in Australia to graduate in veterinary science. After graduation and before her marriage, she worked in a small animal practice on the North Shore. Peg Christian stressed the importance of treating the owners as well as their animals. When her husband took up an appointment as a government laboratory veterinarian in Alice Springs, Peg Christian opened her own private practice in the family home. For this she is featured in the Pioneer Women's Hall of Fame, Alice Springs. In 1952, the family moved to Adelaide and again Peg Christian started her private practice in the family home. Peg Christian is best known for her work with native animals, especially joeys, wombats and kangaroos. She learnt by trial and error because care of native animals was not included in her studies at Sydney University. As a pioneer in this work, Peg Christian's memories are a valuable record. She was awarded the Order of Australia Medal in 1984. Voluntary work has always been important to Peg Christian, from being a an air raid warden at Sydney University, through the CWA in Alice Springs, to the Girl Guides, the RSPCA, and Cleland Reserve in Adelaide. She retired from private practice when arthritis caused her to lose the feeling in her fingers. Peg Christian2s philosophy is that humans are responsible for animals. They do not have dominion over them. She also believes strongly that if you want to change something you must become involved with it, without being too aggressive. She reflected on modern day feminism.

Recorded on 12 &amp; 21 December 2000</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>4 cassettes</extent>
<physfacet>Digital audio tape</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>