<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE0908</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2004-04-20">2004-04-20</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Anne Heywood and Robin Secomb</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-08-14">2015-08-14</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0908b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Caw</part>
<part localType="givenname">Harriet Marjorie</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="maiden name"><part>Hubbe, Harriet</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1893-01-01">1893</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1993-12-31">1993</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Community worker</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Marjorie Caw was the fourth child of Edith Agnes Hubbe, née Cook, 1859-1942, a South Australian educator. Her father was killed in the Boer War and her mother opened a school at Knightsbridge. Caw trained as a kindergarten teacher and taught at Halifax Street and Bowden. She travelled to Europe with her mother and Miss George of the Advanced School for Girls. They returned home when World War I broke out. On their return Caw set up a kindergarten in their drawing room (at Knightsbridge) following the Montessori methods she had observed on her travels. At the same time she studied economics at the University of Adelaide under Professor Heaton. She married Alfred Caw and they moved to Western Australia to farm at Kojonup. Her son William was born one year later and then her daughter Virginia. They returned to Adelaide by ship each year to visit her family. On one of these visits in 1929 she joined the Lyceum Club. During the depression she formed a branch of the Country Women's Association (CWA) in Kojonup and over the years the branch helped many country people. She taught her children via correspondence school and sent her son to St Peter's in Adelaide to board. She and her daughter went to Denmark for a world conference of the CWA. In 1922 they sold the property to her brother and returned to Adelaide where she became involved in the Lyceum Club. The Club helped her celebrate her 90th birthday in 1983.</abstract>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0826b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Lyceum Club (Adelaide) Incorporated (1922 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-768052">
<relationEntry>
Caw, Harriet Marjorie (1893-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Caw, Harriet Marjorie', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Caw, Harriet Marjorie</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0908b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001492.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Beth M. Robertson</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Beth M. Robertson</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 31/3</unitid>
<unitdate>26 August 1979</unitdate>
<abstract>South Australian Women's Responses to the First World War 

Marjorie Caw, nee Hubbe, was 21 years old at the outbreak of the First World War and living in Knightsbridge with her mother, the eminent educationalist Edith Hubbe. Her father had been killed in the Boer War and Marjorie recalls his leaving and the letters he sent home. She also recounts in some detail how, after completing her kindergarten teaching training in Adelaide, she travelled extensively in Europe with her mother in the months before the war. On their return Marjorie set up a kindergarten in their drawing room following the Montessori methods she had observed on her travels. Mrs Caw reminisces at some length about her reactions to the First World War, including those brought on by her brothers' participation and some people's reaction to her family's German name.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 cassettes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001491.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Mary Hutchison</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Mary Hutchison</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 3/1</unitid>
<unitdate>1981</unitdate>
<abstract>Who was Edith Hubbe? 

Marjorie Caw was the fourth child of Edith Agnes Hubbe, nee Cook, 1859-1942, South Australian educator. In the first interview Mrs Caw speaks of the Hubbe household during her childhood, including her father's death in 1910. In the second interview Mrs Caw talks of her mother's career and interests.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 cassettes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001490.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Yvonne Abbott</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Harriet Marjorie Caw [sound recording] Interviewer: Yvonne Abbott</unittitle>
<unitid>SRG 438/29/34</unitid>
<unitdate>1988</unitdate>
<abstract>Adelaide Lyceum Club Oral History 

Marjorie Caw was born in 1893 into a Unitarian household. Her father was killed in the Boer War and her mother opened a school at Knightsbridge. Marjorie trained as a kindergarten teacher and taught at Halifax Street and Bowden. She travelled to Europe with her mother and Miss George of the Advanced School for Girls. They returned home when World War I broke out. Marjory started a Montessori School at Knightsbridge and studied economics at the University of Adelaide under Professor Heaton. She married Alred Caw and they moved to Western Australia to farm at Kojonup. Her son William was born one year later and then her daughter Virginia. They returned to Adelaide by ship each year to visit her family. On one of these visits in 1929 she joined the Lyceum Club. During the depression she formed a branch of the CWA in Kojonup and over the years the branch helped many country people. She taught her children via correspondence school and sent her son to St Peter's in Adelaide to board. She and her daughter went to Denmark for a world conference of the CWA. In 1922 they sold the property to her brother and returned to Adelaide where she became involved in the Lyceum Club. The Club helped her celebrate her 90th birthday in 1983.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 cassettes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>