<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE1825</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2006-01-24">2006-01-24</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Ann-Mari Jordens</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1825b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Cruz</part>
<part localType="givenname">Elba</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="maiden name"><part>Cruz-Zavalla, Elba</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="married name"><part>Valenzuela, Elba</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1945-12-09">9 December 1945</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Chepica, Chile</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Women's refuge worker</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Union activist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Elba was born into a strongly socialist working-class family in Chile, which became closely associated with the government of Savador Allende and was forced to flee Chile following his assassination. On settling in Canberra she instigated a strike of workers at the at the Health Services Supply Services laundry at Mitchell in 1987. In 1991 she joined the staff of the Beryl Women's Refuge, where she is still employed. She has assisted many Chilean refugees settle in Canberra and has been involved in a number of community organizations.</abstract>
<p>Elba Cruz was born in 1945 in Chepica, Chile, daughter of Leopoldo Cruz-Soto and Maria Magdalina Zavalla-Jimenes. Her father, a self-employed sharecropper and community leader, imbued her and her six siblings with strong sense of social justice and socialist and communist values.</p>
<p>Dyslexia impeded Elba's education and she left school at about 14 to help her mother in the home. At 18 she went to Santiago where she worked in a men's clothing factory, participated in union activities, and in 1969 married Leonardo Valenzuela Ramirez, a carpenter.</p>
<p>Elba and her husband worked to promote community development centres in suburbs and country towns under the Allende government, and two of her brothers became Allende's unofficial bodyguards. One of her brothers was at the Presidential Palace (Moneda) in November 1973 when Allende was assassinated. The other brother was at the Intedensia (the Santiago administration office). This brother was arrested and executed three days after the coup. The other brother who was at the Moneda in the morning of the coup was imprisoned, tortured, and released after four months.</p>
<p>Her husband was granted refuge in Argentina and Elba followed him with her three small children in November 1974. They lived there for three years under UN protection and another child was born, before the family was accepted as refugees by Australia in 1977. They settled initially in Adelaide, then came to Canberra, where her husband worked as a carpenter and she studied English.</p>
<p>In the early 1980s Elba worked as cook, a cleaner in a hotel and hospital, and as a casual worker at the Health Services Supply Services laundry at Mitchell. In 1987 she initiated a successful three week strike over employment conditions at the laundry, and subsequently became the union representative there. After six years she developed RSI and was forced to seek less physically demanding work.</p>
<p>In 1991 she joined the staff of the Beryl Women's Refuge, where she is still employed. She has assisted many Chilean refugees settle in Canberra and has been involved in a number of community organizations such as the Chilean Solidarity Committee, a support organization for Argentinean refugees, the Chilean broadcasting program on 2XX and ANESBWA (Association of Non-English-Speaking Background Women of Australia).</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1824b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Exhibition">
Australian In My Difference: Women and Migration in Australia Since 1945
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-733051">
<relationEntry>
Cruz, Elba (1945-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Cruz, Elba', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Cruz, Elba</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1825b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004466.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Sound recording: Migrant women in the workforce [sound recording] : an oral history series documenting the working lives of migrant women in Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">National Ethnic and Multicultural Broadcaster's Council</name>
<title render="italic">Migrant women in the workforce [sound recording] : an oral history series documenting the working lives of migrant women in Australia</title>
<imprint>
<place>Collingwood, Vic</place>
<publisher>NEMBC</publisher>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001971.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Elba Cruz-Zavalla interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens [sound recording]. Recorded on July 20, 2005 at Canberra, A.C.T.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Oral History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Elba Cruz-Zavalla interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens [sound recording]. Recorded on July 20, 2005 at Canberra, A.C.T.</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 5489</unitid>
<unitdate>1950 - 2005</unitdate>
<abstract>Elba Cruz-Zavalla, born in 1945 in Chepika, Chile, talks about her early life and her family background; her father's strong sense of social justice, socialist and communist values; her dyslexia; leaving school early to help her mother in the home; at 18 going to Santiago where she worked in a men's clothing factory; participating in union activities; in 1969 marrying Valenzuela Ramirez, a carpenter; how she and her husband worked to promote community development centres in suburbs and country towns under the Allende government; her two brothers who became Allende's unofficial bodyguards; the assassination of Allende at the Presidential Palace in November 1973; one brother being executed after the coup; her other brother being imprisoned and released after four months; her husband being granted refuge in Argentina; following him with her three small children in November 1974.
Cruz-Zavalla speaks about living in Argentina for three years under UN protection; having another child ; the family being accepted as refugees by Australia in 1977; settling initially in Adelaide, then coming to Canberra; her husband working as a carpenter; studying English; working as cook, a cleaner in a hotel and hospital and as a casual worker at the Health Services Supply Services laundry at Mitchell; initiating a successful three -week strike over employment conditions at the laundry in 1987, and subsequently became the union representative there; after six years developing RSI and being forced to seek less demanding work; in 1991 joining the staff of the Beryl Women's Refuge; assisting Chilean refugees settle in Canberra; her involvement in a number of community organizations such as the Chilean Solidarity Committee, a support organization for Argentinean refugees; the Chilean broadcasting program on 2XX and Association of Non-English-Speaking Background Women of Australia (ANESBWA).</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>4 Sound files</extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00302.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Portrait of Elba Cruz-Zavalla during her visit to the National Library of Australia on the 20 July 2005</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia. Used with permission.</repository>
<unittitle>Portrait of Elba Cruz-Zavalla during her visit to the National Library of Australia on the 20 July 2005</unittitle>
<unitdate>2005</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Item Held at the National Library of Australia. See catalogue record for copyright restrictions</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>