<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE1110</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2004-11-05">2004-11-05</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Rosemary Francis</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1110b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, Sydney</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1927-01-01">1927</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1994-12-31">1994</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>End Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Membership organisation</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Girls' Secondary Schools' Club was formed in Sydney in 1927, registered under that name in 1928 and incorporated as a limited liability company. It provided a meeting place in the city for members of the ex-student unions of, initially, ten independent girls' schools. Membership rose from 400 in 1928 to 1800 after World War II. The club rooms were initially located in Castlereagh Street until 1930, when the Club relocated to the Gowings building in Market Street, Sydney, where it remained until its closure, due to falling membership and increased costs, in 1994.</abstract>
<p>The Club operated a number of circles such as the Dramatic Circle, the Art Circle, the Debating Circle, the Literary Circle, the Music Circle, and during World War II, the War Work Circle. The Social Committee arranged functions and outings for members. In 1977 the Club published Edith Gent's history of the Club entitled 'Fifty years in retrospect: a history of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club Sydney 1927-1977'.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-764050">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, Sydney', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, Sydney</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1110b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001876.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, Sydney - records, 1927-1994</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, Sydney - records, 1927-1994</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 7061</unitid>
<unitdate>1927 - 1994</unitdate>
<abstract>I. MINUTE BOOKS, 1927-1994
1927-1994; Minutes books (11) of the Board of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/1-5)
1929-1969; Minute books (6) of the Social Committee (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/6)
1930-1966; Minute books (4) of the House Committee (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/6)
1970-1974; Minute book (1) of the Management Committee (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/7)
1993-1994; Minute book (1) of the Executive Committee (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/7)
1964-1982; Minute books (4) of the Travellers Circle (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/7)
1946-1947; Minute book (1) of the Social Service Circle (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/7)
1940-1946; Minute book (1) of the War Work Fund (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/7)

II. FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1927-1983
1983; Valuation of furniture, furnishings and effects of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club as at 30 May 1983 (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/8)
1971-1993; Auditors' reports and balance sheets of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/8)
1927-1935; Cash books (2) of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/9)
1928-1960; Journal (1) recording monthly cash summaries (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/9)
1951-1986; Lease agreements, being signed lease agreements between the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club and Gowing Bros. Limited concerning the rental of premises at 45 Market Street Sydney (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/9)
1931; Insurance policy, being an employers' indemnity policy for the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/9)

III. CORRESPONDENCE, 1929-1994
1929-1931; Secretary's correspondence (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/10)
1933-1994; Correspondence, being mainly ts. and ms. letters received, including a letter of thanks from Sir Winston Churchill for an 80th birthday gift sent to him by members of the Club, 1954, previously framed and located in the Club, [copy at MLMSS 7061/11;original held at Safe 3/239] (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)
1971-1990; Correspondence concerning music scholarships awarded by the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)
1970-ca.1992; Christmas cards received, being mainly signed Christmas cards received from Governors of New South Wales (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)

IV. PAPERS, 1928-1994
1928; Certificate of Incorporation of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)
1947;1967; Memorandum and Articles of Association (3) of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, 1947 and By-laws of the Club, 1967 (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)
1956-1972; Annual Report and Financial Statements of the Girls' Secondary Schools Club, being printed leaflets (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11)
1928-1993; Reports to the Annual General Meeting, being ms. and ts. reports presented to the annual meeting of members of the Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/11-12)
1969-1994; Notice to members, being ts. and printed notices and letters sent to members (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/12)
1944-1981; 'Syllabus', being calendar of events sent to members (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/12)
1994; Papers concerning voluntary liquidation of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1992-1994; Attendance records of the Board of Directors (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1948; 'Resume of Club's History', being ts. and printed leaflet outlining history of Club up until 1948 (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1948; Schoolgirl Short Story Competition, being prize winning entries (2) in short story competition run by the Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1983-1991; Records of the Embroidery Group (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1990-1992; Papers concerning donations to the Sir David Martin Foundation (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/13)
1927-1927; Address book of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1983-1994; Visitors Book of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1928-1994; Membership records of Miss Dorcas Bibbing, including letter acknowledging receipt of fees and subscription, 1928; membership cards, 1928-1994;invitations, 1948-1967; receipts, 1928 (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1990-1992; Miscellaneous papers (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1931-1993; Newscuttings (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)

V. PICTORIAL MATERIAL, Date unknown
Date unknown; Black and white photographic portraits of Presidents of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club, including Mrs R.J. Hooton (1927-1928); Mrs J.H. Hammond (1928-1932); Mrs F.H. Jackson (1932-1933); Mrs G.S. Warburton (1933-1935); Miss Frances Gillespie (1935-1961; unidentified studio portrait of woman and child (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)

VI. PRINTED MATERIAL, 1948-1994
1948; Girls' Secondary Schools' Club Sydney: Record of War Work, ed. Ina K. Tait, being printed booklet (2) recording the activities of the War Work Committee (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1977; Fifty years in retrospect: A history of the Girls' Secondary Schools' Club Sydney 1927-1977, compiled by Edith Gent, 3 copies (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)
1994; Girls' Secondary Schools' Club Sydney: Diary of events, compiled Patricia Grayson, being printed booklet (Locn No.: MLMSS 7061/14)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.291 m, 14 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>