<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE2137</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2006-06-18">2006-06-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Nikki Henningham</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-08-28">2015-08-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2137b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Bekas</part>
<part localType="givenname">Anastasia</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1939-01-01">c. 1939</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Komi, Peleponese, Greece</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Anastasia Bekas was born in Greece in the late 1930s, the youngest of four children. She liked school and was a good student, her teachers encouraged her to attend high school. Unfortunately, she could not live this dream because, as was customary at the time, she had to leave school because her help was required to run the farm. She was a good, hard worker, but in the end her father encouraged her to migrate to Australia, as a way of avoiding the dowry he would eventually have to supply should she stay in Greece. The Australian government was keen to attract single Greek girls to the country at this time. As long as she had somewhere to stay, they would pay her fare. 'You are healthy, you are going to Australia', she was told. 'So I have to go.'

She migrated to Australia, where her sister already lived, in December 1963 and arrived in Adelaide, where she would settle, on January 14, 1964. Adjustment was difficult, with the lack of English language skills being the major problem.</abstract>
<p>Anastasia, like millions of other women who arrived in the waves of post war migration, had few skills, little, if any English but a strong desire to work. In the 1960s and 70s, when when the provision of post-arrival migrant services and programs was demonstratively inadequate, this combination was a neverending source of frustration for women who wanted to make a contribution. Anastasia describes this frustration in an interview done for the Thebartson Community Arts Network Project:</p>
<p>'My sister said that young people were being brought here to help the country prosper. I couldn't speak English, it was hard when my family wasn't there to help me. My brother in law could speak English a bit. I wanted to work but he said it would be hard with no English. He helped me go to Social Security but I had to go to the interview by myself on the bus. I didn't know how much to pay on the bus, the conductor took the right money from my hand. I didn't understand anything at the office - they sent me home. I cried and cried. Then I got a lettter telling me I had to go to school to learn English. I went to Thebarton Primary School two nights a week but we only learned words like <span style="font-style:italic">bread, water, hello</span>. I wanted to learn words that would help me to get a job. I had to persuade our teacher to teach these words.'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2181b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Exhibition">
Being Seen And Heard: Migrant Women Organising In Australia, A Documentary History (2006 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2134b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Concept">
Greece Born Community of Australia
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-764093">
<relationEntry>
Bekas, Anastasia (1939-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Bekas, Anastasia', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Bekas, Anastasia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2137b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003665.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Postcards from home : a celebration of departures and arrivals - voices of women from non English speaking backgrounds</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Thebarton Community Arts Network</name>
<title render="italic">Postcards from home : a celebration of departures and arrivals - voices of women from non English speaking backgrounds</title>
<imprint>
<place>Thebarton</place>
<publisher>Thebarton Community Arts Network</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001989.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Postcards from Home: Interviews with Thebarton Women from Non-English Speaking Backgrounds [sound recording]/Interviewers: Members of Thebarton Community Arts Network</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia, Mortlock Library of South Australiana</repository>
<unittitle>Postcards from Home: Interviews with Thebarton Women from Non-English Speaking Backgrounds [sound recording]/Interviewers: Members of Thebarton Community Arts Network</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 349</unitid>
<unitdate>1994</unitdate>
<abstract>A series of six interviews conducted by members of the Thebarton Community Arts Network with local women of non-English speaking backgrounds. The interviews were the first stage of a community arts project in which interviewees collaborated with interviewers to produce lino prints which represented aspects of their migration and settlement experiences. The project culminated in an exhibition at the Fig Gallery, Thebarton during November and December 1994. A catalogue of the interviews and prints was launched at another exhibition of the prints during the 1996 Adelaide Festival of Arts. Not all of the project's interviews are represented in the J. D. Somerville Oral History Collection.
4 hours 52 minutes</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>8 Cassette Tapes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00188.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">My Wedding Day, by Angela Bekas</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>My Wedding Day, by Angela Bekas</unittitle>
<unitid>Theabarton Community Arts Network</unitid>
<unitdate>1991 - 1994</unitdate>
<abstract>Reproduction of a lino print created as a part of a larger project to collect migrant women's stories in Adelaide, South Australia. <span style="font-style:italic">My Wedding Day</span> represents two significant ceremonies in the artist's life, her marriage and her proud declaration of Australian Citizenship. The back ground patterns are taken from hand embroidered linens she made for her dowry before emigrating.</abstract>
<physdesc>Photograph of a Photograph, taken 2006-06-16<geogname>Thebarton, South Australia</geogname>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>