<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE2096</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2006-05-04">2006-05-04</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Barbara Lemon</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-31">2014-07-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2096b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Bancroft</part>
<part localType="givenname">Robyne</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Aboriginal heritage consultant</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Gumbaingerri born of Bundjalung/Thungutti descent, Robyne Bancroft's people come from the northeast coast of New South Wales. For four generations since colonisation, her family (matrilineally) have passed on their genealogies and oral traditions.</abstract>
<p>Robyne Bancroft is a Goori Australian woman who has done much to bolster and broaden the identity of Aborigines, Archaeology and women in the ACT area and beyond. Gumbaingerri born of Bundjalung/Thungutti descent, Bancroft's people come from the northeast coast of New South Wales.</p>
<p>Proudly stemming from a strong matrilineal line, she is part of her family's fourth generation of women on the matrilineal side since colonisation who continue their genealogies and oral traditions. While early white male anthropologists sought to learn about the lives of Aborigines by consulting solely with men, a whole female tradition was neglected. In the 1960s Bancroft's grandmother, born in 1905 and fluent in three dialects, encouraged her to tell the tales to keep their traditions alive:</p>
<p>'Now, they come to ask us our stories - now, when most of us have forgotten so much. We have been so caught up in living day to day, and now there are very few of us left. Look who's here - only three or four of us left. It's time for you to come home my girl, keep our stories going, and take over doing what I do - talking to everyone about Goori people and our heritage.'</p>
<p>Perhaps tackling the field of archeology and anthropology was a further way Bancroft could follow her grandmother's wishes and spread the ways of her people. Even if this meant undertaking studies at the Australian National University as a mature age, single mother with a family, she was not to be deterred.</p>
<p>Through her academic pursuits and as an Indigenous heritage consultant, Robyne Bancroft has striven to improve the understanding of Indigenous Australians by facilitating communication and consultation. Becoming a founding member of the Indigenous Archaeological Association (IAA), an independent archaeological body that represents the interests of indigenous archaeologists and provides a voice for Aboriginal people on archaeological issues is one such example. Her role as an Aboriginal Cultural Heritage Officer with Forests NSW is another. Creating active consultation between State Forests and Aboriginal communities has aimed to develop systems that better consider the landscape context of sites, thereby offering more efficient protection with the concurrent benefit of Aboriginal communities becoming more fundamentally involved in decision making.</p>
<p>Bancroft strongly believes including Aboriginal people in consultative processes is the most effective way to develop policy which is most beneficial to Aboriginal Australians. Her positions on several cultural heritage committees, as the Aboriginal Representative on the International Council of Monuments and Sites (ICOMOS) and her involvement in repatriation of ancestral human remains are some of the ways Bancroft contributes to a more holistic approach to Aboriginal Indigenous cultural heritage. As a founding member of the ACT Heritage Council and of the Multifunctional Aboriginal Children's Services (MACS), Australians for Reconciliation Coordinator for the ACT and region and as an adviser on indigenous issues to the ACT Chief Minister, Robyne Bancroft has contributed greatly to dialogue within the Canberra region and beyond.</p>
<p>As the cultural editor of <span style="font-style:italic">The Oxford Companion to Aboriginal Art and Culture</span>, Robyne Bancroft has helped define Aboriginal heritage and identity for a worldwide audience and is widely sowing the stories of her people.</p>
<p><span style="font-weight:bold">This entry was prepared by Roslyn Russell, Museum Services, and funded by the ACT Heritage Unit.</span></p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0785b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Exhibition">
Women in the making of Canberra
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-513344">
<relationEntry>
Bancroft, Robyne
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Bancroft, Robyne', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Bancroft, Robyne</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2096b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003606.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Archaeologists and Aborigines Working Together</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Iain Davidson, Christine Lovell-Jones and Robyne Bancroft</name>
<title render="italic">Archaeologists and Aborigines Working Together</title>
<imprint>
<place>Armidale, NSW</place>
<publisher>University of New England Press</publisher>
<date>1995</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003605.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: The Oxford Companion to Aboriginal Art and Culture</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Sylvia Kleinert, Margo Neale and Robyne Bancroft</name>
<title render="italic">The Oxford Companion to Aboriginal Art and Culture</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
<date>2000</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00907.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Portrait of Robyne Bancroft</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia, an20549082. Used with permission.</repository>
<unittitle>Portrait of Robyne Bancroft</unittitle>
<abstract>Taken in the 1990s.</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>