<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE2169</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2006-08-25">2006-08-25</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Ann-Mari Jordens</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2169b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Osmani</part>
<part localType="givenname">Gyzele</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Qazimi, Gyzele</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1970-05-12">12 May 1970</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Ternovc, East Kosovo, Serbia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Student</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Refugee advocate</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Gyzele Osmani fled Kosovo in 1999 with her husband and five small children. Accepting temporary refuge in Australia she was housed in the Bandiana Safe Haven where her youngest daughter received medical treatment for a dislocated hip. Refusing repatriation in March 2000 because the situation in the Presevo Valley was unsafe and her daughter needed further medical treatment, the family was interned for seven months in the Port Hedland Detention Centre before being released to settle in Canberra. Now an Australian citizen, Gyzele is studying Business Administration and her story is the subject of a prize-winning essay and radio program.</abstract>
<p>Gyzele Osmani was born on 15 May 1970 in East Kosovo, Serbia, in the village of Ternovc , Bujanovc community , in the Presevo Valley, to Albanian Muslim parents. Her father was a farmer and she had three sisters and two brothers. She left school in Year 8 when she was 14, as the local high school was converted into a military barracks. She was helped by a tutor who lent her books and taught her Serbian and a little English. She then trained as a dressmaker. In 1991, when she was 21, she married Qenan Osmani a local carpenter and upholsterer, and by 1997 had five children, the last of whom were twins born in July 1997.</p>
<p>In May 1999 the Serbian soldiers blockaded the village, conducted a house-to house search and ordered the people to leave. Gyzele and her family walked for eight hours to Macedonia. When she finally reached a UN camp she discovered the hip of her baby daughter, Albinota, had been dislocated from being carried so long. She wanted medical help for her as soon as possible so accepted Australia's offer of asylum, not realising it was only intended to be temporary.<br />
She arrived in Australia on 15 July 1999 and after five days in a camp in East Hills, Sydney, was taken to the Bandiana Safe Haven in the Albury-Wodonga area. Albinota had three unsuccessful operations on her hip over the next ten months.</p>
<p>On 3 March 2000 the Albanian refugees in Bandiana were told they would be repatriated as the United Nations had restored order in Kosovo. The thirty Albanians who, like Gyzele were from the Presevo region in Serbia where the UN had not intervened, knew it was not safe to return and refused to return. On 15 April 2000 twenty-one Albanians were sent from Bandiana to the Port Hedland Detention Centre. After seven months there, she and her family were released on the decision the Minister for Immigration, Philip Ruddock, following intervention from Canberra migration agent Marion Le and other Canberra-based refugee supporters, who also helped her family rebuild their lives in Canberra. She and her family were granted permanent residence in Australia on 15 May 2001 and are now Australian citizens.</p>
<p>Gyzele is studying Business Administration at the Canberra Institute of Technology and takes every opportunity to tell her story of life in detention in the hope of helping other detainees, particularly children. Her story has the subject of a prize- winning essay by Melanie Poole, and an Australian Broadcasting Corporation's Radio Eye program, which won the 2003 Human Rights Radio Award.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1228b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Lê, Marion (1947 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Marion Lê helped Gyzele Osmani and her family gain their release form the Port Hedland Detention Centre, which eventually led to them getting permanent residency in Australia.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-768053">
<relationEntry>
Osmani, Gyzele (1970-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Osmani, Gyzele', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Osmani, Gyzele</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2169b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003699.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: The Place You Cannot Imagine</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Redfern, Lea</name>
<title render="italic">The Place You Cannot Imagine</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>ABC Soundprint</publisher>
<date>2004</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://soundprint.org/radio/display_show/ID/216/name/The+Place+You+Cannot+Imagine"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003698.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: The Place Where God Died. Gyzele's story.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Poole, Melanie</name>
<title render="quoted">The Place Where God Died. Gyzele's story.</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Refugee Action Committee, Canberra</publisher>
<date>2002c</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.refugeeaction.org/stories/gyzele.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002018.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Gyzele Osmani interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens [sound recording]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Oral History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Gyzele Osmani interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens [sound recording]</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 5642</unitid>
<unitdate>1970 - 2006</unitdate>
<abstract>Gyzele Osmani, born 1970 in East Kosovo, Serbia, talks about her early life; the dispersal of Albanians and life in her village; the effect of the political situation on the education of Albanian Muslims by 1984; her marriage and her five children; a blockade of the village by the Serbian army (May 1999); leaving the village and walking towards Macedonia; conditions in the United Nations refugee camp; Macedonian Red Cross; the children becoming sick; her daughter's dislocated hip being diagnosed; meeting with Australian representatives but not understanding that Australia was only offering temporary protection; travelling to Australia with 400 other Albanians; the East Hills camp; contacting the doctors in Bandiana Safe Haven about her daughter's hip; the journey to Albury-Wodonga, the facilities there; her daughter's treatment in Wodonga hospital; being told on 3 March 2000 by the DIMIA that they had to leave Australia; Philip Ruddock's earlier visit to Bandiana (1999); Michelle Harris; pressure from the Dept. of Immigration to leave the Bandiana Safe Haven; Bandiana becoming a detention centre (2000), how it changed.
Osmani discusses the family's removal to Port Hedland, WA and the conditions in the camp; the system of numbering the refugees; getting to know the other refugees; the two mosques in the Centre; the playground equipment; schooling; the staff; the medical treatment available in Port Hedland; her family's health problems; keeping a diary (in Albanian); the isolation block in Port Hedland; psychiatric problems amongst the other refugees; how they got out of Port Hedland; how other Albanians from Presevo were repatriated; Michelle Harris; Marion Le; the people who helped her; John Molony and Janet Mathews from the Kingston Baptist Church; her depression; speaking out in the media; being told of their release following Ministerial intervention; arrival in Canberra; first impressions of Canberra; permanent residency; studying English; her daughter's hip and the need for a further operation; how her children have been affected by their time in detention; the Albanian community; her first job; studying Business Administration (2005); Melanie Poole; her story being published in a book by Eva Salis; speaking at a protest rally in Canberra against detention; SBS Insight Program (October 2001); the ABC Radio Eye program which won the 2003 Human Rights Radio Award; wanting to tell her story; her hopes for the future.

Timed summary available
Recorded May 2006.
5 Sound files - approx 273 minutes</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound files</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>