<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE2894</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2007-11-28">2007-11-28</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Barbara Lemon and Nikki Henningham</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-16">2013-09-16</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2894b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Moore</part>
<part localType="givenname">Winifred</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="pen name"><part>Verity</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<toDate standardDate="1952-11-11">11 November 1952</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>England</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Brisbane, Queensland, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Print journalist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Winifred Moore was a prominent Brisbane journalist in the early twentieth century. She edited the women's section of The <span style="font-style:italic">Brisbane Courier</span> (later <span style="font-style:italic">Courier-Mail</span>), from the early 1920s through to the 1940s, and remained with the newspaper as a columnist until the early 1950s. In addition to her literary and arts interests, Moore was a founding member of the National Parks Association of Queensland. Although generally politically conservative, she had a keen interest in women's affairs and a range of social welfare issues of the day.</abstract>
<p>Winifred Moore was born in England but moved to Queensland (probably after both her parents died) to be raised by her elder sister in Ingham, North Queensland. She was a teacher of music, and travelled to her students by sulky. During the First World War, Moore joined the staff of the <span style="font-style:italic">Daily Mail</span>. In 1921, she was appointed Social Editress of the <span style="font-style:italic">Brisbane Courier</span> (later the <span style="font-style:italic">Brisbane Courier-Mail</span>). For two decades, Moore edited the women's section for the paper, contributing her own anecdotes and observations in her column, 'Between Ourselves', under the pseudonym 'Verity'. She remained a columnist for the paper until the early 1950s, and was responsible for the expansion of the <span style="font-style:italic">Courier-Mail</span> Christmas Toy Fund.</p>
<p>Under Moore in the 1920s, the weekly women's section of the <span style="font-style:italic">Brisbane Courier</span> - 'Home Circle' - combined London gossip, Paris fashion, recipes, poems and riddles, serialised novels, cartoons, domestic tips, news of Australians abroad, a children's section, and a 'how-to' column with instructions for making everything from knitted slippers to 'a pretty cretonne work-box which can be used also as a seat'. The section also included a political column of sorts, profiling prominent public personalities - from statesmen to sportsmen - in Australia and overseas. In November 1922, Sir Walter Edward Davidson, governor of New South Wales, was listed alongside the 'picturesque and romantic figure' of the Maharajah of Jaipur.</p>
<p>Moore used her own column to discuss topical questions around women in parliament, women and marriage, and women's organisations, or to offer personal anecdotes and tips in domestic economy. An early column discussed the proposed introduction of a League of Skilled Housecraft in England which, if successful, might be emulated in Queensland. Women could sit for an examination to demonstrate elementary knowledge of general housework skills (cooking, needlework etc), and go on to sit an advanced exam to receive a diploma, and full membership of the League: 'It is believed that such a hallmark of efficiency will go far towards giving such women the status of their sisters who are certificated teachers or district nurses', wrote Moore.</p>
<p>By the 1950s, the <span style="font-style:italic">Courier-Mail</span>'s 'Women's Interests' section was a far more splashy affair, dominated by photographs of women engaged, married or going abroad. Its editor complained that 'the ranks of Brisbane's society girls are thinning out so quickly with the steady stream making for England, that soon it will be necessary to go overseas just to find out what Brisbane people are doing'. Pages were dedicated, magazine-style, to society gossip and fashion. A caption in February 1950 described the 'unusual fashion accessory' of one Mrs. John Down, who arrived at a supper party wearing a 'fascinating cloche hat, complete with a full-size bird draped under her chin'. By this time Moore was no longer heading the section, but she continued to submit a weekly column on Wednesdays entitled 'Speaking for Women'. Again, her discussion was wide-ranging. One week Moore was writing about the shortage of trained nurses, or the need for women to assert themselves in the workplace, and the next, she was illuminating her readers on the subject of vice-regal etiquette and how to present oneself.</p>
<p>According to historian Patience Thoms, Winifred Moore 'wrote as a woman, not a feminist, but as one conscious of the contribution women could make if they had the will'.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1920-01-01">c. 1920</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1950-12-31">c. 1950</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Career in journalism active</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-744071">
<relationEntry>
Moore, Winifred
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Moore, Winifred', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Moore, Winifred</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2894b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004001.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: They Wrote as Women</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Thoms, Patience</name>
<title render="quoted">They Wrote as Women</title>
<imprint>
<place>Nathan, QLD</place>
<publisher>Australian Institute for Women's Research and Policy, Griffith University</publisher>
<date>1994</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Women in History: Places of Purpose</title>
<name type="author">Peg Penberthy and Pam Liddle</name>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004262.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cal/cal-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004440.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: AustLit: The Australian Literature Resource</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">AustLit: The Australian Literature Resource</title>
<imprint>
<date>2002</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.austlit.edu.au/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>