<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE2124</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2006-06-14">2006-06-14</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Nikki Henningham</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2124b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Office of Multicultural Affairs</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1987-01-01">1987</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1995-12-31">1995</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Government agency</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Office of Multicultural Affairs (OMA) was a division of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet. It was established early in 1987 to advise the Prime Minister directly on issues relating to Australian multicultural society.  The purpose of the office was to be that of  a 'bridge-builder', linking community and government to further the policy of multiculturalism. To that end, it had a liaison and Community Information Branch and a Policy and Research Branch.  The focus of the community information program was on building upon research undertaken and evaluating ongoing projects. Although most staff were located in Canberra, there  were  Regional Coordinators in each State and in the Northern Territory, so there was some attention to decentralised services.

In early 1995 the functions of the OMA were to be transferred to the Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs.  For administration purposes, OMA officially ceased to be part of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet on 26 January 1995.</abstract>
<p>The Office of Multicultural Affairs aimed to:</p>
<list><item>Promote acceptance of and respect for cultural differences;</item>
<item>Improve communication between community groups and Government;</item>
<item>Ensure equal access and equity for all groups to government services and programs, including health, social welfare, employment, training and education;</item>
<item>Develop a National Agenda of practical long-term strategies for multiculturalism;</item>
<item>Advise Government on multicultural programs and services after consultation with community groups;</item>
<item>Provide information on multicultural policies.</item></list>
<p>The OMA's first head, Peter Shergold, adopted the view that, as a bridgebuilder, the agency would be best served by appointing community workers to the regional coordinators' positions. It is said that he believed that is was easier to teach community advocates how to be bureaucrats than it was to teach bureaucrats how to liaise with the community. This type of thinking led to Beryl Mulder being appointed to the position of Regional Coordinator for the Northern Territory. It also led to innovative programs, such as employing bilingual officers to run the OMA's consultative programs. This meant that consultations could be managed in community languages, but reports could be written in English. This process resulted in a series of Policy Options Papers, many of which informed debate about access and equity to services for women of culturally and linguistically diverse backgrounds.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2120b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Mulder, Beryl (1941 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Beryl Mulder was the Regional Coordinator of the Office of Multicultural Affairs (OMA) for the Northern Territory from 1988 until 1995, when the OMA's activities were absorbed by the Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs (DIEA). She continued to work for the DIEA as a community and multicultural affairs liaison officer until 2000 but found the work environment and culture less to her liking than when she worked for the OMA.</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-491420">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Office of Multicultural Affairs', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Office of Multicultural Affairs</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE2124b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003671.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Dr Peter Shergold, Foundation Director of the Office of Multicultural Affairs, looks at the role of the Office, and ethnic support.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Shergold, Peter</name>
<title render="quoted">Dr Peter Shergold, Foundation Director of the Office of Multicultural Affairs, looks at the role of the Office, and ethnic support.</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Office of the Board Of Studies New South Wales</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Making Multicultural Australia</title>
<name type="author">and Training; Information Services Branch of the Office of the Board of Studies NSW. Multicultural Programs Unit of the Department of Education</name>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.multiculturalaustralia.edu.au/library/library.php?mediaCode=vid&amp;mode=Category&amp;myOption=Interview"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003629.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Issues for non-English speaking background women in Multicultural Australia/ Australian Office of Multicultural Affairs Policy Options Papers Series</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Eliadis, Maria; Colanaro Rosetta and Roussos, Patricia</name>
<title render="italic">Issues for non-English speaking background women in Multicultural Australia/ Australian Office of Multicultural Affairs Policy Options Papers Series</title>
<imprint>
<place>Canberra</place>
<publisher>Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet</publisher>
<date>1988</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">National Agenda for a Multicultural Australia</title>
<name type="author">Association of Non-English Speaking Background Women of Australia and the Office of Multicultural Affairs</name>
<num type="pages">47</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001984.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Correspondence files, Department of Prime Minister &amp; Cabinet, annual single number series</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Archives of Australia, Sydney Office</repository>
<unittitle>Correspondence files, Department of Prime Minister &amp; Cabinet, annual single number series</unittitle>
<unitid>P2681</unitid>
<unitdate>May 1988 - Jan 1995</unitdate>
<abstract>This series consists of correspondence files of the Office of Multicultural Affairs in Tasmania.  They detail the liaison of the Office with the Central Office of the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet and with the State Government, Tasmanian ethnic groups and other agencies.  Upon closing of the Office in 1995 the files were transferred to the Department of Immigration and Ethnic Affairs. Information found on file includes administration of Committees and projects, information from outside agencies and groups, planning matters, reports and miscellaneous correspondence, finance matters, requests for information, staffing, accommodation, stores and services matters and policies and issues relating to the ethnic communities of Tasmania. There are no known index cards for this series.
These records were originally held in the Hobart office of the NAA and were transferred to the NAA, Chester Hill, NSW in February 2005.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Paper files and documents</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00194.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">The Prime Minister, Bob Hawke, and Staff of the Office for Multicultural Affairs at the launch of the National Agenda for a Multicultural Society in 1989</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>The Prime Minister, Bob Hawke, and Staff of the Office for Multicultural Affairs at the launch of the National Agenda for a Multicultural Society in 1989</unittitle>
<unitid>Dr Sev Ozdowski</unitid>
<unitdate>1989</unitdate>
<physdesc>Photograph of a Photograph<geogname>Canberra</geogname>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>