<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE3801</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2008-10-31">2008-10-31</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Barbara Lemon</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3801b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Haussegger</part>
<part localType="givenname">Virginia</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1964-03-01">March 1964</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Melbourne, Victoria, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Print journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Television journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Radio journalist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Virginia Haussegger has been presenter of the ABC Canberra News since 2001. She began work as a cadet journalist with the ABC in 1986. Haussegger won the United Nations Association of Australia Media Peace Prize for her coverage of Indigenous Affairs in 1996.</abstract>
<p>Virginia Haussegger is the daughter of Kálmàn Haussegger, an engineer whose own father migrated to Australia from Germany in 1901. Her parents met and married in Melbourne. Virginia was educated in Burwood, then Bulleen, and finally Eltham, at the Catholic Ladies' College. She spent a year on exchange in Mexico in 1981, where she developed a fascination with Pre-Columbian art. She undertook tertiary studies at the University of Melbourne, majoring in English and Fine Arts.</p>
<p>In 1986, Haussegger successfully applied for a cadetship with the Australian Broadcasting Commission (ABC), and began in television news. At that time, she remembers, there were no more than five senior women in senior reporting or presenting positions on television. After a term in the Victorian Press Gallery as a political reporter for ABC News, Haussegger joined the <span style="font-style:italic">7.30 Report</span> in Melbourne. By 1987 she was presenting the program's Darwin edition, but returned to Melbourne two years later to be with her husband. A brief stint on Channel 7 with Steve Vizard ended in conflict and a legal battle, and she returned to the ABC.</p>
<p>In 1992, Haussegger joined Channel 9 as a reporter on <span style="font-style:italic">A Current Affair</span>, working with Mike Willesee, Jana Wendt and Ray Martin. In this role, she broke a story on The Children of God, a sect now referred to as The Family. The story resulted in a raid on sect houses by Victoria Police, after which 60 children were taken into protective custody.</p>
<p>Haussegger left Channel 9 in 1994 and moved to Adelaide the following year, where she presented the South Australian edition of the <span style="font-style:italic">7.30 Report</span>. When the program was centralised, Haussegger joined the new team in Sydney as national 'social affairs' reporter. In 1996, one of her stories - documenting the work of Magistrate Stephen Scarlett at the Bidura Children's Court in Glebe, as he attempted to curb high rates of incarceration of Indigenous juvenile offenders - won the United Nations Association's Media Peace Prize.</p>
<p>In 1996, Haussegger was poached by Channel 7's <span style="font-style:italic">Witness</span> program. She travelled widely, reporting from Iraq in the lead-up to war, and from Washington during the Clinton/Lewinsky sex scandal. As a reporter for <span style="font-style:italic">Witness</span>, Haussegger spent just four months per year at home in Sydney. The relentless pace continued until the show was axed in 1998.</p>
<p>For a time, Haussegger worked as a freelance print journalist, and later, a consultant in financial communications. By 2001, she was ready for a return to the news world, and joined the ABC once again, this time as presenter of ABC TV News in Canberra.</p>
<p>In 2002, Haussegger learned that she had problems with age-related infertility, and would be unable to have children. Her opinion piece in the <span style="font-style:italic">Age</span>, expressing her disappointment with the feminist claim that women could 'have it all', sparked enormous controversy. The result was the publication of Haussegger's book, <span style="font-style:italic">Wonder Woman: The Myth of 'Having It All'</span> in 2005. It was launched by Julia Gillard at the National Press Club.</p>
<p>Virginia Haussegger married Mark Kenny, political editor for the <span style="font-style:italic">Adelaide Advertiser</span>, in October 2005. Since 2006, she has been writing a weekly column for the <span style="font-style:italic">Canberra Times</span>. She is an active member of the journalists' union, the MEAA (Media Entertainment and Arts Alliance) and the National Press Club, and has been a judge for the Walkley Awards several times.</p>
<p>Interviewed in 2008, Haussegger remarked that 'I am fearful for the future of TV reporting in Australia. Quality television journalism takes time and time is money. It seems Australia just doesn't have a big enough audience market to justify big expenditures. I am very worried that we are taking an increasing amount of international news and current affairs product'.</p>
<p>Speaking to 200 members of the Golden Key International Society at the Australian National University, though, Haussegger 'came away feeling tremendously uplifted and energized about this young generation of Australians':</p>
<p>'One of the themes in my speech to them', she said, 'was about confronting failure. I wanted to impress upon them an understanding that all successful careers must - and will - involve moments or periods of what feels like failure. I wanted them to know that what matters most is how they handle it. And I wanted them to know that no matter how hard they work, they will occasionally stumble and maybe even fall over. But it's all about the getting up.'</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1986-01-01">1986</fromDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Career in journalism active</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-511510">
<relationEntry>
Haussegger, Virginia (1964-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Haussegger, Virginia', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Haussegger, Virginia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3801b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004260.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Wonder Woman: The Myth of 'Having It All'</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Haussegger, Virginia</name>
<title render="italic">Wonder Woman: The Myth of 'Having It All'</title>
<imprint>
<place>Crows Nest, NSW</place>
<publisher>Allen &amp; Unwin</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004262.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cal/cal-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>