<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE3501</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2008-08-26">2008-08-26</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Rosemary  Francis and Janet Butler</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3501b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Drechsler</part>
<part localType="givenname">Audrey Louise</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Walsh, Audrey Louise</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1933-06-03">3 June 1933</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Preston, Victoria, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Political candidate</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Farmer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Social activist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Following a visit to a farm in Gippsland during a period of rehabilitation, Audrey Drechsler developed a lifetime love of farming. Audrey was heavily involved in the CWA as a regional president, but was also a leader in the movement for recognition and support for women's hands-on involvement in farming, through farmers' organisations, and the women in agriculture movement. She was a member of the steering committee which organised the 1994 First International Women in Agriculture Conference, and an organiser of the 1997 and 2010 Women on Farms Gatherings. Sharing the movements' commitment to sustainable agriculture, Audrey has been active in land conservation, occupying, amongst other positions, that of first woman president of the Grassland Society of Victoria. She still farms at Sedgwick, south of Bendigo.

As Audrey Walsh, she stood as a candidate for the Democratic Labor Party in the Legislative Assembly seat of Evelyn at the Victorian state election, which was held in 1967.</abstract>
<p>Audrey Drechsler was born Audrey Walsh, the daughter of James Walsh, who in 1928 took over the Warrandyte bakery, which she still owns. She won a scholarship to University High which she took up in 1949. Whilst recuperating from an operation in 1953, she attended the former West Melbourne Technical School for rehabilitation training in secretarial studies. It was through a friendship formed there that she was introduced to farming. She commenced secretarial work at RMIT in 1956, studying various subjects at night, including book keeping. In 1963, she went overseas, and worked briefly on farms in a number of countries, including Ireland, Denmark and the USA. In 1967 she stood for the DLP in the seat of Evelyn, and while campaigning, met Bendigo candidate Bill Drechsler, whom she subsequently married. Bill Drechsler was a sheep farmer from Sedgwick in Central Victoria, and Audrey invested money in improvements in the farm, and time and energy into learning practical farming skills, and in keeping the books.</p>
<p>Audrey became involved in many community and farming organisations. She was the secretary of the Strathfieldsaye and Sutton Grange branches of the Victorian Farmers' Federation; the public relations officer, political action convenor, president, treasurer and secretary of the Bendigo Pastoral District Council, and Bendigo branch president and inaugural convenor of the Australian Farm Management Society.</p>
<p>Along with other involvement in her community's schools, church and CFA, Audrey was involved in the Country Women's Association, as secretary and president of the Sedgwick branch, and as president of the Bendigo Northern Group in 1981-3 and 2001-2003. Audrey was active in the movement to achieve recognition, a voice and education for women as farmers in their own right. She was a member of the steering committee for the 1994 First International Women in Agriculture Conference, and a constant support for the Women on Farms Gatherings, attending 17 out of the 20 held, and helping to organise the 1997 Bendigo and 2010 Inglewood gatherings. A person of forthright character, who holds the attention of those around her, Audrey is also a woman of great courage and integrity, sharing at the Bendigo gathering her story of being pack-raped at the age of 18, in Queensland, in 1951, and her steadfast appearance at five criminal trials to secure convictions, and gaol terms, for those involved. After the 1994 conference, she was a co-founder of the Central Victorian Women in Agriculture Group, and is now a member of the Victorian Branch of Australian Women in Agriculture, as well as of the national body.</p>
<p>Reflecting the Women in Agriculture movement's commitment to sustainable agriculture, Audrey has been involved as a leader in a number of organisations. She was the first women president of the Grassland Society of Victoria (1985), the Victorian State President and Federal Vice- President of the Soil &amp; Water Conservation Association of Australia (1990), and a member of the Shire of Strathfieldsaye Environment Planning Advisory Committee. Later she became Chairman of the Land and Water Working Group, Bendigo Region Conservation Strategy, as well as a member of the Bendigo Region Land Protection Advisory Committee of the Department of Conservation, Forests and Land. Audrey was the convenor and inaugural president of the North Harcourt-Sedgwick Landcare Group, the 14th such group set up in Victoria, the Convenor of the Axe Creek Catchment Landcare Group, and a Victorian Committee member of the Australian Landcare Foundation. For thirty years she has been involved with departmental trials, experiments and field days.</p>
<p>When Audrey was widowed in 1989, and the farm passed to her son, she secured 125 acres of it, did a six months farm mechanics course, borrowed on her bakery to build a mud-brick house, and still farms there today, producing prime vealers. She is concerned about the drift to the city, with encouraging young women to stay on the land, and about water policy.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0791b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Country Women's Association of Victoria Inc. (1928 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00832b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Central Victorian Women in Agriculture Inc. (1994? - 2006)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00488b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
First International Women in Agriculture Conference (1994)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Conference Organiser</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00727b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women on Farms Gatherings (1990 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Organiser</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00733b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Women in Agriculture Movement (1990s - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-725051">
<relationEntry>
Dreschsler, Audrey Louise
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-773075">
<relationEntry>
Drechsler, Audrey (1933-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Drechsler, Audrey Louise', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Drechsler, Audrey Louise</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3501b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005590.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: The Encyclopedia of Women and Leadership in Twentieth-Century Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Smart, Judith and Swain, Shurlee (eds)</name>
<title render="italic">The Encyclopedia of Women and Leadership in Twentieth-Century Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2014</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/leaders"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004269.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Carrying on the Fight: Women Candidates in Victorian Parliamentary Elections</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">Carrying on the Fight: Women Candidates in Victorian Parliamentary Elections</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cws/home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00833.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Audrey Drechsler Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Audrey Drechsler Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc11.023</unitid>
<unitdate>1979 - 2009</unitdate>
<abstract>The papers reflect Audrey Drechsler's thirty years' involvement as an activist in the Women in Agriculture movement. They include rare papers relating to very early conferences, including two in 1979, and the 1994 First International Women in Agriculture Conference; registration forms for Australian Women in Agriculture Inc. skills workshops; Minutes, newletters, letters, flyers, planning documents, media clippings, mailing lists, questionnaire, report relating to Central Victorian Women in Agriculture; papers relating to attendance at seventeen annual Women on Farm Gatherings, and the Heritage Project, including programs, proceedings, registration forms, media clipping; booklet on stress management in country communities prepared by Women in Agriculture - Victorian Mallee Group.

These papers were recently accessed by the National Library of Australia. Please contact them for further details.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 box</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002623.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Laurene Dietrich, 1990-1994 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Laurene Dietrich, 1990-1994 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc11.024</unitid>
<unitdate>1990 - 1994</unitdate>
<abstract>Comprises papers relating to Laurene Dietrich's role as a member of the organising committee for the first Women in Agriculture Conference, held in Melbourne, July 1994. The collection includes correspondence, reports, list of participants, minutes of meetings, copies of some of the papers presented at the conference, photographs, a questionnaire for particpants and news cuttings</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00502.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Mary Salce Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Mary Salce Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc10.145, MS Acc11.123</unitid>
<unitdate>1976 - 2007</unitdate>
<abstract>Minutes, press releases, press clippings, correspondece, reports, proposals, funding applications, video tapes, post conference proceedings and evaluations, lists of attendees, newsletters, brochures, photographs and programs relating to Mary Salce's early activism, the formation of the original Statewide Women in Agriculture organisation, the First International Women in Agricuture Conference, and subsequent international conferences,and the Foundation for Australian Agricultural Women.

NB - Papers have been recently acquired by the National Library of Australia. Contact repository for details.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.8 m</extent>
<physfacet>1.80 m. (7 boxes) + 1 fol. box + 1 fol. packet.</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00838.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Grasslands Society of Southern Australia Inc. Records</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Private Hands (contact Australian Women's Archive Project)</repository>
<unittitle>Grasslands Society of Southern Australia Inc. Records</unittitle>
<unitdate>September 1969 - </unitdate>
<abstract>Committee meeting minutes, Annual General Meeting minutes, Annual Conference Proceedings</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001305.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Country Women's Association of Victoria Inc.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Australian Historic Records Register</repository>
<unittitle>Country Women's Association of Victoria Inc.</unittitle>
<unitid>267</unitid>
<unitdate>1928 - 1987</unitdate>
<abstract>Minutes of the Executive Committee which was originally the Provisional Organising Committee, March 1928-1987 (10 vols). 
Minutes of various committees such as finance, welfare, international, home help, 1928-1987 (29 vols). Minutes of about 80 Victorian branches, mostly defunct, 1929-1981, (c200 vols). 
Printed agendas for Annual General Meetings, 1929-1987 (59 agendas). 
Annual reports, 1929-1987 (59 printed reports). 
Country Crafts, monthly newsletter, no.1, December 1930-1987 (c600 issues). 
Minutes of Biennial meetings of the Country Women's Association of Australia, June 1945-1960 (1 vol.). 
Minutes of Annual General Meetings, June 1960-1987 (1 vol.). 
Scrapbook of newscuttings and photographs covering the Tenth Triennial Conference of the Associated Country Women of the World, Melbourne, October 1962 (1 vol.).</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>