<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE3121</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2008-06-18">2008-06-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Barbara Lemon</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3121b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Osborn</part>
<part localType="givenname">Betty Olive</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="maiden name"><part>Roberts, Betty</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1935-01-01">c. 1935</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Historian</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Print journalist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>An accomplished journalist and local historian, Betty Osborn (then Betty Roberts) was known as the 'girl reporter' of the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> newspaper in the 1950s.</abstract>
<p>In 1951, a young Betty Roberts took herself to the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> offices to enquire about a career in journalism. She was advised to complete her matriculation at University High School, keep up her typing and short-hand, and return the following year. Betty began work as a secretary for the <span style="font-style:italic">Weekend Magazine</span> at the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> in 1952, and noted that - unusually - men and women journalists were being paid equally. That year, she wrote a report for the paper on the itinerants living at Melbourne's Dudley Flats (now the exclusive Docklands development site), who survived by scavenging from the tip. She took photographs for the feature herself, using her mother's box brownie camera.</p>
<p>Feeling there was little prospect for a career in journalism, Betty enrolled to do a Bachelor of Laws at the University of Melbourne, but on the eve of her first week as a law clerk was offered a cadetship with the social pages of the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span>. She accepted, but continued at the university as a part-time Arts student. She remembers, on returning to the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span>: 'Virginia Gerrett, of Sydney, was in charge of the Social pages… She had replaced Gladys Hain much to the consternation of all the women journalists who considered Freda Irving as the heir apparent. Freda cooled her heels briefly on the <span style="font-style:italic">Weekend Magazine</span> where her deep voice would often have telephone callers referring to her as "Peter Irving". This greatly appealed to her sense of humour.'</p>
<p>Under Freda Irving, Betty worked with Kath Coyne, Grace Hutchinson, Cynthia Strachan, Elaine Young and Julie Sparrow. In addition to the usual social pages fare, Irving encouraged her young proteges to investigate stories of importance to women, and to write detailed profiles of women in the news. The cadets were expected to look the part, with hats, gloves, and appropriate evening wear when necessary. In 1955, Betty Roberts won the Australian Journalists' Association's Montague Grover Prize for cadet journalists. She was soon transferred to the general staff:</p>
<p>'For a start I didn't have to worry about hats and gloves any more. Ellie Knox, the Town Hall roundswoman, and I were the only women in a sea of men, young and old. The newsroom was a vast open space with the day chief of staff Laurie Kerr's office at one end, an array of reporters' desks in the middle and the subs tables at the northern end where a door led to the printery. Once opened, the noise of the old linotype machines could be heard clattering away and in the distance the compositors could be glimpsed, quietly going about arranging their leaden trays of type. How close we all were, journalists and printers, bringing out the news of the world to the people of Melbourne.'</p>
<p>Betty was assigned to cover nearly every session of the Legislative Assembly as a gallery reporter in 1956 - 'competition was fierce and I can remember being absolutely appalled when I came upon the <span style="font-style:italic">Sun</span> political roundsman rifling through Lance [Loader]'s papers one day' - and made the most of the parliamentary library for her studies. She remembers: 'There was not one woman in the Victorian Legislative Assembly that year and the only woman I recall coming into the press gallery was Rose Kinson from the <span style="font-style:italic">Sun</span>'. Outside of parliament, Betty was given a number of reporting tasks, including coverage of a Coroner's Court case in which Frank Galbally was representing an Italian man whose wife had been stabbed to death.</p>
<p>To her delight, Betty Roberts was assigned to cover the 1956 Olympic Games in Melbourne. She spent a great deal of time at the Olympic Village in Heidelberg, chasing up stories on famous (and infamous) international athletes. Just six weeks after the closing day of the Games, the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> folded. Betty wrote for the <span style="font-style:italic">Sun</span>, but the <span style="font-style:italic">Argus</span> was the paper she truly loved. She returned to full time study at the University of Melbourne.</p>
<p>After marrying Bruce Osborn, Betty moved to Bacchus Marsh, Victoria. Here began her abiding interest in local history. By 1971 she had published <span style="font-style:italic">A History of Holy Trinity, Bacchus Marsh</span> (republished 1977). In 1973, she published <span style="font-style:italic">The Bacchus Story: A History of Captain W.H. Bacchus and his Son</span>. That same year, the Osborns moved to Maryborough with their four children: Robyn, Diana, Cathy and Philip. Betty became a member of the Midlands Historical Society, and for three years she edited the Wimmera-Mallee edition of the <span style="font-style:italic">Country Bulletin</span>. She was also a columnist for the <span style="font-style:italic">Maryborough Advertiser</span>. With local resident Trenear DuBourg, Betty was commissioned by the Maryborough City Council to produce a history of the region, and in 1985 they published <span style="font-style:italic">Maryborough: A Social History 1854-1904</span>. Ten years later Osborn completed its sequel, <span style="font-style:italic">Against the Odds: Maryborough 1905-1961</span>, again by commission from what had then become the Central Goldfields Shire Council.</p>
<p>Betty Osborn is a life member of the Bacchus Marsh and District Historical Society, and a member of the Royal Historical Society of Victoria.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1952-01-01">c. 1952</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1980-12-31">c. 1980</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Career in journalism active</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-513260">
<relationEntry>
Osborn, Betty (1935-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Osborn, Betty Olive', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Osborn, Betty Olive</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3121b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003984.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Against the Odds: Maryborough 1905-1961</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Osborn, Betty</name>
<title render="italic">Against the Odds: Maryborough 1905-1961</title>
<imprint>
<place>Maryborough</place>
<publisher>Central Goldfields Shire Council</publisher>
<date>1995</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP003983.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Maryborough: A Social History 1854-1904</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">DuBourg, Trenear and Betty Osborn</name>
<title render="italic">Maryborough: A Social History 1854-1904</title>
<imprint>
<place>Maryborough</place>
<publisher>Maryborough City Council</publisher>
<date>1985</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004262.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">The Women's Pages: Australian Women and Journalism since 1850</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cal/cal-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>