<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4788</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2012-06-22">2012-06-22</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kim Doyle</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4788b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Cunningham</part>
<part localType="givenname">Mary Emily</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="birth name"><part>Twynam, Mary Emily</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1869-09-30">30 September 1869</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1930-11-15">15 November 1930</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Goulburn, New South Wales</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>'Fairvale', Canberra, Australian Capital Territory</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Pastoralist wife</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Activist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Poet</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>War worker</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Red Cross Worker</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Born to English parents, and daughter of the Surveyor General, Mary Emily Twynam married wealthy pastoralist James 'Jim' Cunningham and became an important and formative figure in the developing pastoralist community in the Tuggeranong district. She was a compassionate, sensitive and intellectually curious woman whose capacity for friendship and kindness turned her homestead 'Tuggranong' into the social focal point of the community. Her early married years were taken up with raising eight children and battling with the bouts of serious depression that would shadow her for her entire life. As her children grew she found time to indulge in her love of gardening as well as pursue her passion for poetry and the written word. Cunningham was also an outspoken advocate for conscription during the two referenda in 1916 and was dedicated to fundraising for soldiers in the Great War.</abstract>
<p>Mary Emily Twynam was born and grew up in the New South Wales township of Goulburn. Her family home 'Riversdale' was a place she always remembered fondly. Her father, Edward Twynam came to the colony in 1885 from England and prospered as a surveyor. He would eventually go on to become the Surveyor General. His wife Emily Rose was an accomplished artist who left behind many beautiful woodcarvings and etchings. She took a keen interest in the natural world and Mary Emily seems to have inherited a love of gardening and nature from her. From the archival material that exists Emily Rose appears to have been a loving and kind mother to her children. Mary Emily however, developed a close bond with her father that would be one of the cornerstones of her whole life. They shared an interest in literary pursuits and both possessed keen and inquiring intellects. As an adult Mary would often run drafts of her poems and ideas by her father. Like other young women of her class, Mary was educated at home by Governess Miss Nora Martyr. 'Riversdale' was to occupy a special place in Mary's heart for her whole life indicating that she had a warm loving and happy childhood in the place she would call 'Home' until her death.</p>
<p>On 24 April 1889 a 19 year old Mary Emily was married to successful pastoralist James 'Jim' Cunningham, who at 39 was 20 years her senior. It was a marriage partly borne of duty, but one which would become, if not passionate, stable and affectionate. After a honeymoon abroad in Europe the couple returned to Australia to settle at 'Tuggranong' (spelled this way to distinguish it from the surrounding Tuggeranong district). 'Tuggranong' was one of a number of properties owned by Jim Cunningham and his brother Andrew Jackson Cunningham. 'Tuggranong' like the brothers' nearby property 'Lanyon' was a large sheep station on the eastern banks of the Murrumbidgee river; up to 50 000 sheep were shorn at the 'Tuggranong' sheds. The brothers also had properties on the western side of the river as well as holdings in the Cooma and Forbes districts. Both 'Lanyon' and 'Tuggranong' would come to occupy an important part of Mary's heart and life with both providing her a deep sense of place and belonging. She also left her mark on both properties with her skilful and committed gardening.</p>
<p>Mary Emily was already pregnant with the couple's first child by the time they settled at 'Tuggranong' and on 2 June 1890 Jane Cynthia Cunningham was born. Seven more children would follow in the next 12 years. During this period Mary's first documented battle with what we would now call depression or postnatal depression occurred. Mary herself never referred to these battles in her letters or notebooks, but references to her breakdown in 1902, after the birth of her son Alexander 'Pax', are found in her family's letters. In October 1903 Mary's sister, Edith wrote from 'Riversdale' to her friend Stella Miles Franklin and expressed relief and gratitude at Mary's restoration 'from the dead'.</p>
<p>Despite her personal struggles with such darkness Mary remained a much loved, and loving, member of her community. She took to her role as a successful pastoralist's wife with gusto attending balls, getting involved in fundraising activities for the parish church as well as other causes like raising funds for a local hospital. The homestead itself became the social hub of the district and Mary and Jim hosted many fine gatherings there. When the new military academy at Duntroon was opened in June 1911 Mary warmly welcomed the cadets. Many of them would call on 'Tuggranong' whenever possible, probably in part due to her teenaged daughters, and a few would keep up correspondence with Mary when they were serving overseas in the Great War a few years later. Her involvement in the community and her loyal and giving friendship were all the more admirable as in these years she lost both her eldest daughter Jane Cynthia to appendicitis and her beloved mother just a few short weeks later.</p>
<p>By 1914 with the Great War well and truly looming large the family moved to 'Lanyon'. The move was precipitated by the death of Andrew Jackson as well the changes afoot with the planning for the new Federal Capital. There were uncertainties about how quickly 'Tuggranong' would be reclaimed as Commonwealth land and so a move to 'Lanyon' afforded the family some stability. At this time the couple offered 'Tuggranong' to the Commonwealth government as a convalescent hospital for the duration of the war, but this offer was not taken up. The war also caused other shifts in the Cunningham family and in the texture of Mary's everyday life. Always a staunch supporter of Empire, (her Empire Day bonfires for the Tuggeranong district were big affairs) Mary was unequivocally supportive of the war. Her eldest son, Andrew would go on to distinguished service with the First Light Horse Regiment, and her sister Joan served as nurse overseas for the duration of the war.</p>
<p>Mary herself became a passionate fundraiser and like many of her class a committed advocate of conscription during the campaigns in 1916. To the disapproval of some of the conservative people in her community she took a public role in joining a local pro-conscription committee. In the winter of 1915 she threw a ball at 'Lanyon' to raise funds for the Red Cross, and in 1917 she took the post of president of the newly created War Chest Flower Shop. The War Chest was established in 1914 as fundraising group that aimed to support all soldiers, not just the wounded ones like the Red Cross did. The position meant Mary had to travel between Sydney and 'Lanyon' of which she was now involved in managing as her husband had succumbed to chronic ill-health. The Flower shop, based on Elizabeth Street in Sydney, sold fresh produce, fresh flowers and over time Mary would come to sell some of her poems in the store too; a move she relied on her father to help her make with him often acting as critic and editor of her work. The Flower Shop was a successful venture and they eventually moved to larger premises on George Street. Despite the growing pressures and gloom of her ailing husband Mary, as always, formed supportive intellectually stimulating and loyal friendships, she struck a particularly affectionate relationship with the young artist Grace Cossington-Smith during these years.</p>
<p>After the war Mary's life changed. Her son Andrew returned from war in 1919 but had been broken by his service and eventually descended into alcoholism. He took over 'Lanyon' as Mary was now based in Bondi, Sydney with Jim whose health was too poor to be in the cold southern climate. Andrew proceeded to publicly disgrace the family and mismanage 'Lanyon' to the point that it was publicly auctioned off in 1926, much to Mary's dismay. 'Tuggranong' was also gone by this stage having been taken over by the Department of Defence in 1922; it became the Official Historian, Charles Bean's residence for the duration of the history's writing. Both of these losses came after a deeply felt loss of Jim, who died on 28 December 1921 after years of poorly healthy. For a woman so bound to community, place and family Mary was adrift in many ways. After Jim's death she went 'home' to reside at 'Riversdale', but the final hurt came with the death of her father in 1923 after just a brief illness. After this latest grief she split her time between 'Riversdale' and 'Fairwater', a property near Ulladulla that she acquired in 1927 after the sale of 'Lanyon'. Here Mary withdrew into her herself and unlike in 1902 her family was now grown and busy with their own lives and did not rally around to pull her out of her darkness. She died alone at 'Fairvale' (her daughter's home) at the age 61 on 15 November 1930. Her death certificate refers to her refusal to take drink or food and of her 'unsound mind'. Her son Andrew found her body and had her buried at the family cemetery at 'Lanyon' where her husband and four of her daughters also lay. With the end of her life so came the end of an era of her family's proud pastoral heritage and deep ties with the land and people of the Tuggeranong valley.</p>
<p>Read more about Mary Cunningham's activities during World War I at the exhibition <citation xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="exhib/cww1/cunningham.html">Canberra Women in World War 1: Community at Home, Nurses Abroad</citation>.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5408b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Dunlop, Mary Paule (1893 - 1978)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5407b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Davies, Griselda Dorothea (Tommy) (1894 - 1931)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0988b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Comforts Fund (1916 - 1920)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0715b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Red Cross (1914 - )
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Mary Cunningham volunteered for the Australian Red Cross during WW1</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5392b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Crace, Helen Blanche (1878 - 1926)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Both Cunningham and Crace volunteered for the Red Cross during WW1</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5415b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Parnell, Ida Mary (1871 - 1950)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Both Cunningham and Parnell volunteered for the Red Cross in WW1</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1535003">
<relationEntry>
Cunningham, Mary Emily (18690930-19301115)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Cunningham, Mary Emily', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Cunningham, Mary Emily</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4788b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004950.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal Article: Beautiful Colours to Arrange: Mary Cunningham, Mistress of Tuggeranong</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Horsfield, Jennifer</name>
<title render="quoted">Beautiful Colours to Arrange: Mary Cunningham, Mistress of Tuggeranong</title>
<imprint>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">National Library of Australia News</title>
<num type="volume">13</num>
<num type="issue">7</num>
<num type="pages">18-21</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004949.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Mary Cunningham: An Australian Life</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Horsfield, Jennifer</name>
<title render="italic">Mary Cunningham: An Australian Life</title>
<imprint>
<place>Charnwood</place>
<publisher>Ginninderra Press</publisher>
<date>2004</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004948.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Twynam, Edward (1832-1923)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Twynam, Edward (1832-1923)</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Obituaries Australia, National Centre of Biography, Australian National University</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://oa.anu.edu.au/obituary/twynam-edward-1648/text1756"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004947.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Tuggeranong Homestead</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Tuggeranong Homestead</title>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.tuggeranonghomestead.com.au/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004946.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Lanyon Homestead</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Lanyon Homestead</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">ACT Museum and Galleries</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.museumsandgalleries.act.gov.au/lanyon/"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004945.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Cunningham, Mary Emily (1870 - 1930)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Cunningham, Mary Emily (1870 - 1930)</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Obituaries Australia, National Centre of Biography, Australian National University</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://oa.anu.edu.au/obituary/cunningham-mary-emily-1639"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004944.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource Section: Cunningham, James (Jim) (1850-1921)</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Cunningham, James (Jim) (1850-1921)</title>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Obituaries Australia, National Centre of Biography, Australian National University</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://oa.anu.edu.au/obituary/cunningham-james-jim-278"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004943.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Silver Wedding</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Silver Wedding</title>
<imprint>
<date>1914</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Queanbeyan Age</title>
<num type="pages">2</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004942.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Marriage Notice</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Marriage Notice</title>
<imprint>
<date>1889</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</title>
<num type="pages">1</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004941.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newspaper Article: Funeral Notice. Mrs. M. Cunningham</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="quoted">Funeral Notice. Mrs. M. Cunningham</title>
<imprint>
<date>1930</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Sydney Morning Herald</title>
<num type="pages">10</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005702.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Canberra Women in World War I: Community at Home, Nurses Abroad</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Clarke, Patricia and Francis, Niki</name>
<title render="italic">Canberra Women in World War I: Community at Home, Nurses Abroad</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2015</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cww1"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005644.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Official History of Australia in the War of 1914-1918: Australia during the war</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Scott, Ernest</name>
<title render="italic">The Official History of Australia in the War of 1914-1918: Australia during the war</title>
<edition>4</edition>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Angus and Robertson</publisher>
<date>1938</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005365.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">From Lady Denman to Katy Gallagher: A Century of Women's Contributions to Canberra</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ldkg"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002572.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>NLA MS 6734</unitid>
<unitdate>1834 - 1902</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Manuscript</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002571.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Letters</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Letters</unittitle>
<unitid>NLA MS 6748</unitid>
<unitdate>1910 - 1960</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Manuscript, </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002570.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Letters</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Letters</unittitle>
<unitid>NLA MS 6749</unitid>
<unitdate>1858 - 1931</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Manuscript</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002824.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Nimmo family. and Cunningham family. Letters, 1910-1960 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Nimmo family. and Cunningham family. Letters, 1910-1960 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS 6748</unitid>
<unitdate>1910 - 1960</unitdate>
<abstract>Five letters; Mary E. Cunningham to her son Andrew ca. 1910; Peggy Cunningham (later Nimmo) to her brother-in-law William Dunlop, 1917; Edward Twynam to his daughter, Mary Cunningham, 1919; Peggy Nimmo to her aunt Joan Twynam, 1932 and Mary Dunlop (nee Cunningham to her niece Anne Nimmo (later Truman) ca. 1960.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.02 m, 5 Letters</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002823.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Cunningham family, 1834-1902 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Cunningham family, 1834-1902 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS 6734</unitid>
<unitdate>1834 - 1902</unitdate>
<abstract>Family and business papers relating to John Hamilton Mortimer Lanyon (1834-1863); business records of Lanyon (1834-1902); receipts for rent on runs, licence to occupy waste lands; Correspondence with John Davidson, solicitor of Goulburn, 1884-1886; Mining papers, 1888-1889; Bank records. Business letters and accounts relating to Moothumbil Station (on the Bland), Thomas Herbert and Andrew Cunningham, 1875-1880. Also includes a copy of P.G. Smith sermon and a copy of the Will of Mary Cunningham.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.14 m, 1 Box</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00932.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Pro-conscription Referendum Reinforcements campaign, circa 1917</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Lanyon Homestead, ACT Museums and Galleries, Canberra, Australian Capital Territory, Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Pro-conscription Referendum Reinforcements campaign, circa 1917</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1917</unitdate>
<abstract>Mary Emily Cunningham on the pro-conscription Referendum Reinforcements campaign (which woman she is is unknown).</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>