<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4472</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2010-03-15">2010-03-15</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Nikki Henningham</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4472b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">McMillan</part>
<part localType="givenname">Jennifer</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1950-01-01">1950</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Maffra, Victoria, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Farmer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Agriculturalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Board member</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Scientist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Jennifer McMillan was a nominee for the ABC Rural Woman of the year Award in 1997. She and her husband ran a dairy farm near Rosedale in Gippsland, Victoria.</abstract>
<p>Jennifer McMillan was born in Maffra, Victoria, in the heart of the Macalister irrigation district. Her father was granted a soldier settlement block at Denison in 1951, and her parents dairy farmed there. When she finished school she worked as a herd tester (testing milk volume composition for fat and protein) in the dairy industry until she married.</p>
<p>Herd testing was a job that a lot of young women did at the time. She worked in the Bunyip district, visiting a round of twenty farms per month. Most testers stayed on the farms, comin home only on the weekends. The job has changed sign. They can collect samples and then bring them to the lab.</p>
<p><br />
Jennifer's husband was also a herd tester; that is how they - moved into a variety of share farming positions before buying their own farm at Rosedale in 1980. They bought and adjoining block of land in 1986.</p>
<p>Jennifer and her husband split the work between them. She is the herd manager and her husband in the farm manager. She also manages the financial records. She is extremely knowledgable in the science of artificial insemination of breeding stock. She never had formal education in the process, she just picked up knoewledge as she went along.</p>
<p>Jennifer has taken an interest in farming organisations beyond her own front gate. She has served as president of the Victorian branch of United Dairy Farmers and secretary of the district council of that same organisation. She has been vice-chair of the East Gippsland Rural Financial Counselling Committee; a board member of the School of Primary Industries at the local college of Techinical and Further Education (TAFE); a board member of the Macalister Research Farm and has serves on the course advisory committee of the Victorian Curriculum and Assessment Authority (VCAA).</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1997-01-01">1997</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1997-12-31">1997</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Nominated for ABC Rural Woman of the Year in Victoria</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477377">
<relationEntry>
McMillan, Jennifer (1950-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'McMillan, Jennifer', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">McMillan, Jennifer</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4472b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004918.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Brilliant Ideas and Huge Visions: ABC Radio Australian Rural Women of the Year - 1994-1997</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">Brilliant Ideas and Huge Visions: ABC Radio Australian Rural Women of the Year - 1994-1997</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2011</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/rwya/rwya-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002426.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jennifer McMillan interviewed by Ros Bowden Women of the land oral history project</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia, Oral History and Folklore Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Jennifer McMillan interviewed by Ros Bowden Women of the land oral history project</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 3406/27</unitid>
<abstract>McMillan, a farmer, speaks of her childhood on a dairy farm, working as a herd tester after finishing school, share farming, buying a farm in 1980, division of responsibilities between her husband and herself, the use of artificial insemination and bull farms in herd management, the importance of efficient irrigation systems in farm management, her extensive involvement in local committees (the local branch of United Dairy Farmers of Victoria, District Council of United Dairy Farmers of Victoria, East Gippsland Rural Financial Counselling Committee, the board of the School of Primary Industries of TAFE and the VCAH Course Advisory Committee), and her plans for the farm.
Recorded in 1995.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 Sound cassette</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>