<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4091</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-03-03">2009-03-03</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Barbara Lemon</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4091b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Landorf</part>
<part localType="givenname">Christine</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1961-12-23">23 December 1961</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Broken Hill, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Architect</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Academic</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Christine Landorf is an architect and academic who grew up in Broken Hill. With David Manfredi, she designed the Visitors' Centre there and three of her students - Angus Barron, Steve Kelly and Dario Palumbo - designed the Broken Hill Miners' Memorial. Together, the Memorial and the Visitors' Centre received the Royal Australian Institute of Architects' Walter Burley Griffin Award for Urban Design.</abstract>
<p>The second daughter of Ross and Marion Landorf, Chris has a strong connection to Broken Hill. Both her maternal and paternal grandparents settled and worked in the city, though they came from quite different social backgrounds. Her paternal grandfather worked underground in the mines as a winder house driver, and her father Ross after him completed a fitting and turning apprenticeship before working as a mine manager. Her maternal grandfather was a surveyor who, after working in Southern Cross and Mount Isa, became the General Manager of New Broken Hill Consolidated. Chris's mother Marion (née Hooper), was born in Southern Cross in Western Australia and worked as a comptometrist on the mines in Broken Hill before her marriage.</p>
<p>Chris attended Alma Primary School and enjoyed an active childhood riding bikes and playing sport on the weekends. She spent two years at Willyama High School before moving to Adelaide to attend boarding school. After completing high school, she began a degree in Interior Design at the South Australian Institute of Technology, and at the end of second year transferred into Architecture on the advice of her lecturer. Chris was one of only two women in a class of 28, but never experienced sexism or discrimination. Although her father Ross held conservative views, he gave Chris his full support and never discouraged her from pursuing an atypical career in a predominantly masculine profession. Rather, Ross was proud that his children were studying at university as he had never had the opportunity to undertake tertiary study himself.</p>
<p>After graduating Chris worked for a small practitioner, Russell Prescott, and then for the bigger firm of Rod Roach Architecture. At the age of 26 she was employed by the Adelaide City Council to work on the redevelopment of the town hall, a major project spanning several years. Having completed her Interior Design degree part time, Chris began teaching this discipline at the University of South Australia whilst undertaking a Masters of Business. After moving to teach architecture, she became a program convenor and was appointed Head of School for three years.</p>
<p>Though she left Broken Hill at the age of 14, Chris maintained a connection to the town where she was born. She regularly returned to visit her parents until they left the Silver City in 1985, and researched Broken Hill's history as part of a final year project for her architecture degree. While teaching at the University of South Australia, Chris initiated a summer elective study trip to Broken Hill. The project was set up in conjunction with the Line of Lode Association, which was interested in making a tourist attraction out of an old mine lease that had been donated back to the city. Chris's students proposed a number of designs for a visitors' centre, a restaurant and a memorial. The Association was thrilled by the proposals and, after receiving $1.84 million in Centenary Funding, was able to commission two of the projects: the Miners' Memorial and the Visitors' Centre. The walls of the Miners' Memorial, designed by students Angus Barron, Steve Kelly and Dario Palumbo, are inscribed with the names and causes of death of those who died in the mines. The design for the Visitors' Centre was conceived by Chris and her former student, David Manfredi. Its fractured roof and constricting walls simulate the experience of being underground. Both buildings were officially opened by the Hon. John Anderson, Deputy Prime Minister, on 21 April 2001. In December of that year they received the Walter Burley Griffin Award for Urban Design from the Royal Australian Institute of Architects.</p>
<p>Chris Landorf continues to teach architecture at the University of Newcastle while completing a doctorate in Industrial Heritage. Her PhD investigates the sustainability and preservation of significant industrial sites, combining the maintenance of the built environement with a respect for its heritage. It compares the management models of six industrial sites in the United Kingdom with the management model proposed for the city of Broken Hill, recently nominated for the National Heritage list. If that nomination is successful, Broken Hill will be the first Australian city to be heritage listed in its entirety.</p>
<p><br />
<span style="font-weight:bold">This entry was prepared and written by Georgia Moodie.</span></p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-716098">
<relationEntry>
Landorf, Christine (1961-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Landorf, Christine (Chris)', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Landorf, Christine (Chris)</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4091b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004420.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal Article: Managing for Sustainable Tourism: A Review of Six Cultural World Heritage Sites</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Landorf, Christine</name>
<title render="quoted">Managing for Sustainable Tourism: A Review of Six Cultural World Heritage Sites</title>
<imprint>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Journal of Sustainable Tourism</title>
<num type="volume">17</num>
<num type="issue">1</num>
<num type="pages">53-70</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004419.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Conference Paper: Silk Purses from Sows' Ears: An Argument for Industrial Heritage: The Cultural Significance of Broken Hill</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Landorf, Christine</name>
<title render="quoted">Silk Purses from Sows' Ears: An Argument for Industrial Heritage: The Cultural Significance of Broken Hill</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>University of Adelaide</publisher>
<date>2002</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">20th Century Heritage, Our Recent Cultural Legacy: Australia ICOMOS National Conference, November-December 2001</title>
<name type="author">School of Architecture, Landscape Architecture and Urban Design</name>
<num type="pages">440-444</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004418.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal Article: A Sense of Identity and a Sense of Place: Oral History and Preserving the Past the Mining Community of Broken Hill</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Landorf, Christine</name>
<title render="quoted">A Sense of Identity and a Sense of Place: Oral History and Preserving the Past the Mining Community of Broken Hill</title>
<imprint>
<date>2000</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Oral History Society Journal</title>
<num type="volume">28</num>
<num type="issue">1</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004417.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: What's left when the ore runs out, mate?</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Landorf, Christine</name>
<title render="quoted">What's left when the ore runs out, mate?</title>
<imprint>
<place>Berkeley, USA</place>
<publisher>Center for Environmental Design and Research, University of California, Berkeley</publisher>
<date>1998</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Conservation Projects and Cultural Survival</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004564.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Unbroken Spirit: Women in Broken Hill</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">Unbroken Spirit: Women in Broken Hill</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2009</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/bh/bh-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002212.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Christine Landorf</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Private Hands (contact Australian Women's Archive Project)</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Christine Landorf</unittitle>
<unitdate>2 February 2009</unitdate>
<abstract>Interview conducted in Broken Hill as part of the AWAP Broken Hill exhibition. To be lodged with the Outback Archives, Broken Hill City Library.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Audio</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00451.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Line of Lode, Broken Hill</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Line of Lode, Broken Hill</unittitle>
<unitdate>2009</unitdate>
<abstract>With Visitors' Centre and Miners' Memorial visible on the top left.</abstract>
<note label="rights">Barbara Lemon</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>