<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4940</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-03">2013-09-03</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Jan Hipgrave, Marian Quartly and Judith Smart</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4940b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Scotford</part>
<part localType="givenname">Jessie Margaret</part>
<part localType="honorific title">OBE</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Timms, Jessie Margaret</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1917-11-10">10 November 1917</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2003-05-13">13 May 2003</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Casino, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Women's right activist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Women's rights organiser</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Community worker</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Arts administrator</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Novelist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Jessie Scotford was president of the National Council of Women of New South Wales (1967-1970), and national president (1970-1973). She brought to her work with the National Councils a strong sense of the importance of history and literature as the creators of national culture and identity. The same concern led her to join the National Trust, where she campaigned for 'the importance of preserving not only the buildings, but the contents of the buildings'. In 1973, she ran in Sydney the first International Council of Women's Regional Conference to be held in the Pacific region.</abstract>
<p>Jessie Scotford was born in 1917 in Casino in outback New South Wales, where her father, Edward Vivian Timms, had taken up farming after returning injured from Gallipoli. The family returned to city life a few years later when Timms and his wife, Alma, decided he was better suited to a career as a writer. Timms went on to become a successful historical novelist; his best-known works are probably <span style="font-style:italic">Forever to Remain</span> (1948) and <span style="font-style:italic">The Beckoning Shore</span> (1950). Jessie Scotford remembered her country upbringing as a time when 'we put down a lot of very good Australian roots'.</p>
<p>Jessie attended Gosford High School, becoming the school captain in her final year. She went on to become an evening student at Sydney University, working by day at a number of jobs, including journalism. In 1940, before she graduated, she married Herbert Edward Scotford, at that time a sergeant in the AIF. For the next 6 years the couple were separated by war. Mrs Scotford was awarded a BA in 1942.</p>
<p>After the birth of her children - twins, a boy and a girl - Jessie Scotford became involved in a range of community activities. She joined the Women Graduates Association and found herself preparing abstracts of United Nations documents on women's rights for publication in the WGA newsletter. She joined the mothers' association at her children's school and soon became president. She worked as honorary archivist for the New South Wales National Trust for about 7 years, later joining its council. And, as president of North Shore group of the National Heart Campaign in its first year of operation, she became involved in fund-raising, event organisation, and public speaking. She became a speaker for the National Heart Campaign and subsequently for the Freedom From Hunger Campaign, discovering a talent for public persuasion.</p>
<p>Advised by her husband that she needed a professional qualification, in 1955 Jessie Scotford undertook a Diploma of Education in the new education-by-distance program at the University of New England, again studying by night and teaching by day. A thesis written for this program became in Scotford's words 'a turning point in my whole life'. Taking a trunkful of 19th-century family letters, she analysed their potential as a means of teaching history. This innovative exercise also involved her in the new discipline of folklore studies, and the popular movement to establish folk museums for the preservation of 'our Australian heritage'.</p>
<p>After an overseas tour, during which she visited 'all the major folk museums in the British Isles and on the Continent', Jessie Scotford began to campaign through the National Trust 'on the importance of preserving not only the buildings, but the contents of the buildings'. The idea was entirely new to the National Trust Executive Council and its members were difficult to convince. But Scotford established a large collection of historical costumes dating from early Sydney, and, by the mid-1970s, the Trust was persuaded to purchase these as the basis of a future folk museum. She was a council member of the National Trust of Australia (NSW) from 1974 to 1981.</p>
<p>In parallel with this work on the heritage front, Jessie Scotford became involved in the national and international women's movement. She joined the National Council of Women of NSW as a delegate of the Women Graduates Association, becoming convenor of the committee for arts and letters in 1965, and president of the Council from 1967. This led to her chairing the Women's Committee of the Captain Cook Bicentenary Celebrations, and effectively managing a range of bicentenary events in 1970, including a women's 'Pageant of Endeavour'-an exhibition in the Sydney Town Hall demonstrating women's contribution to the development of NSW. 120,000 people visited the exhibition. A series of 'Life in the Home' tableaux demonstrated 'family life, costume, customs, household furniture and contents'. Scotford also collected and later published a collection of brief histories of all the 250 women's organisations involved in the 'Pageant'.</p>
<p>In 1970, Scotford also became president of National Council of Women of Australia. As president she carried forward the reform programs of her predecessor, Ada Norris, including the long struggle for equal pay, finally achieved with the Arbitration Court decision to abolish the male basic wage in 1974. She initiated new programs to obtain equal treatment for women in the areas of pensions and taxation, and to improve the standard of care in child-care centres. She raised the issue of Aboriginal welfare within the National Councils, calling in 1972 for reports from all affiliates on the local treatment of Aborigines.</p>
<p>In retrospect Jessie Scotford remembered as the major achievement of her presidency the staging of the 1973 International Council of Women's Regional Conference in Sydney. She got funding for the conference from the United Nations Development Program in New York-'probably the hardest thing I ever had to do'. Scotford was made a life member and a vice-president of ICW in 1979, in recognition of her skills and commitment in organising this and several later events for the ICW Board. She attended the United Nations Mid-Decade Conference for Women in Copenhagen in 1980, the United Nations World Conference for Women in Nairobi in 1985, the UNESCO General Conference in Paris in 1983, and the United Nations Conference on Decolonisation in Port Moresby in 1984.</p>
<p>In Australia, Scotford's work with the National Councils led her to undertake a range of voluntary positions: membership of the State Committee for Human Rights Year 1968; chair of the Sydney Opera House Festival Women's Committee in 1973; membership of the board of governors of the Law Foundation of New South Wales, 1974-1977, the first non-legal woman so appointed; membership of the Council for the Royal Flying Doctor Service; and membership of the Standing Committee of Convocation at Macquarie University.</p>
<p>In 1977, Scotford was appointed executive officer of the Cultural Council of the City of Sydney. This involved the organisation of the City of Sydney Eisteddfod, an event with over 20,000 entrants, and also a more general brief to promote the performing and creative arts in the city.</p>
<p>In her later years, Scotford wrote a historical novel, <span style="font-style:italic">The Distaff Side</span>. It follows her ancestral female lines, to her great grandmothers and beyond. She wrote that 'I wanted to honour my ancestors, not because they were great heroines, but because of the sort of people they were-steady, and good'. The book was published in 1996 by Harper Collins.</p>
<p>Jessie Scotford was active for many years on the presbytery of St David's church, Lindfield, and, with the union of the Presbyterian, Congregational and Methodist churches in 1977, she became an Elder in the Uniting Church of Australia-'perhaps my greatest honour'. In 1976 she told an all-women service in St David's that the impact of International Women's Year was like a huge submerged ocean current whose force was not yet felt. Women are rising in slow persistent waves to effect a 'revolution that is as vital a part of human progress as the discovery of the wheel, the invention of the printing press or the conquest of space'.</p>
<chronList><chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1973-01-01">1973</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1973-12-31">1973</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Presided - Festival Women's Committee for the opening of the Sydney Opera House</event>
</chronItem>
<chronItem>
<dateRange><fromDate standardDate="1995-01-01">c. 1995</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1995-12-31">c. 1995</toDate>
</dateRange>
<event>Chair - Central West Region Women's Committee of the National Trust of Australia NSW</event>
</chronItem>
</chronList>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0555b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Council of Women of New South Wales (1896 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1966-01-01">1966</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1970-12-31">1970</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0067b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Council of Women of Australia (1931 - )
</relationEntry>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1970-01-01">1970</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1973-12-31">1973</toDate>
</dateRange>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4928b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Giddings, Maureen
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1665901">
<relationEntry>
Scotford, Jessie Margaret (19171110-20030513)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Scotford, Jessie Margaret', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Scotford, Jessie Margaret</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4940b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005572.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Conference Paper: Education for Citizenship</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Scotford, Jessie</name>
<title render="quoted">Education for Citizenship</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Sutherland</publisher>
<date>1970</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian Local Government Women's Association Convention</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005571.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Conference Paper: A Super Achiever</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Scotford, Jessie</name>
<title render="quoted">A Super Achiever</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>Australian Federation of University Women</publisher>
<date>1995</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Positive Ageing: Recognition and Reward</title>
<num type="pages">96 - 97</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005570.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Journal: NCWA Quarterly Bulletin</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">National Council of Australian Women</name>
<title render="italic">NCWA Quarterly Bulletin</title>
<imprint>
<date>1974</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005569.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The Distaff Side: An Epic Saga Spanning Five Generations of Women</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Scotford, Jessica</name>
<title render="italic">The Distaff Side: An Epic Saga Spanning Five Generations of Women</title>
<imprint>
<place>Pymble, NSW</place>
<publisher>Harper Collins</publisher>
<date>1996</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP001308.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who in Australia, 1971</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Legge, J S</name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who in Australia, 1971</title>
<edition>20</edition>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>The Herald and Weekly Times</publisher>
<date>1971</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP000147.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who of Australian Women</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Lofthouse, Andrea</name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who of Australian Women</title>
<imprint>
<place>North Ryde (NSW)</place>
<publisher>Methuen Australia</publisher>
<date>1982</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005528.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Stirrers with Style! Presidents of the National Council of Women of Australia and its predecessors</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">National Council of Women of Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Stirrers with Style! Presidents of the National Council of Women of Australia and its predecessors</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/ncwa"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002733.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">NCWA Papers 1984 - 2006</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>NCWA Papers 1984 - 2006</unittitle>
<unitid>MS07/096</unitid>
<unitdate>1984 - 2006</unitdate>
<abstract>MS07/096</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>manuscript</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002731.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1924-1990 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1924-1990 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS7583</unitid>
<unitdate>1924 - 1990</unitdate>
<abstract>MS 7583 comprises correspondence, board minutes, executive records, conference records and papers relating to submissions and campaigns. There are also papers relating to the International Council of Women (24 boxes).

The Acc GB 1993/1502 instalment comprises records of the National Council of Women of the Australian Capital Territory and includes minutes, correspondence, membership lists, reports, including annual reports for 1952-1990, photographs, cuttings and financial records (4 cartons, 1 small carton).

The Acc07/96 instalment comprises records relating to seminars and conferences, policy and the history of the National Council of Women of Australia, correspondence, publications, submission papers and meeting minutes (35 boxes).
The National Council of Women of Australia originated with various state councils, the first being formed in 1896 in New South Wales. In 1931 the Australian National Council of Women was founded as a non-profit organisation promoting women's issues and social welfare. In 1970 the Council's name was changed to the National Council of Women of Australia. The Council is an affiliated member of the International Council of Women, a federation of non-government organisations in many countries.
Manuscript reference no.: MS 7583, MS Acc GB 1993/­1502, MS Acc07/­96.

Associated materials: Records of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1936-1972 MS 5193.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>10.25 m, 59 Boxes + 4 cartons + 1 small carton.</extent>
<physfacet>manuscript</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001893.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">National Council of Women of New South Wales - further records, ca. 1895-2004</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>National Council of Women of New South Wales - further records, ca. 1895-2004</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 3739</unitid>
<unitdate>1895 - 2004</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection includes a number of add on's listed at different URL's.

Key reference number is MLMss 3739. Listed online at: http://acms.sl.nsw.gov.au/item/itemDetailPaged.aspx?itemID=845141

Add on call numbers :
- 2088
- 1690
- 2061


material concerning the Centenary year, 1996; Captain Cook Bi-centennial celebrations, 1970; minute books; newsletters; annual reports; photographs including Rose Scott, Lady Windeyer, Miles Franklin, Dame Mary Gilmore, Margaret Windeyer; balance sheets; booklets; seminars and papers; reports and letters; audio tapes; video tapes; newscuttings.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>4 boxes</extent>
<physfacet>Paper files and documents</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002746.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jessie Scotford interviewed by Hazel de Berg for the Hazel de Berg collection [sound recording]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Oral History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Jessie Scotford interviewed by Hazel de Berg for the Hazel de Berg collection [sound recording]</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 1/1010</unitid>
<unitdate>7 July 1977</unitdate>
<abstract>Bibliographic Id: 3005284

Scotford speaks of her work as the Executive Director of the Cultural Council of the City of Sydney ; of her interest in the National Trust and the International Council of Women. Scotford relates some details of her childhood and family environment.

Transcript also available.

ORAL TRC 1/1010</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 sound tape reel (ca. 36 min.)</extent>
<physfacet>Audio</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00882.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Jessie Scotford</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>NHCA Quarterly Bulletin, Feb-March 1971 2; NHCA</repository>
<unittitle>Jessie Scotford</unittitle>
<unitdate>1971</unitdate>
<note label="rights">Courtesy of National Council of Women Australia.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>