<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4734</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2011-01-10">2011-01-10</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Hollie Aerts</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4734b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Donaldson</part>
<part localType="givenname">Mona</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1900-01-01">1900</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Film editor</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Mona Donaldson is an important figure in early Australian film production and worked as film editor on numerous quintessentially Australian films.

In February 1915, at the age of 15, Mona Donaldson began work for Australasian Films in Sydney as a film examiner. In 1917, she moved to Paramount and worked first as a film examiner and then a booking clerk. In 1921, Donaldson left work to take care of her mother. Once she could return to work, her previous work experience again allowed her a job with Australasian Films.

Donaldson soon became known for her competence and perfectionism. This was said to have led to a reputation of being formal and distant.

Many of Donaldson's early editing is uncredited. In an interview with Andree Wright and Stuart Young in the 1980s, Donaldson described cutting for Whyte's <span style="font-style:italic">Painted Daughters</span> (1925), Webb's <span style="font-style:italic">Tall Timber </span>(1926) and <span style="font-style:italic">The Grey Glove</span> (1928) and Longford's <span style="font-style:italic">Hills of Hate</span> (1926) and <span style="font-style:italic">The Pioneers</span> (1926).

Donaldson's first clear onscreen recognition for editing was in <span style="font-style:italic">For the Term of His Natural Life</span> (Dawn, 1927). The silent film was based on a novel by Marcus Clarke of the same name and tells the story of an English aristocrat who is transported for life as a convict to Van Dieman's Land for a crime he did not commit.

Donaldson again worked with director Norman Dawn on his film <span style="font-style:italic">The Adorable Outcast</span> (1927). The film was based on the romantic adventure novel, <span style="font-style:italic">Conn of the Coral Seas </span>by Beatrice Grimshaw.

In 1928, Lacey Percival, a colleague from Australasian Films, left and started Automatic Films. He invited Donaldson to join him. Donaldson used this job offer to attempt to get a pay raise from Australasian Films, however they refused and she began work for Automatic Films.

While working at Automatic Films, Donaldson was 'loaned out' to work on other feature films. She re-edited Chauvel's <span style="font-style:italic">Heritage</span> (1935), which then won the Australian Film Award in 1935. She worked again with Chauvel on <span style="font-style:italic">Uncivilised</span> (1936). Donaldson also co-edited Badger's <span style="font-style:italic">Rangle River</span> (1936). In 1937, Donaldson edited Chauvel's documentary about how screen tests were conducted, <span style="font-style:italic">Screen Test.</span>

In 1946, after working for Automatic Films for eighteen years, Donaldson fell ill and was hospitalised for seven months. During this time, Donaldson was denied sick leave and she was fired. Both Cinesound and Commonwealth Film Laboratories offered her employment, however she decided to leave the film industry completely.

Upon retirement from the Australian film industry, Donaldson bought a shop in Chatswood and became a successful milliner.</abstract>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE3704b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Jenner, Dorothy Gordon (Andrea) (1891 - 1985)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote>
<p>Gordon and Donaldson both worked on the movie <span style="font-style:italic">Hills of Hate. </span></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477683">
<relationEntry>
Donaldson, Mona (1900-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Donaldson, Mona', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Donaldson, Mona</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4734b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004846.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Australian Film 1900-1977: A Guide to Feature Film Production</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Pike, Andrew and Cooper, Ross</name>
<title render="italic">Australian Film 1900-1977: A Guide to Feature Film Production</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
<date>1980</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002536.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">The Grey Glove</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>The Grey Glove</unittitle>
<unitid>343589</unitid>
<unitdate>1928</unitdate>
<abstract>Documentation relating to the making of the film <span style="font-style:italic">The Grey Glove</span> edited by Mona Donaldson</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002535.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Black Cargo of the South Seas</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Black Cargo of the South Seas</unittitle>
<unitid>1822</unitid>
<unitdate>1928</unitdate>
<abstract>Feature Film (silent). A Pacific Island romance about a young adventurer, Stephen Conn, and his love for Luya. -- General notes: This is the US release title of the Australian film, 'The Adorable Outcast' (see related title), which has survived with substantially more scenes -- Shot on location in the Fiji Islands with interiors at Australasian's Bondi studios in Sydney, the film had many native extras and three American players (Burns, Roberts and Long) -- Locations show authentic native villages, sailing craft, and a spectacular longhouse built on an atoll -- Originally 7300 feet, surviving 6300 feet (35mm, 93 mins @ 18fps). Access copies: 35mm, 16mm</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002534.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Screen Test</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Screen Test</unittitle>
<unitid>11281</unitid>
<unitdate>1937</unitdate>
<abstract>Documentary produced by Charles Chauvel and edited by Mona Donaldson that focuses on the screen test process.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002533.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">For the Term of His Natural Life</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>For the Term of His Natural Life</unittitle>
<unitid>231</unitid>
<unitdate>1927</unitdate>
<abstract>Feature film (silent) edited by Mona Donoldson. Van Dieman's Land for a crime he did not commit, and his enduring love for Sylvia, the daughter of a prison governor. -- General notes: Four of the principals in the cast, Eva Novak, George Fisher, Steve Murphy and Katherine Dawn were Americans, as was the director, Norman Dawn and the principle cameraman, Len Roos. Shot on location in New South Wales at Berrima, Wombeyan Caves and Sydney Harbour, as well as in Tasmania at the ruins of the convict settlement at Port Arthur, the film portrays some fine scenes of the convicts in the penal colony and also puts on screen some special effects such as 'glass shots' which enabled Dawn to 'restore' roofs to the derelict buildings at Port Arthur. Hundreds of extras were employed on the film. The use of Americans in the production was hoped to ensure American release. -- There was public opposition to the film at the time it was made concerning its portrayal of this less favourable aspect of Australia's white history. -- Originally 10 000 feet of 35mm, surviving substantially complete at 2448 feet of 16mm. The film has been restored as a tinted 35mm print with music. -- Access copies: 35mm (restored, tinted, music), 16mm, video. Documentation associated with the production of the movie exists in the NFSA collection.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002532.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">The Adorable Outcast</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>The Adorable Outcast</unittitle>
<unitid>125</unitid>
<unitdate>1927</unitdate>
<abstract>Feature film (silent) edited by Mona Donaldson. A Pacific Island romance about a young adventurer, Stephen Conn, and his love for Luya. -- General notes: Several scenes survive, although heavy nitrate damage is visible -- Shot on location in the Fiji Islands with interiors at Australasian's Bondi studios in Sydney, the film had many native extras and three American players (Burns, Roberts and Long) -- Locations show authentic native villages, sailing craft, and a spectacular longhouse built on an atoll -- An incomplete print of the American release title, 'Black Cargo of the South Seas', has survived with substantially more scenes (see related title). -- The script for the film was written by Norman Dawn from the novel, "Conn of the Coral Seas", by Beatrice Grimshaw. There is documentation associated with the making of the movie in the NFSA collection.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002531.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Donaldson, Mona: Interviewed By Andree Wright and Stuart Young: Oral History</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Donaldson, Mona: Interviewed By Andree Wright and Stuart Young: Oral History</unittitle>
<unitid>274184</unitid>
<abstract>Mona Donaldson, feature film editor, discusses her career. Source material for 'Don't Call Me Girlie'. Mona discusses her experience of working with several film companies including : Australasian [examination and film repair], Paramount [1917-1921], the difficulties of working as an editor in the film industry and her experience of working with Raymond Longford, editing such works as 'Pioneers'. [01:36:05]

Recorded 29 August 1983</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00526.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Carty, William: Group Shot Showing Staff at the Rushcutters Bay Studio, 1923</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<unittitle>Carty, William: Group Shot Showing Staff at the Rushcutters Bay Studio, 1923</unittitle>
<unitid>348976-1039</unitid>
<unitdate>1923</unitdate>
<abstract>From left to right: Bill Carty, Arthur Hanson, Charlie Elliers, Mona Donaldson, Phil Markham and Bill Jackson</abstract>
<note label="rights">These digital items are provided for research purposes only and can not be reproduced without the prior consent of the National Film and Sound Archive.</note>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>