<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE4722</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2010-12-23">2010-12-23</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Hollie Aerts</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4722b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Johnson</part>
<part localType="givenname">Darlene</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Director</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Scriptwriter</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Darlene Johnson is one of Australia's most prominent indigenous filmmakers.
Her films and documentaries are centered upon Aboriginal identity and the position of Aboriginals within contemporary Australian society.</abstract>
<p>Darlene Johnson is from the Dunghutti tribe from the east coast of New South Wales. Johnson graduated with First Class Honours from the University of Technology, Sydney, majoring in Indigenous and Post-Colonial cinema.</p>
<p>In 1996, Johnson wrote and directed <span style="font-style:italic">Two Bob Mermaid: A Short Film About Aboriginal Identity.</span> The short film was set in the summer of 1957, a period of racial tension as government policy shifted its approach towards Aboriginal rights. The film followed the story of a young Koori girl who 'passes for white' at the local swimming pool. <span style="font-style:italic">Two Bob Mermaid</span> won the Australian Film Critics Circle Award for the Best Australian Short Film in 1996. Today the film is used as a teaching resource in primary and secondary schools throughout Australia.</p>
<p>In c.2000, Johnson wrote and directed the documentary <span style="font-style:italic">Stolen Generations.</span> The film employed personal testimony, archival footage and photographs to tell the history of assimilation. The Government policy of assimilation involved the systematic removal of Aboriginal children from their families. The documentary addressed the reasons behind the policy, how it was implemented and maintained, and how it continues to affect Aboriginals. <span style="font-style:italic">Stolen Generations</span> was nominated for an International EMMY as well as an Australian Film Institute award for Best Documentary.</p>
<p>In 2001, Johnson wrote and directed the documentary <span style="font-style:italic">Stranger in My Skin</span> for Film Australia. She also directed the documentary <span style="font-style:italic">Following Rabbit Proof Fence</span> which traced the journey of three young Aboriginal girls from their communities to starring in a Hollywood movie. In 2002, Johnson wrote and directed the documentary <span style="font-style:italic">Gulpilil: One Red Blood</span>, about the Aboriginal actor David Gulpilil. Gulpilil was nominated for a Logie Award, an Australian Film Critics Circle Award and an Australian Teachers of Media (ATOM) Award.</p>
<p>In 2006, she wrote and directed <span style="font-style:italic">Crocodile Dreaming.</span> <span style="font-style:italic">Crocodile Dreaming</span> tells the story of a traditional Aboriginal community that upsets the spiritual world. As a result, a young man from the tribe is called to fulfill his ancient tribal obligation and find the power of his mother's dreaming. It is his success that will restore peace and harmony to the natural world. The film received a number of international nominations and awards, including an AFI Award for visual effects. It was featured at the Melbourne International Film Festival 2007, and Flickerfest in Sydney 2008. It won the Audience Choice Award at the WOW Film Festival in Sydney and won Best Short Film at the Santa Fe Film Festival in New Mexico 2007.</p>
<p>In 2007, Johnson graduated from the Australian Film, Television and Radio School with a Master of Arts (Hons).</p>
<p>In 2008, she directed the documentary <span style="font-style:italic">River of No Return</span>. The film followed the story of Frances Djulibing, a 42 year old mother of three from the remote Ramingining community in North East Arnhem land. Frances had always dreamt of acting and stardom, despite living a traditional tribal life. Her acting break came with a role in the successful Australian film <span style="font-style:italic">Ten Canoes</span> (2006). The documentary highlighted the difficulties Frances faced in her attempt to reconcile her pursuit of an acting career with the cultural opposition from the ancient life of the Yolgnu.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1160b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Moffatt, Tracey (1960 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1160b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Moffatt, Tracey (1960 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477674">
<relationEntry>
Johnson, Darlene
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Johnson, Darlene', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Johnson, Darlene</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4722b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004850.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Article: Lights Up! - Indigenous Filmmakers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Hessey, Ruth</name>
<title render="quoted">Lights Up! - Indigenous Filmmakers</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Time Out Group Ltd.</publisher>
<date>2008</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Time Out Sydney</title>
<num type="issue">28</num>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.timeoutsydney.com.au/film/indigenous-filmmakers-28.aspx"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004849.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Showcases</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Screen Australia</name>
<title render="italic">Showcases</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Screen Australia</publisher>
<date>2010</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.screenaustralia.gov.au/showcases/8478/bios.asp"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004848.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Resource: Darlene Johnson</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Ronin Films</name>
<title render="italic">Darlene Johnson</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Ronin Films</publisher>
<date>2010</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.roninfilms.com.au/person/136.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002491.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Crocodile Dreaming</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Crocodile Dreaming</unittitle>
<unitid>712058</unitid>
<unitdate>2006</unitdate>
<abstract>Short Film directed by Darlene Johnson. Crocodile Dreaming is the story of two estranged half-brothers, Burrimmila and Charlie, who must struggle against their own jealousy and distrust for each other. When there is a violent death in the community upsetting the spiritual world, Burrimmilla is unexpectedly called upon to fulfill an ancient tribal obligation. As a result he embarks on a journey to find the sacred stone which holds the power of his mother's dreaming. If he finds the stone, he must return it to its secret belonging place. When the brothers finally come together, they are confronted by the spirit of their mother, who leads them to the special creation place, and the possibility of restoring peace and harmony in the natural world. There is a significant amount of documentation assocaited with the making of the film in the NFSA collection.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Video and WMV file</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002490.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Gulpilil: One Red Blood</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Gulpilil: One Red Blood</unittitle>
<unitid>560179</unitid>
<unitdate>2002</unitdate>
<abstract>Documentary film directed by Darlene Johnson. David Gulpilil is one of the most highly respected Aboriginal actors of his generation. At the same time he is an elder of the Yolngu clan in Arnhem Land in Northern Australia. This documentary looks at Gulpilil's continuing struggle to regain control over his life. (00:55:00). -- General note: summary from FFC production notes.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Video and WMV file</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002489.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">River of No Return</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>River of No Return</unittitle>
<unitid>759093</unitid>
<unitdate>2008</unitdate>
<abstract>Documentary directed by Darlene Johnson. Frances Djulibing is a 42 year old mother of three who comes from the remote community of Ramingining in North East Arnhem land. Like many young girls, Frances always dreamed of being a movie star. Her journey from traditional tribal life to red carpets and awards ceremonies is unlike any other. It's a fascinating and unique story as Frances fights to overcome huge personal and cultural challenges. Yappa's Story is a story of change and transformation as Frances learns to move between the ancient life of the Yolgnu and modern world of the balanda.

There is a significant amount of documentary material related to the making of this film in the NFSA catalogue.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Tape</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002487.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Two Bob Mermaid: A Short Film About Aboriginal Identity</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Two Bob Mermaid: A Short Film About Aboriginal Identity</unittitle>
<unitid>306361</unitid>
<unitdate>1996</unitdate>
<abstract>Short Film directed by Darlene Johnson. Set in the summer of 1957, 'Two Bob Mermaid' is about a young Koori girl who 'passes for white' at the local swimming pool. It is a story about Aboriginal identity, transformation and change, set in a period of cultural conflict and racial tension.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Video and WMV file</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002488.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Stolen Generations</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Film and Sound Archive</repository>
<unittitle>Stolen Generations</unittitle>
<unitid>448627</unitid>
<unitdate>2000</unitdate>
<abstract>Documentary scripted and directed by Darlene Johnson. account based on personal testimony, and examines the reasons why the policy of assimilation and removal of Aboriginal children was introduced and maintained for so long. It reveals some of the long term effects of the policy and shows why the stolen generations are as much a part of our present as they are of our past. -- General notes: The documentary combines intimate interviews with archival footage and still photographs and subtle recreations. -- Source of information: FFC publicity notes. There is a significant amount of documentation relating to the makin gof this movie in the NFSA collection.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Tape and WMV file</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>