<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE5648</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-09">2016-05-09</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Nicola Silbert</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-09">2016-05-09</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5648b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Wilson</part>
<part localType="givenname">Margaret</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Queensland, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Lawyer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Solicitor</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Barrister</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Queen's Counsel</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Judge</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Commissioner</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Margaret Wilson is a trailblazing judge, particularly in the areas of mental health and civil procedure.</abstract>
<p>Although Margaret Wilson came from a non-legal family, she became a trailblazing judge, particularly in the areas of mental health and civil procedure. After graduating as school captain and dux, Margaret won open scholarship at University of Queensland. Having initially enrolled in a Bachelor of Arts, Margaret began studying law subjects in her third year at university and soon became absorbed by them. She graduated with an LLB with Honours in 1976, having completed her Arts degree in 1973.</p>
<p>After completing her articles, Margaret practised as a solicitor for six months. However, she did not enjoy the environment of the commercial legal practice. She resigned, travelled to the United Kingdom on an extended holiday, and upon her return was admitted to the Queensland Bar, on 29 March 1979. Margaret had a successful career at the Bar, enjoying the individual pursuit of professionalism. She was appointed Queen's Counsel in 1992 and as a judge of the Supreme Court of Queensland six years later.</p>
<p>In 2002, Margaret was appointed as the judge constituting the new Mental Health Court. The Court is the only one of its kind in Australia, if not the world. Consisting of a Supreme Court judge and two government-appointed assisting psychiatrists, the court determines whether individuals who have been accused of criminal offences were of unsound mind at the time of the alleged offences. Justice Wilson oversaw a number of procedural changes in the Mental Health Court to make it as accessible and efficient as possible and add transparency. From 2009 to 2011, Margaret was a Commercial List Judge of the Supreme Court of Queensland. For the following year, she sat on the Queensland Court of Appeal. From 2014 onwards, Margaret has sat on the Court of Appeal of Solomon Islands.</p>
<p>Margaret has been an active contributor to procedural reform. She was a member of the Civil Procedure Division of the Litigation Reform Commission from 1994 to 1996 and has been a member of the Rules Committee since 1999. The Committee's work has included the introduction of the Uniform Civil Procedure Rules and their constant refinement which makes Court procedures more contemporary and user-friendly. Margaret has helped prepare booklets for jurors that explain the process of jury deliberation and also the counselling services now available to jurors.</p>
<p>Margaret is a committee member of the Bar Association of Queensland. Her work as the convenor of its Continuing Legal Education sub-committee has been transposed into a commitment to ongoing judicial education. She has consistently contributed to the organisation of the annual Supreme Court of Queensland Judges' Seminar.</p>
<p>Margaret also presided over a Commission of Inquiry into the closure of a residential mental health facility for adolescents.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Wilson, Margaret', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Wilson, Margaret</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5648b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005880.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Margaret Wilson</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Keenan, Sarah and Batch, Margaret Mary</name>
<title render="quoted">Margaret Wilson</title>
<imprint>
<place>Brisbane</place>
<publisher>Supreme Court of Queensland Library</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">A Woman's Place: 100 Years of Queensland Women Lawyers</title>
<name type="author">Susan Purdon and Aladin Rahemtula</name>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>