<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE5634</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-04-27">2016-04-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Rachel Wallbank</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-04-27">2016-04-27</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5634b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Wallbank</part>
<part localType="givenname">Rachel</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1956-01-01">1956</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Lawyer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Solicitor</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Human rights advocate</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Rachael Wallbank is an Accredited Specialist (Family Law LSNSW) and principal of the legal practice Wallbanks Legal. She represented and appeared on behalf of 'Kevin' and 'Jennifer' at trial in Re Kevin: Validity of Marriage of Transsexual (2001) 28 Fam LR 158 and on appeal in The Attorney-General for the Commonwealth &amp; "Kevin and Jennifer" &amp; Human Rights and Equal Opportunity Commission [2003] FamCA 94 whereby the Applicants' marriage was declared to be valid and the law of Australia was determined so that Australians who experience diversity or Difference in Sexual formation, including Transsexualism gained the right to be declared male or female, as the case may be, at law and to legally marry in their affirmed sex.

Wallbank also acted and appeared for the Applicant Parents as in Re Bernadette [2010] FamCA 94; the first case in Australia to authorise Phase 1 Treatment to suspend puberty for an adolescent living with the condition of Transsexualism (as an interim order in 2005) and the first case to challenge the Australian legal regime initiated by Re Alex (2004) FLC 93-175 which requires court authorisation of Phase 1 and 2 Treatments as a precondition for treatment.

Wallbank is a member of the Legal Issues Committee of the World Professional Association for Transgender Health (WPATH) and a founding member of the Australian and New Zealand Professional Association for Transgender Health (ANZPATH).

Wallbank has writes academically and undertakes lectures and presentations on the subject of the legal and human rights of people who experience diversity or Difference in sexual formation, including Transsexualism, as well as those who experience diversity or Difference in gender expression; especially with regard to Australia. Wallbank appears regularly in the media as a public advocate and legal expert on the subject.</abstract>
<p>Born on 4 March 1956, as Richard Wallbank, Rachael attended St Patrick's College Strathfield in Sydney and the University of New South Wales. Rachael was admitted to practise as a solicitor on 4 July 1980. Rachael has three adult children, Kate, Rebecca and James.</p>
<p>Rachael began her legal career working as a student clerk and later junior solicitor under the tutelage of John Newnham at Messrs Fred A. and John F. Newnham of Sydney. Rachael was eventually promoted to Associate at that practice. Rachael established her own legal practice, Wallbanks Legal, on 1 July 1985. Wallbanks Legal is a specialist practice concerned with Family, Estate and Succession Law. Rachael has also obtained post-graduate qualifications in mediation and alternative dispute resolution at the University of Western Sydney, is qualified as a Collaborative Lawyer and is an Accredited Specialist in Family Law as awarded by the Specialist Accreditation Board of the Law Society of New South Wales.</p>
<p>Rachael was aware of her female self in childhood. In the circumstances of the times, however, and although she was referred to doctors by her parents for being found dressing in her sister's clothes and telling them "I'm really a girl" at about 7 years of age, the condition remained unrecognised, unexplained and untreated until adulthood. As for all young people who experienced Transsexualism in the 1960's, Rachael's adolescence and young adulthood were extremely confusing, painful, filled with secretive shame-filled exploration and expression of her innate female self.</p>
<p>For example, at 17 years of age, at the same time as playing Flanker in her school's 2nd 15 Rugby Union team, Rachael was also secretly working as an assistant in a nearby hairdressing salon, learning about makeup and hair, and undertook her first secret solo car trip as a female during which she enjoyed her first dinner date and romantic evening as a female at Goulbourn.</p>
<p>Through a period of much suffering for herself and her family, especially her children and her then wife, Louise, Rachael transitioned public sex on 4 July 1994, undertook sex affirmation procedures including genital surgery in 1995/6 and had her legal sex reassigned to female in New South Wales on 17 July 1997. Rachael deeply appreciates that her family were all obliged to share in the social and personal suffering associated with her Difference and her public affirmation of her innate female self and that without her children's love and support this entry would not exist.</p>
<p>Rachael is grateful that her life and legal career has presented her with the opportunity to achieve significant legal and human rights reform for people of all ages who experience Transsexualism and to advance the understanding of that phenomena as a naturally occurring form of difference or diversity in human sexual formation and an intersexual disorder of sexual development with a clearly therapeutic and successful medical treatment protocol - and not a mental disorder.</p>
<p>Re Kevin has been relied upon in several landmark international decisions; including I v The United Kingdom and Christine Goodwin v The United Kingdom decided by the European Court of Human Rights. These decisions, which quote Justice Chisholm's decision in Re Kevin at length and with approval, finally determined that there had been violations of articles 8, 12, 13 and 14 of the Convention for the Protection of Human Rights and Fundamental Freedoms in respect of the legal status of people who experienced Transsexualism in the United Kingdom and, in particular, such people's treatment in the spheres of employment, social security, pensions and marriage. As a result of these decisions the government of the United Kingdom introduced the Gender Recognition Act 2004.</p>
<p>Re Kevin has also relied upon in the United States of America. In the landmark decision of Justice O'Brien in the Florida case called The Marriage of Kantaras, his Honour said at page 673 '...it is essential that Kevin not be given a mere "citation" but studied for what it represents in the law. It is one of the most important cases on transsexualism to come on the scene of foreign jurisprudence.'</p>
<p>Rachael continues to provide legal advice and representation for parents of young Australians living with Transsexualism and to advocate for the abandonment of the requirement imposed by the Family Court of Australia for court authorisation of time critical therapeutic hormonal treatment for Australian adolescents who experience Transsexualism; with all the unnecessary suffering that inevitably results from non-treatment or delayed treatment. Rachael continues to advocate for a better cultural understanding and acceptance of Difference and the recognition of the human and legal rights of Transsexualism in Australia and throughout the world.</p>
<p>Enjoying her 21st birthday as an affirmed female in 2015, Rachael is proud to be both female and Different and is now one of those fortunate people who do not fear if the family parrot falls into the hands of the town gossip.</p>
<p>Significant Presentations by Rachael Wallbank:</p>
<list><br />
<item>The inaugural (2013) Isabelle Lake Memorial Lecture for the Equal Opportunity Commission Western Australia and The University of Western Australia</item><br />
<item> 'Medico/Legal Issues in the Treatment of Young People With Transsexualism", XVIII World Congress of the World Association of Sexual Health (WAS) - 1st World Congress For Sexual Health (April 2007) Darling Harbour, Sydney, Australia.</item><br />
<item> 'Human Rights and Diversity in Sexual Formation and Expression', XXIII ILGA World Conference (March 2006) Geneva, Switzerland.</item><br />
<item> 'Children with Transsexualism - From Difference to Disorder', The Fourth World Congress on Family Law and Children's Rights (2005), Cape Town, South Africa.</item><br />
<item> 'Difference on Trial" presentation and paper, 11th National Biennial Conference of the Family Law Section of the Law Council of Australia 2004, Conference Handbook (2004) TEN, GPO Box 61A Melbourne, VIC, 3000, Australia'</item><br />
</list>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Wallbank, Rachel', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Wallbank, Rachel</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5634b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005873.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newsletter: Re Alex - Through a Looking Glass'</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Wallbank, Rachel</name>
<title render="italic">Re Alex - Through a Looking Glass'</title>
<imprint>
<date>2004</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Australian Children’s Rights News</title>
<num type="issue">37</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005871.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Wallbank, Rachel</name>
<title render="quoted">Australia</title>
<imprint>
<place>United Kingdom</place>
<publisher>Intersentia</publisher>
<date>2015</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The Legal Status of Transsexual and Transgender Persons</title>
<name type="author">Scherpe, Jens M.</name>
<num type="pages">pp. 457 - 526</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005874.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Speaking Secrets: Sex and sexuality as public property</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Joseph, Sue</name>
<title render="italic">Speaking Secrets: Sex and sexuality as public property</title>
<imprint>
<place>Buderim</place>
<publisher>alto Books</publisher>
<date>2013</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>