<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE5399</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-08-26">2015-08-26</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Patricia Clarke</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5399b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Lawler</part>
<part localType="givenname">Gertrude Frances</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1879-03-01">1 March 1879?</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Grantham, England</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Ireland ?</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Nurse</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Army Nurse</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Gertrude Frances Lawler served briefly in India with the Australian Army Nursing Service during World War I. She enlisted in 1917 after Canberra Hospital, where she was employed as matron/dispenser, closed and resumed her position when the hospital reopened in 1921.</abstract>
<p>Gertrude Frances Lawler was Matron of Canberra Hospital both before and after her service with the Australian Army Nursing Service. She had been matron at Deniliquin Hospital when she was appointed matron/dispenser at Canberra in February 1917 at a time when the hospital was already running down as construction work in the Capital slowed to a halt in wartime. Her employment at Canberra Hospital ceased in October 1917 when the hospital closed and she enlisted on 5 November in Melbourne. On her enlistment form she stated she was born at Grantham, England on 1 March 1879, was a widow aged 29, her permanent place of residence was Sunbury, Victoria and her religion was Church of England. She named her next-of-kin as her step-brother, Lt J.A. Underwood of Seymour, Victoria.</p>
<p>Soon after enlisting Gertrude was on the Indarra on route to Bombay to nurse in India. She arrived on 18 December 1917 and was immediately admitted to hospital sick. After about three weeks in hospital she was posted to the Station Hospital at Bangalore on the Deccan Plateau in southern India. Like other Australian nurses in India she was sent in response to a British Government request for nurses to staff British hospitals. The nurses who arrived in December 1917 and other groups which arrived in 1918, found little demand for their services. Gertrude nursed at Bangalore for about six months and arrived back in Melbourne early in September. She was discharged in November 1918.</p>
<p>In 1921 when Canberra Hospital re-opened Gertrude Lawler who had obtained an undertaking in 1917 that she would be reinstated, returned as matron/dispenser and remained in the position until 1928 when she was criticised at an official inquiry and resigned.</p>
<p>Gertrude Lawler appears in reminiscences and histories of Canberra as an exuberant, controversial, rather eccentric Irishwoman. She was described as 'nearly six feet tall, with black hair, blue eyes, a very strong Irish brogue and a fiery temper'. She was portrayed as warm hearted towards friends but implacable towards enemies and a sympathetic matron who became one of Canberra's best known figures, riding side-saddle to the workmen's camps to treat her patients. A sociable and outgoing personality in a city where there were few amenities, she made the hospital a social centre entertaining visiting parliamentarians and dignitaries at dances and social events. She was even known to dance on tables.</p>
<p>The account of her background and qualifications, as recorded in several sources, such as her enlistment papers, ACT Government Archives, early histories and other published sources, became her accepted life story. But there are many questions about her, for example, about her birth which does not appear in English records and the discrepancy in stating she was born in 1879 and was aged 29 late in 1917 - by then she would have been 39; her claim to be the daughter of the late Captain Michael Lawler R.E., sister of the late Major Jim Lawler R.E. and of the late Captain Michael Lawler, I.N. [?] and her extensive nursing and pharmaceutical training in Dublin and England. Also her claim to be a widow. There are many mysteries about Gertrude Lawler.</p>
<p>Her claim about her father and brothers first raised alarm bells. None has been traced in British Army records. In the same article published originally in the journal, The Chemist and Druggist of Australasia, she stated she was a cousin of the late Captain Harry Linford AIF, Imperial Camel Corps. Linford, a labourer, enlisted in the AIF in 1915 and was a 2nd Lieutenant when he was killed in action in January 1917 in the Battle of Rafa during the Sinai Palestine campaign. On his enlistment papers he named Gertrude Lawler as his next of kin and allocated her three shillings per day. After his death his widow, Mrs Linford of Cape Town, South Africa, the mother of several children, wrote to the Australian Army and his Army record was changed to record her as his wife. Linford was born in England and had served with the English Lancers. A letter in a National Archives file in which Linford refers to Gertrude as 'my dearest Gerty' and several times as 'dear' may give the impression that they were lovers rather than cousins. Her claim that Joseph Alexander Underwood was her step brother is also difficult to verify. Underwood was born in Violet Town, Victoria in 1886 and both his mother and father were born in Violet Town and lived there all their lives. There is no indication that either his father or mother was married more than once.</p>
<p>Gertrude Lawler appears to have migrated to Victoria about 1912. Her first position was at the Hospital for Insane at Sunbury, just outside Melbourne. She then joined the Bush Nursing Association and was stationed at Edenhope near the South Australian border until she was appointed Matron at Deniliquin Hospital in October 1916.</p>
<p>There is no doubt Gertrude Lawler was a well-qualified nurse. She had several articles published in Una: The Journal of the Royal Victorian Trained Nurses' Association in 1915 each of which was awarded 'The Miss Lyons' Prize Essay'. The titles included: 'Treatment of Post Partum Haemorrhage'; 'Laryngeal Diphtheria'; 'Acute Mania' and 'Compound Fracture of the Femur caused by gunshot'. In various statements she said she trained at Richmond Royal Hospital near London receiving a 3-year certificate in 1907; that she completed a two-year course in Midwifery and Gynaecology at Holles St Royal Hospital and trained as a pharmacist at the Rotunda Hospital, both famous hospitals in Dublin, and that she had a qualification in infectious diseases. The absence of records makes it difficult to trace details of this training.</p>
<p>She had been Matron at Deniliquin only a few months when she was appointed Matron/Dispenser at Canberra Hospital early in 1917. This appointment is another mystery in Gertrude Lawler's life. She was not among the eleven applicants listed in an Archives file. From the applicants Matron Marsden of Goulburn Hospital was chosen to be interviewed. Then there is a gap in the small file until arrangements were made for Gertrude Lawler to travel to Canberra via Yass to take up the position. There is no indication of any application from her or whether the Goulburn matron was ever interviewed.</p>
<p>Gertrude Lawler's seven years as matron of Canberra Hospital after she returned in 1921 became a saga dotted with complaints by and about her. She particularly objected to receiving directions from the Administrator of Canberra, J T H Goodwin, not the head of the Department of Home Affairs. She claimed he persecuted her over paltry matters to make her position unbearable and she made frequent complaints about many matters including a fight for compensation for a broken arm when she fell off her horse and the refusal to provide chaff for her horse - Goodwin said there was no need to ride a horse as the Department provided car travel. She appealed to members of parliament including Austin Chapman, Member for Eden Monaro. She was revered, however, by many of her patients who collected a sizeable testimonial for her when she left the hospital.</p>
<p>Details of her life after she left Canberra in 1928 are unclear apart from a reference to a belief that she died in Ireland.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0408b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Australian Army Nursing Service (AANS) (1902 - 1948)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1666043">
<relationEntry>
Lawler, Gertrude Frances (18790301-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Lawler, Gertrude Frances', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Lawler, Gertrude Frances</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5399b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005706.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: History of Medicine in Canberra and Queanbeyan and their hospitals</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Proust, A. J.</name>
<title render="italic">History of Medicine in Canberra and Queanbeyan and their hospitals</title>
<imprint>
<place>Gundaroo, N.S.W.</place>
<publisher>Brolga Press</publisher>
<date>1994</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005705.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Canberra 1913-1953</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Gibbney, Jim</name>
<title render="italic">Canberra 1913-1953</title>
<imprint>
<place>Canberra</place>
<publisher>Australian Government Publishing Service</publisher>
<date>1988</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005704.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: With Horse and Morse in Mesopotamia: The story of the Anzacs in Asia -The Australian Nurses in India</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Burke, Keast (ed)</name>
<title render="italic">With Horse and Morse in Mesopotamia: The story of the Anzacs in Asia -The Australian Nurses in India</title>
<imprint>
<place>Sydney</place>
<publisher>A. &amp; NZ Wireless Signal Squadron History Committee</publisher>
<date>1927</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005702.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Canberra Women in World War I: Community at Home, Nurses Abroad</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Clarke, Patricia and Francis, Niki</name>
<title render="italic">Canberra Women in World War I: Community at Home, Nurses Abroad</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2015</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/cww1"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005253.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Official History of the Australian Army Medical Services 1914-18. Vol. III: Problems and Services</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Butler, A.G.</name>
<title render="quoted">Official History of the Australian Army Medical Services 1914-18. Vol. III: Problems and Services</title>
<imprint>
<place>Canberra</place>
<publisher>Australian War Memorial</publisher>
<date>1943</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005177.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Royal Canberra Hospital: An anecdotal history of nursing 1914 to 199</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Newman, Janet and Warren, Jennie</name>
<title render="italic">Royal Canberra Hospital: An anecdotal history of nursing 1914 to 199</title>
<imprint>
<place>Mawson, ACT</place>
<date>1993</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002807.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">LAWLER Gertrude Frances : Service Number - Sister : Place of Birth - Grantham England : Place of Enlistment - N/A : Next of Kin - (Step Brother) UNDERWOOD J A</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Archives of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>LAWLER Gertrude Frances : Service Number - Sister : Place of Birth - Grantham England : Place of Enlistment - N/A : Next of Kin - (Step Brother) UNDERWOOD J A</unittitle>
<unitid>NAA: B2455, LAWLER GERTRUDE FRANCES: 7376962</unitid>
<unitdate>1914</unitdate>
<abstract>Service Record; Paper Files and Documents</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 File</extent>
<physfacet>Paper Files and Digital Copy</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/objects/D00915.htm">
<relationEntry localType="digitalObject">Gertrude Lawler</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Chemist and Druggist of Australasia, 6 April 1921 (State Library Victoria)</repository>
<unittitle>Gertrude Lawler</unittitle>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Include in Gallery</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>