<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE5426</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2015-10-06">2015-10-06</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Catherine Ordway (with Nikki Henningham)</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5426b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Ordway</part>
<part localType="givenname">Catherine</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Lawyer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Solicitor</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Tribunal member</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Board member</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Sportswoman</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Sports administrator</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Catherine Ordway is a highly respected sports lawyer, sports administrator, lecturer and consultant. In recognition of her strong reputation for regulatory review in the international sport integrity field, Catherine has recently been awarded an academic appointment at La Trobe University IN Melbourne, Victoria as Professor of Practice (Sports Management).

Ordway's expertise in assisting organisations to strengthen integrity in sport programs has led to her consultancy services being highly sought after by National Anti-Doping Organisations and countries bidding to host Summer or Winter Olympic Games. She is regularly requested to present at conferences and seminars, and to comment in the media on sports law, gender equity and integrity issues.</abstract>
<p>Catherine Ordway has a Bachelor of Arts (Jurisprudence) and Law from the University of Adelaide; a Graduate Diploma of Legal Practice from the University of South Australia; and a Graduate Diploma in Investigations Management from Charles Sturt University. She has been admitted as a solicitor in the High Court, South Australia, the Australian Capital Territory and New South Wales. Catherine lectures at the Masters level in sports law and sports management subjects: at La Trobe University (risk management), the University of New South Wales (anti-doping), the University of Melbourne (sports integrity and investigations) and the University of Canberra (performance integrity). She has also taught undergraduate sports management units as Senior Lecturer at the University of Canberra.</p>
<p>Catherine Ordway is currently completing her PhD in governance, leadership and sports integrity. The Australian Sports Commission has mandated a 40% gender inclusion policy and intends that this should lead to better integrity outcomes. Her research involves gathering data and consulting stakeholders to determine whether this new regulatory initiative is likely to have the desired effect.</p>
<p>A former national level handballer, Catherine Ordway has competed for the Australian Capital Territory (ACT) in rugby union, and at intervarsity level in fencing. Her professional interest in integrity in sport began when, as a solicitor working for Browne &amp; Co from 1997, her primary client was the Australian Olympic Committee. She appeared in over thirty anti-doping hearings, before the Court of Arbitration for Sport or National Sports Dispute Centre, in the lead up to the Sydney Olympic Games. At that time, Catherine had conducted one third of all international anti-doping cases. After living and working in Europe and the Middle East for five years developing national and international anti-doping programs, She returned to Canberra to work at the Senior Executive level at the Australian Sports Anti-Doping Authority (ASADA).</p>
<p>Ordway has represented and chaired tribunals in sports as diverse as: archery, athletics, baseball, combat sports, cricket, cycling, football, softball and swimming in a variety of selection, anti-doping and code of conduct disputes. Catherine has also served as a board member of Australian Canoeing and Capital Football. Catherine is on the International Sports Law Journal (ISLJ) Editorial and Advisory Board and is an Expert Contributor to the Australian Sports Commission Clearinghouse. Catherine is also an Ethics and Integrity Panel member for Triathlon Australia.</p>
<p>AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS</p>
<list><br />
<item>Brazilian Olympic Award, as a consultant contributing to the IOC awarding hosting rights to Rio for the 2016 Olympic and Paralympic Games</item>
<item> World Anti-Doping Agency (WADA), legal paper prize</item>
<item>Australian and New Zealand Sports Law Association (ANZSLA), legal paper prize</item>
<item>Represented WADA at the 2002 Manchester Commonwealth Games in the WADA Outreach team</item>
<item>Represented WADA at the 2007 Rio Pan-American Games as a WADA Independent Observer</item></list>
<p>CURRENT (2025)TRIBUNAL AND BOARD MEMBERSHIPS</p>
<list><br />
<item>International Sports Law Journal (ISLJ) Editorial and Advisory Board</item>
<item> International Association of Athletics Federations (IAAF), Medical &amp; Anti-Doping representative for Australia</item>
<item> International Cricket Council (ICC) Anti-Doping Panel</item>
<item>International Baseball Federation (IBAF) Anti-Doping Tribunal</item>
<item>SportAccord Members Doping Hearing Panel</item>
<item> West Indies Cricket Board's Independent Review Board </item>
<item>Australian Sports Commission, Clearinghouse, Expert Contributor</item>
<item>Triathlon Australia, Ethics and Integrity Panel member</item><br />
</list>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1625038">
<relationEntry>
Ordway, Catherine
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Ordway, Catherine', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Ordway, Catherine</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5426b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>