<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>AWE5657</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-11">2016-05-11</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Pauline Truong</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-11">2016-05-11</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5657b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Truong</part>
<part localType="givenname">Pauline</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Vietnam</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Lawyer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Entrepreneur</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The daughter of Vietnamese asylum seekers, Pauline Truong travelled with her parents to Australia as a young girl. She studied law at the University of Melbourne and went on to be the first person of Vietnamese background to be awarded the prestigious Justice Lionel Murphy
 International Postgraduate Award for attendance at UCLA Law School to complete postgraduate studies. Her thesis (with empirical research) on international and comparative law at UCLA Law School received top score from a world-renowned and distinguished Law Professor from Columbia Law School and UCLA Law School.

Described as a socio-legal entrepreneur, Pauline is working on some interesting innovations for global commercialization and impact.</abstract>
<p>Honored in the Worldwide Who's Who VIP, Who's Who in the World, Who's Who in American Law and the Queen's Trust, Pauline Truong is originally a Vietnamese Boat Person with over twelve years global experience in international law, business, education, public-speaking and a track record of awards.</p>
<p>She is one of, if not the first, Australian-Vietnamese woman to receive Honorable Order (U.S.A.) for her global innovation, leadership and contribution. The prestigious honor has been including President Bill Clinton, President Ronald Reagan, President George Bush, President Johnson, Prime Minister Winston Churchill, John Glenn, George Clooney, Elvis Presley, Johnny Depp, Betty White, Muhammad Ali, Whoopi Goldberg &amp; Billy Ray Cyrus.</p>
<p>Pauline is featured on Forbes (USA &amp; Global), MOGUL (USA), Examiner (USA), The Boston Globe (USA), Postgraduate (EU), Social Media Week (USA), Nagoya News (Japan) and other media globally. She will be the first person of Australian and Vietnamese origin to be inducted into the Millennium Global Woman of Honor.</p>
<p>As a Vietnamese refugee fleeing Vietnam after the war with her extended family, Pauline is very grateful for all the opportunities that the global leaders and community have offered her. Her family first migrated from China to Vietnam, and then a generation later risked their lives to reach Malaysia from Vietnam on their family boat after the war. They were blessed to receive refugee status in Australia and expanded internationally thereafter. At each transition, it was necessary to 're-build' part of their lives and businesses. Whilst it was challenging initially, this later became an asset for the globalization of her work, businesses and lifestyle.</p>
<p>As a minority woman, Pauline studied and worked very hard, winning scholarships and awards frequently (since childhood) to attend selective schools and be with the top people around the globe. Pauline attended MacRobertson Girls' High School, winning the General Excellence, Oreads and Melbourne Community Chest Awards. Upon graduation, she studied Science and Law at the University of Melbourne, on the E. Richards Scholarship, where she was the Convener of the Cultural Collective and Polyglot Magazine.</p>
<p>At Law School, most of her friends' parents were judges, partners in law firms, owners of well established businesses and/or other distinguished professions. As a migrant student, she realized that her career could be interesting by being 'different.' Whilst completing her studies, she undertook community and advocacy work for various state and national Ethnic Community organisations, and government organisations to promote access and equity to the law. Pauline also initiated and developed new community educational programs with the Equal Opportunity Commission. She also guest lectured at various government organisations and at Melbourne Law School whilst taking on many leadership roles and other public speaking engagements.</p>
<p>After graduation from Melbourne Law School and a period of legal practice, Pauline was the first person of Vietnamese background to be awarded the prestigious Justice Lionel Murphy International Postgraduate Award for attendance at UCLA Law School to complete postgraduate studies. Her thesis (with empirical research) on international and comparative law at UCLA Law School received top score from a world-renowned and distinguished Law Professor from Columbia Law School and UCLA Law School.</p>
<p>Pauline has served as a Young Ambassador where she worked with the United Nations, State Law Office &amp; Parliamentarians on U.N. Conventions, human rights, gender and diversity issues. She has been an Editor and Board Member of the prestigious Journal of International Law and Foreign Affairs (JILFA) and Asian Pacific American Law Journal (APALJ) and Vice-Chair of the Los Angeles Bar Association.</p>
<p>Described in Forbes (USA) as a 'Dynamic Entrepreneur Shaping the Global Economy,' Pauline is a passionate Founder and C.E.O. of Ascendo International Group and a share- and stake- holder in a conglomerate of global companies, specializing in innovations to help global clients in: Innovation &amp; Start-Ups, International Legal, Government, Investments, Trade &amp; Business, Strategic Internationalization, M &amp; A's, Immigration and Real Estate. Her peers and colleagues now 'witness the business acumen, strategic vision and networking expertise she brings to her clients.' (Todd Moster - Attorney &amp; Author)</p>
<p>As a socio-legal entrepreneur, Pauline is working on some interesting innovations for global commercialization and impact. She is also the Founder of ShePreneurs.com, a global platform endorsed by celebrities that empowers and celebrates global entrepreneurs from diverse backgrounds in a 'different' way.</p>
<p>MOGUL describes Pauline as having had 'a true dream career that has spanned across multiple areas' and 'an inspiration who is giving back to the community.' She is honored to be a Global Adviser to famous Public Figures, global Guest Lecturer &amp; Public Speaker, at UCLA Law School, international universities, professional conferences &amp; events and Philanthropist. She is also an Ambassador and regional representative for UCLA Law School for the U.S.A., Australia and Asia. Moster Esq states that 'even in a world brimming with talented people, Pauline brings a breathtaking energy level and generosity of spirit to the table that is truly unique.'</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Truong, Pauline', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Truong, Pauline</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE5657b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>