<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>IMP0125</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2002-09-24">2002-09-24</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Clare Land</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0125b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Arnot</part>
<part localType="givenname">Jean Fleming</part>
<part localType="honorific title">MBE, FLAA</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1903-04-23">23 April 1903</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1995-09-27">27 September 1995</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Pymble, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Librarian</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Trade unionist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Distinguished librarian, trade unionist and feminist, Jean Fleming Arnot, worked at the State Library of New South Wales from 1921 until her retirement in 1968. During her life Arnot was a member and leader of numerous women's organisations. Arnot was appointed as a Member of the Order of the British Empire (Civil) on 12 June 1965 for her community services in Sydney. She died in Sydney on 27 September 1995, at the age of 92.</abstract>
<p>Born at Pymble, New South Wales, Jean Arnot was educated at Fort Street Girls' High School. She never married. Her distinguished career in librarianship was served with the Public Library of New South Wales from 1921 until her retirement in 1968. She was extension librarian in charge of services to country areas, 1944-1948; head cataloguer, 1950-1968; and acting Mitchell librarian, 1956-1958. In 1948-1949 Jean received grants from the British Council and the Carnegie Corporation of New York to study library services in Great Britain and North America. She was a member of the Australian delegation to the First International Conference on Cataloguing Principles, held in Paris in 1961.</p>
<p>A founding member of the Library Association of Australia (LAA) in 1949, she was convenor of its Cataloguing Code Revision Committee, 1962-1968, and elected Fellow in 1963. With the LAA's precursor, the Australian Institute of Librarians, she had served as a councillor, general secretary,1941-1943, and president of the New South Wales branch, 1941-1942. After she retired, Miss Arnot became honorary librarian of the Royal Australian Historical Society, 1975-1980. Her expertise remained much in demand; she advised on the cataloguing of private libraries and assisted the booksellers, Berkelouw. </p>
<p>From 1937 Jean became an active campaigner for equal pay for women. In 1944 she was the recipient of the Gold Medal of the Public Service Association of New South Wales. An accomplished and popular public speaker, Miss Arnot addressed a range of issues ranging from the historical to the contemporary. She had honed her debating skills through her involvement with the women's service organisation, the Kooroora Club, in the 1930s. The Club's affiliation with the National Council of Women of New South Wales led to Jean's long-time association with the latter, becoming president from 1960-1966, and elected honorary vice-president in 1972. </p>
<p>In 1959 she was the only female representative at the Conference on Unemployment, convened by New South Wales Premier, R. J. Heffron. She was also prominent in the activities of several other organisations. Arnot was president of the Business and Professional Women's Club, 1953-1954 and 1959-1960; president of the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women, Division of New South Wales; founding member in 1961 and executive council member of the Australian Freedom from Hunger Campaign; vice-president of the League of Women Voters, 1974-1980; longtime member of and fund-raiser for the Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association; and multiple office bearer of the Women's Club (Sydney, New South Wales). </p>
<p>Jean Fleming Arnot was appointed MBE in 1965 for services to the community.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0994b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Women's Club (1901 - ?)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1017b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
BPW Australia (1947 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE0555b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
National Council of Women of New South Wales (1896 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1059b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
BPW Sydney Club (1939 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE4933b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Metcalfe, Thelma Constance (1898 - 1984)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-622017">
<relationEntry>
Arnot, Jean Fleming (19030423-19950927)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Arnot, Jean Fleming', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Arnot, Jean Fleming</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/IMP0125b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP002590.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Faith, Hope and Charity Australian Women and Imperial Honours: 1901-1989</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">Faith, Hope and Charity Australian Women and Imperial Honours: 1901-1989</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2003</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/honours/honours.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP000147.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Edited Book: Who's Who of Australian Women</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Lofthouse, Andrea</name>
<title render="italic">Who's Who of Australian Women</title>
<imprint>
<place>North Ryde (NSW)</place>
<publisher>Methuen Australia</publisher>
<date>1982</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001871.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Arnot Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Arnot Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>Ml MSS 3147 ADD-ON 1904</unitid>
<unitdate>1907 - 1988</unitdate>
<abstract>Papers mainly relate to Arnot's bibliographic work. Also inlcuding are files on various functions, the 'Freedom from Hunger Campaign', the National Women Archives (National Library), the Anit Liquor Campaing 6pm closing (1969), and the International Bible contest, 1963-64.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001870.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Arnot Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Arnot Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>ML MSS 3147</unitid>
<unitdate>1931 - 1976</unitdate>
<abstract>Misc. papers mainly concerning the status of women and the campaign for equal pay, including newcuttings, correspondence, reports, minutes of meetings and conferences. Also, various invitation, programs, menus for official diners, lectures, openings etc., 1949-1976.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>4 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH001791.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Jean Arnot, librarian and activist for equal pay for women [sound recording] / Interviewer: Amy McGrath</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Oral History Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Jean Arnot, librarian and activist for equal pay for women [sound recording] / Interviewer: Amy McGrath</unittitle>
<unitid>ORAL TRC 659</unitid>
<abstract>Recorded in Sydney, N.S.W. on 8 March 1979. Transcript available (typescript, 50 leaves) 

Summary:  Arnot speaks of her family background; Fort Street School; joining Public (later State) Library of New South Wales; transfer from Bent Street building; design of present Library building; library exams; fight for equal pay; Council of Action for Equal Pay; membership of Public Service Association; family influences; looking after aged parents; Kooroora Club; Business and Professional Women's Club; United Nations Committee; Sydney Club, Trades and Professions Committee; National Council of Women; Royal Australian Historical Society; Freedom From Hunger, New South Wales Executive; Australian Institute of Librarians; her MBE; knowledge gained through library work; Miles Franklin papers; Havelock Ellis diaries; associated institutions of the SLNSW; book theft; slashing of section on Archbishop Laud from the Dictionary of National Biography; study tours; institutional libraries; attending international cataloguing conference, Paris; library automation; Sir William Dixson coin collection; theft from H.L. White stamp collection; Berkelouw antiquarian booksellers; Riverina CAE Library; Northern Rivers CAE Library; cataloguing private collections; donations of family papers; overseas acquisition of material; Sir William Dixson; David Scott Mitchell; pirated ed. of The Pickwick Papers; Aboriginal, PNG collecting; cataloguer training; preservation; relocation of SLNSW material during WW2; London Library bomb damage; changes in type of staff; contemporary collectors; retirement activities.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 audio cassettes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000451.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Fleming Arnot - pictorial material and medals, 192--1995</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Fleming Arnot - pictorial material and medals, 192--1995</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 3147 ADD-ON 2070/16-17 and R 871</unitid>
<unitdate>1920s - 1995</unitdate>
<abstract>1927-1995; Photographs of her social and professional activities in Australia and overseas, including her travels around N.S.W., 1927-1930, and functions with, among others, Joan Sutherland; oil painting, 35.8 x 25.5 cm, by Diana Gai Mary Fitzgerald, 1992, being an allegorical depiction of Jean Arnot's career, with related notes and letters to Jean Arnot, 1991-1995; and documentation concerning King's Coronation medal, 1937 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/16) 1993-1994; Photographs concerning Jean Arnot's 90th birthday celebrations at Parliament House, Sydney, 1993, including album of photoprints (col.) with enclosed pen and ink and watercolour card presented to her from Dr Maurine Goldston-Morris, President of the Women's Club; and the Jean Arnot Annual Luncheon, Parliament House, 8 Apr. 1994 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/17) 1937, 1965; King's Coronation and MBE medals (Locn No.: R 871)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Photocopies, Ephemera</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000450.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Arnot Memorial Service - papers, 1995, being attendance book and transcript of the service held in the Dixson Room, State Library of New South Wales, 5 October 1995</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Arnot Memorial Service - papers, 1995, being attendance book and transcript of the service held in the Dixson Room, State Library of New South Wales, 5 October 1995</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 6130</unitid>
<unitdate>5 October 1995</unitdate>
<abstract>Papers,  attendance book and transcript of the service. Note: two sound recordings of the memorial service are located at MLOH 203/1-2. Should you wish to consult these, please contact the Curator of Oral History.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Notes, Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000448.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Arnot - interviews, 1974-1994</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Arnot - interviews, 1974-1994</unittitle>
<unitid>MLOH 394</unitid>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 6 cassettes, 1 reel - 7hrs</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000441.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Fleming Arnot - personal and professional papers, 1890-1995</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Fleming Arnot - personal and professional papers, 1890-1995</unittitle>
<unitid>MLMSS 3147 ADD-ON 2070/1-15</unitid>
<unitdate>1890 - 1995</unitdate>
<abstract>1948-1949; Diaries (3): 8 Apr.-1 Aug. 1948, 2 Aug.-26 Nov. 1948, and 27 Nov. 1948-15 Feb. 1949, concerning study trip of American and British libraries (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
5 Sep.-15 Dec. 1961; Diary mainly concerning trip to IFLA International Conference on Cataloguing Principles, Paris, 9-18 Oct. 1961 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
1963-1994; Pocket appointments' diaries, being one for each year, except two for 1989, and excluding 1983 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/1)
1983-1988; A4 and quarto appointments' diaries (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/2)

ca. 1913, 1933-1989; Correspondence, with enclosures including Future Projection for Women at Work, being her paper at the Victorian Employers' Federation Women at Work Conference, Melbourne, 21 July 1969, and copy of Public Aministration, vol. 5 no. 8, Dec. 1945, featuring her article, ' Employment of Women in the Civil Service'. Correspondents include Australian Congress for International Co-operation and Disarmament, Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Division of New South Wales, Australian Freedom from Hunger Campaign. New South Wales Committee, Ruby W. Board, Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, R. F. Doust, Mary Fairfax, Sir Vincent Fairfax, Eileen Furley, Irene Greenwood, Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper, Noel L. Lamidey, Andrea Lofthouse, Norman Mackenzie, National Council of Women of New South Wales, Ted Noffs, Fanny Reading, Bessie Mabel Rischbieth, Jessie Street, Nancy Bird Walton and Margaret Woodhouse (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1934-1990; 'Letters of Library Interest and Documents', being correspondence, with enclosures including her paper, Cataloguing and Classification of Special and Private Collections, delivered at the Library Association of Australia Conference, Melbourne, 27 Aug. 1975. Correspondents include Henry and Leo Berkelouw, Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, Carnegie Corporation of New York, Jim Cleary, Gerald Fischer, Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper, Eleanor M. Hinder, W. H. Ifould, Phyllis Mander-Jones, John Andrew Osborn, Barrett Reid, G. D. Richardson and the State Library of New South Wales (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1948-1949; Letters received from her mother, Jane Arnot, Alison McPherson and a nephew. See also letters from Jean Arnot to family and friends, 1948-1949, 1961, at ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1959-1992; Postcards received and drafts not sent (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, AAD ON 2070/3)
1961-1975; 'Vice Regal &amp; Official Christmas Cards' (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1964-1965; Correspondence concerning her nomination for MBE and congratulatory letters received (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)
1965-1991; References and testimonials for others (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/3)

1916-1969; Papers concerning her secondary education and employment with the Public Library of New South Wales (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1933-1994; Papers mainly concerning friends, colleagues and interests, including letters received, newscuttings and obituaries. Correspondents and/or subjects include James Allison, Zoe Emma Bertles, Freda Milicent Bryant, Flo Cluff, Alison Crook, Sir Vincent Fairfax, Film Australia, L. F. Fitzhardinge, Muriel A. Heagney, Theodora Hobbs, Millie Hoy, Marie V. Hurley, W. H. Ifould, Jessie Street Women's Library, Beatrice Anne Stewart Instone, Bee Miles, Museum of Australian Childhood, Molly Newman, Wilma Radford, Barrett Reid, Edith Alice Sims, Jocelynne A. Scutt, H. L. White and Margaret Woodhouse (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1948-1949; Papers concerning overseas study trip. Includes correspondence with the British Council and the Carnegie Corporation of New York; professional itinerary and copies of her report, Visit to Libraries in Britain and America 1948-9; theatre programs; and menus from the ship, RMS Queen Elizabeth (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1959-1961; Papers mainly concerning the International Federation of Library Associations' International Conference on Cataloguing Principles, Paris, 9-18 Oct. 1961 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1961-1962; Papers concerning 'Committee on Cataloguing Paris Conference - LAA File' (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1961-1967; Papers concerning Cataloguing Code Revision, including Australian working papers on 1961 IFLA Conference agenda items (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1962, 1972-1995; Papers concerning the Nita B. Kibble Literary Award and the Nita May Dobbie Award (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/4)
1962-1965, 1981-1993; Papers concerning her entries submitted to the Australian Dictionary of Biography, being the Reverend John McGarvie (1795-1853), W. H. Ifould (1877-1969), Nita Bernice Kibble (1879-1962) and Margaret MacPherson (1875-1956) (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968; Papers concerning her retirement from the Public Library of New South Wales on 19 Apr. 1968, including testimonial under seal issued by the Library Trustees; letter received from G. D. Richardson, Principal Librarian, 26 Apr. 1968; farewell cards, invitations and tributes from outside the Library; letter received from Mollie Thomson, co-host of the afternoon tea party held in Jean Arnot's honour; and papers concerning universal party organised by Wilma Radford at the University of NSW, 27 Apr. 1968, with letters of appreciation received (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968-1971; Papers concerning her indexing the reprint volumes of The Sydney Gazette 1810-1811 for the Library of NSW, including correspondence with Frank Dunn, Dixson Librarian (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1968-1992; Papers mainly concerning her oral history interview by Anne Robertson for the State Library of New South Wales' sesquicentenary and the Library's acquisition of her papers. Includes her notebook compiled for the interview with details of her career and campaign for equal pay. (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1969-1991; Papers concerning her cataloguing of the Library of Camden Park, Menangle, N.S.W., including correspondence with the owners, Quentin and Antonia Macarthur Stanham, 1969-1971 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1980-1992; Papers mainly concerning the State Library of New South Wales and its Library Society and the Australian Library and Information Association, including correspondence, newscuttings and invitations (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1987; Papers concerning the Library Association of Australia's 50th anniversary celebrations, Canberra, 2-4 Sep. 1987, including her talk on her first visit to Canberra for the launching of the Australian Institute of Librarians, 1937 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/5)
1993-1995; Papers concerning luncheons in honour of her 90th birthday, celebrated chiefly at Parliament House, Sydney, 19 Apr. 1993. Includes presentation album with letters received from, among others, Alison Crook, State Librarian; Jean M. Elliston, President, National Council of Women of N.S.W. Inc.; Premier John Fahey; Warren Horton, Director-General, National Library of Australia; Prime Minister Paul Keating; Kaye Loder, Convenor, National Women's Consultative Committee; Di Manning, President, Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women; and G. D. Richardson; with a copy of Congratulations Miss Arnot (State Library of NSW Press, 1993), being augmented reprint of her 1946 ABC broadcast, Should Both Sexes Receive Equal Pay for Equal Work ? (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/6)
1994; Papers concerning Jocelynne A. Scutt's book, Taking a Stand - Women in Politics and Society (Artemus Publishing Pty Ltd, 1994), including letters received from Jocelynne A. Scutt, 15 May 1994, concerning her essay on Jean Arnot in the book (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/6)

1950-1951, 1964-1965, 1979; Certificates concerning her appointment to MBE, 1965; her election to Fellow of the Library Association of Australia, 1964; her Honorary Membership of the Royal Australian Historical Society, 1979; and copy of her report, Library Facilities in New South Wales Government Institutions, 1950, with note, 1951 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/7X)

1976-1994; File concerning British Empire Association, including circular leters received and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1948-1989; Files (2) concerning the Business and Professional Women's Club of Sydney, including correspondence, membership lists, constitution and by-laws, material concerning the 40th anniversary of the Club, 1979; and the Club's study tour of Papua-New Guinea, 15-29 July 1968 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1985-1995; File concerning the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women Inc. Division of New South Wales, including correspondence, news bulletins, and constitution and by-laws (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/8)
1982-1995; File concerning the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women Inc., including correspondence and copies of Federation News (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1933-1937; File of Kooroora Literary and Debating Society magazine, being five volumes: 1932-33, 1933-34, 1934-35, 1935-36, 1936-37 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1980-1994; File concerning the National Council of Women Inc., including correspondence, circular letters received, material concerning Margaret Windeyer and report of the Womanhood Suffrage League of New South Wales, 1892 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/9)
1990-1995; File concerning National Council of Women of New South Wales Inc., being printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1978-1995; File concerning Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association, including circular letters received, reports and proceedings of the Association's 9th (Canberra, 1961), 13th (Seoul, 1975) and 15th (Saratoga Springs and New York, 1981) international conferences (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1955-1985; File concerning the Royal Australian Historical Society, including letters received from John Bennett, 1985, and D. I. McDonald, 1983; talks; copy of obituary of Harold Casterton (Harry) Harper by Hazel King; and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1967-1995; File concerning the Royal Australian Historical Society and its Library and Library Committee, including correspondence, newscuttings and printed material (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/10)
1960-1965; File concerning the Women's club, including correspondence, circular letters recived and annual reports (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/11)

ca. 1937-1991; Literary papers, being mainly notes and drafts of talks and speeches, with related correspondence and newscuttings. Topics and themes: Travel, ca. 1949-1972, date unknown; National Council of Women, 1963-1966, date unknown; Public Service, ca. 1942-1945; Internationalism, 1966-1967; Old Sydney, 1979-1991; Bibliotherapy - Libraries, ca. 1937-1971, including New Anglo-American Code for Australian Libraries, 1967; Dedications in Books, 1946, 1988, date unknown; Local History, 1970-1978 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/12)
1937-1990; Literary papers continued. Topics and themes: Status of Women in the Christian Church, 1968-1980; Women in Australia - Norman Mackenzie - Status of Women etc., 1945-1975, 1990; Australia Day &amp; Victoria League Coronation day, 1957-1984; 'Articles, etc &amp; Speeches ... Not Library', 1937-1975, 1989, including 'Equal Pay for Equal Work', 1937, Conference on Unemployment, 1961, Ruby Board, with prisoners' Christmas cards, 1949, and pamphlet on the opening of Berrima Training Centre, 1949; Reminiscences of a Cataloguer, 1981; The Australian Subscription Library and the Royal Australian Historical Society Library, 197--1982, date unknown; Early Australian Newspapers, Sydney Gazette, Hobart Town Gazette, 1989, date unknown; 'Speeches Miscellaneous' concerning, among other topics, Christmas, retirement, missionary work, the Big Sister Movement, Sydney Harbour, Captain Cook Bi-Centenary, BPW Club of Sydney study tour of Papua-New Guinea, 1968, and Soroptismy (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/13)

1926-1989, date unknown; Newscuttings concerning librarians and libraries, including obituary of Edith Alice Sims (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1934-1994; Newscuttings mainly concerning Jean Arnot, being four folders: no. 1, 1934-1953, with letter received from Lorelei booker; no. 2, 1953-1961; no. 3, 1961-1967; no. 4, 1968-1994 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1952-1995; Newscuttings on a range of topics, with letters received from Irina Dunn, 1990; Irene Greenwood, 1978, 1990; W. Boyd Rayward, 1992; and the Australian Stockman's Hall of Fame and Outback Heritage Centre, Longreach, Qld, 1990-1991 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1968-1994; Newscuttings mainly concerning librarians and libraries, with letters received from, among others, Alison Crook and Wilma radford; list of Kooroora Club members, 1968-1969; invitations; and copy of speech, 'Australia's Cultural Heritage', by Sir David Smith to the A.C.T. Branch of the Royal Commonwealth Society, 5 June 1992 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)
1988-1990; Newscuttings concerning the property, Belltrees, at Scone, N.S.W., owned by the Michael and Judy White (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/14)

192--197-; Miscellaneous papers, including letters received from Jean Arnot to family and friends, 9 Apr. 1948-7 Feb. 1949, and to her sisters, Gillian and Mary Arnot, and Alison McPherson, 6 Sep.-7 Dec. 1961; photocopied specimens of handwriting of Library staff who have contributed to entries in the card catalogues, 192--193-; passports (2), 1948 and 1961-1966, with enclosed identity card, 1942,; travel documents for Paris trip, 1961, and New Zealand trip, 1973; and unused postcards, 194--197- (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15)

1938-1990; Printed material, including order of proceedings of memorial ceremony for Emeritus Professor John Ward, AO, Patricia Ward, AM, Jennifer Ward and Moira Jennings at the Great Hall, University of Sydney, 21 June 1990, and of evening of tribute to Patricia Bruce Ward, AM, BA, DipED, FLAA, held at the State Library of NSW, 28 June 1990; and travel maps, 1938-198-, date unknown, including New South Wales Tourist Bureau regional maps, 1938 (Locn No.: ML MSS 3147, ADD ON 2070/15)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Correspondence, diaries, Paper files and documents, Speeches, Printed material, Press cuttings</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000436.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by Rosemary Block about her role in the development of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1994</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by Rosemary Block about her role in the development of the National Council of Women of Australia, 1994</unittitle>
<unitid>Z MLOH 162</unitid>
<unitdate>1994</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 1 cassette - 1hr</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000435.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by Rosemary Block about her life after she retired from the State Library. She also speaks in some detail of her colleagues Miss Nita Kibble and Miss Nita Dobbie, 1994.</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by Rosemary Block about her life after she retired from the State Library. She also speaks in some detail of her colleagues Miss Nita Kibble and Miss Nita Dobbie, 1994.</unittitle>
<unitid>Z MLOH 214</unitid>
<unitdate>1994</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 3 cassettes - 2hrs 30mins.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000434.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by John Macallister about her career in the State Library of New South Wales, 1991</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>State Library of New South Wales - Jean Arnot interviewed by John Macallister about her career in the State Library of New South Wales, 1991</unittitle>
<unitid>Z MLOH 105</unitid>
<unitdate>1991</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 5 cassettes - 4hrs</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000449.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Jean Arnot Luncheon - Book of Honour, 1996-</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Jean Arnot Luncheon - Book of Honour, 1996-</unittitle>
<unitdate>1996 - </unitdate>
<abstract>At the third annual Jean Arnot Luncheon in April 1996 a Book of Honour was introduced to acknowledge and record the contribution of each 90-year-old member of the organising bodies, the National Council of Women (NSW) Inc. and the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Associations Inc.Biographical entries of women honoured at the luncheons are followed by their authors in brackets. Photographs of most of the entrants are included.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.15 m</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000433.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Ros Bowden - interviews with people who knew Ida Leeson, former Mitchell Librarian, 1985</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Ros Bowden - interviews with people who knew Ida Leeson, former Mitchell Librarian, 1985</unittitle>
<unitid>Z MLOH 23</unitid>
<unitdate>1985</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 5 cassettes - 4hrs 30mins. Interviews with:
Arnot, Jean Fleming, 1903-1995
Conlon, T.J. (Telford James), 1941-
Conlon, Wilma
Dix, A. T. (Alexander Thomas), 1927-
Gollan, Daphne
Kerr, John, Sir, 1914-1991
Phelan, Nancy, 1913-</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH000432.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Ros Bowden - interviews conducted for radio programmes and documentaries, ca.1975 - 1989</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Mitchell and Dixson Libraries Manuscripts Collection, State Library of New South Wales</repository>
<unittitle>Ros Bowden - interviews conducted for radio programmes and documentaries, ca.1975 - 1989</unittitle>
<unitid>Z MLOH 304</unitid>
<unitdate>c. 1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>Collection comprises - 78 reels and 90 cassettes - 100hrs.
Subjects include
Aborigines, Australian -- Children -- Northern Territory.
Aborigines, Australian -- Missions -- South Australia.
Antarctica -- Discovery and exploration.
Hiking -- New South Wales.
Women -- Employment -- Australia.
Women -- Social conditions.
Women agricultural laborers -- Australia.
Women air pilots, Australian -- 20th century.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Social aspects -- Australia.
World War, 1939-1945 -- War work.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- Australia</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>100 hours</extent>
<physfacet>Sound recording</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>