<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00039</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-12-18">2009-12-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kathleen Bambridge</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00039b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Moon</part>
<part localType="givenname">Silver</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Birth Name"><part>Smith, Valerie</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1952-07-09">9 July 1952</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Adelaide, South Australia, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Political activist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Musician</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Composer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Environmentalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Public servant</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Lecturer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Lecturer</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Audio Engineer</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Silver Moon has been a political activist since 1968, and was active during the Anti Vietman War Moratoriums and anti aparthied demonstrations in the 1970s. She became active in the women's movement while still at high school. She has spent her life as a peace and environmental activist and as an anarchist-feminist activist.

</abstract>
<p>Silver Moon has been a political activist since 1968, when she first became active, as a high school student, in the women's movement. Her political interests  extended beyond women's liberation; she participated in the Anti Vietman War Moratoriums and anti apartheid demonstrations of the 1970s. Since those early years, she has maintained a long and active involvement in political matters at a community and organisational level. </p>
<p>Between 1980-83 she was a member of the Hindmarsh Women's Community Centre, in Adelaide, South Australia. While there she helped establish the Unemployed Women's Union. She taught women's studies at Department of Education, Technical and Further Education Colleges (DETAFE) in South Australia. Silver has also been a public servant.</p>
<p>She was at Greenham Common Women's Peace Camp (UK) from 1983-1988, and travelled on the peace bus to the Soviet Union. She was arrested many times and imprisoned three times during her time at Greenham Common. She was a member of the International Women's Day Collective and the Women's Studies Resource Centre Collective. She is currently a member of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter Collective (Liberation). She helped establish the Women's Environmental Action Group 1988-1991c and is the public officer for the Women's Support Fund.</p>
<p>As a musician she has performed with the Women's Drumming Group and the Bangshees, and she writes and performs her own music. She was an active member of Lesbian over forty (Lofty), Lesbian Line (counselling phone service for lesbians) and the Rural Lesbian Separatist Group. She worked in Women's Radio at Radio 5UV the Adelaide University Radio Station, mainly on the women's magazine program "No Frills".</p>
<p>Her environmentalist activitism is now focused on the Native Grasses Group and the Finnis Catchment Group to environmentally protect the Finnis River (SA) and its catchments and wet lands. She is a board member for the Goolwa to Wellington Local Action Planning Association, lobbying for the Murray River lower lakes environs and Trees for Life.</p>
<p>With her audio engineering work she has recorded many women poets and musical performers including Standard Deviations. Silver worked at the Elder Conservatorium of Music as a sound technician and recordist doing CD production for students and staff. She works for the State Library of South Australia as a audio engineer in audio preservation. She is a member of the Audio Engineers Society. The State Library of South Australia has recorded 20 hours of her oral history. She lives on a farm at Finniss.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00099b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Ward, Elizabeth (Biff)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00085b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Frazer, Connie (1925 - 2002)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00040b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women's Environmental Action Group (1988 - 1991)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00071b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Unemployed Women's Union (1980 - 1981)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00040b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women's Environmental Action Group (1988 - 1991)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00074b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
International Women's Day Collective (1974 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00078b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre  (1974 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00063b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Rape Crisis Centre (1976 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00064b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Kinder, Sylvia
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477503">
<relationEntry>
Moon, Silver (1952-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Moon, Silver', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Moon, Silver</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00039b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00054.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newsletter: Liberation</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Liberation</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>Liberation</publisher>
<date>1970</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter</title>
<num type="volume">314</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00802.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Silver Moon</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Silver Moon</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 800</unitid>
<unitdate>2006 - 2007</unitdate>
<abstract>Interviews with Silver Moon 2006-7. Full transcript available for first 9 hours (234 pages); Summary of the full interview available (6 pages).</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>On CD , 20 discs</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002304.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Interview with Silver Moon - Interviewer: Allison Murchie</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Interview with Silver Moon - Interviewer: Allison Murchie</unittitle>
<unitid>OH 800</unitid>
<abstract>Recorded on 7 &amp; 21 November, 19 December 2006; 8 &amp; 21 February, 3, 11, &amp; 17 May 2007; 15 &amp; 22 June 2007; 13, 19, 30 July, 24, 25 October, 15, 23 November and 4 &amp; 21 December 2007 

Other Versions Available on CD (20 discs) 
Transcription Full transcript available for first 9 hours (234 pages); Summary of the full interview available (6 pages)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>18 hours</extent>
<physfacet>Compact Flash Card</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00108.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1969 - May 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement began at the University of Adelaide in 1968, with the women who were active in young labour, the anti-vietnam war campaign questing their frustration and roles in these groups that were male dominated. Anna Yeatman, Anne Summers and Julie Ellis are credited with starting the newsletters Sisterhood, and Body Political by late 1969 they produced Liberation, the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter which replaced Sisterhood. Their first protest was against the Miss Fresher competition, which gain media exposer to their ideas of women's liberation. Public meetings where called and the broader community involvement brought about the establishment of the Women's Liberation Movement housed at Bloor House. They provided an environment where ideas for supporting women'd rights were fostered. From this the Women's Liberation Movement in Adelaide was the catalyst for the establishment of the Women's Health Centre at Hindmarsh, The Rape Crisis Centre, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Abortion Action Campaign, St Peters Women's Community Centre, Women's Health Centers at Chrisities Beach and Elizabeth, lobbied for Women's Studies to be part of Tertiary education, women's representation in parliments, Working Women's Centre to Protect women's working rights, the Women's Peace Movement. Bloor House provided a space for women to express their personal political ideas and to get feedback and support. The Women's Liberation Movement moved from Bloor House to Eden St in Adelaide and then to Mary St, Hindmarsh were it was closed in 1989.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.323000013828278 m, 1021 </extent>
<physfacet>banners, minutes, correspondence, badges, posters, flyers, daybooks</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00075.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </unittitle>
<unitdate>1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first Women's Health Centre in South Australia. The Women's Liberation Movement recognised the need for a separate women's health centre from the number of health related calls and personal enquires. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. Because funding was through the state the feminist way of running the centre and the bureaucracy and its requirements often clashed. This was further complicated by the feminist groups involved in the centre. The Centre was run by a feminist collective. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre. The Health Centre became a teaching centre for women's health. The Centre produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. The conflict with the Health Department eventially lead to the withdrawal of funding. With the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier the continuing need for a Women's Health Centre was argued and the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. Hindmarsh Women's Health Centre continued with the Medicare payments to support other work of the centre. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.109999999403954 m, 80 </extent>
<physfacet>minutes, daybooks, film, posters, pamphlets, </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00073.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">International Women's Day Collective</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>International Women's Day Collective</unittitle>
<unitdate>c. 1984 - </unitdate>
<abstract>International Women's Day (IWD) Collective, not to be confused with the IWD Committee formed in 1938. The IWD Collective was form by the second wave of feminism and was concerned with the IWD March the festival or picnic after the march and the IWD Dance. They organised speakers and have themes for the day, produce posters badges and tshirts (this does not happen each year). </abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.340000003576279 m, 36 </extent>
<physfacet>minutes and agendas, correspondence, badges, tshirts, scrapbook, posters, photographs, songs and arm bands. </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00072.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Unemployed Women's Union</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Unemployed Women's Union</unittitle>
<unitdate>1980 - 1981</unitdate>
<abstract>The Unemployed Women's Union was a response to the economic downturn of 1980. They wanted to debunk the myth of working married women as the cause of unemployment, defend the right for all women to work, and as a support group for unemployed women. The picketed employers, published a newsletter, spoke at rallies, wrote letters to newspapers and politicians, and applied for jobs en masse. </abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.340000003576279 m, 20 </extent>
<physfacet>Minutes, members list, newspaper clippings, daybooks, correspondence</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00065.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Sylvia Kinder</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Sylvia Kinder</unittitle>
<unitid>PRG 1500</unitid>
<unitdate>1970 - 1986</unitdate>
<abstract>Sylvia Kinder was active in the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement. As a teacher she was active with the South Australian Institute of Teachers (SAIT) questioning the sexist teaching practices within schools. She was active in changing education standards to include girls, the use of non sexist language in school and equal opportunities for girls. Sylvia was a member of the Australian Women's Education Coalition (SA Branch). She was involved in the establishment of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archives and the Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre. She was a member of International Women's Year National Advisory Committee 1974-1976. The need for a women's studies courses became apparent to Sylvia and other concerned teachers and set about setting up the a women's library as part of the Women's Liberation Movement. Books and papers where donated and the Women's Studies Resource Centre was created. She taught women's studies at the Women's Studies Resource Centre. She was A collective member of Liberation, Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter. She served on the Status of Women's Standing Committee from 1974-1976. Sylvia addressed International Women's Day rallies or marches. She helped organise conferences including the Young Women's Festival and the Women in Labour Conference both held in Adelaide. She was also active in gay liberation in South Australia. Some of the other groups she was involved in are Women Behind Bars, Salisbury Women's Group Newsletter, Salisbury Women's Health centre, National Women's Consultative Council, SAIT Professional Development Committee, International Women's Day Collective. Women's Theatre Group (South Australia). There is a collection of taped interviews with South Australian feminist including Pat Ronald, Liz Byard, Anna Yeatman, Judy Gillett, Betty Fisher, Connie Frazer, Debroah McCulloch, Jill Mathews, Sue Higgins (Sheridan) and Gail Tauscher. Sylvia Kinder wrote Herstory of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement 1969-1974.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.29999995231628 m, 86 badges, folders t shirts, minutes, printed papers,</extent>
<physfacet>Printed papers, lists, minutes, t shirts, badges, posters audio tapes</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00038.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Women's Environmental Action Group Booklet</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Women's Environmental Action Group Booklet</unittitle>
<unitdate>September 1988 - c. 1991</unitdate>
<abstract>Booklet hand made with correspondence, photographs, hand made paper and intructions on how to make it, stickers and a banner (not the one in the photographs)</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>5.00000023748726E-04 m, 2 1Booklet 1 banner</extent>
<physfacet>corrspondence, instructions, drawings, photographs, stickers</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>