<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00107</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-12-18">2009-12-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kathleen Bambridge</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00107b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Eagle</part>
<part localType="givenname">Robin Ann </part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="birth name"><part>Duke, Robin Ann</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1951-07-22">22 July 1951</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Hopetoun , Victoria, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Environmentalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Poet</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Teacher</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Robin Eagle has been active in the South Australian Women's Movement since 1976 and a lesbian feminist activist in Victoria before then. Born in Hopetoun, Victoria, she joined the Women's Liberation Movement in Victoria in 1975. A dedicated community worker, she helped establish and run many community groups. She is on the Board of Management for the Women's Studies Resource Centre in Adelaide, South Australia 1999-2013. Robin has published a book of poetry.</abstract>
<p>Robin Eagle has been a lesbian feminist activist since 1975. In Melbourne she was involved in the founding of Womens Liberation Halfway House Collective Inc ( Womens refuge) Then in 1975 she co-founded the Vesuvia Women's Book and Craft Association in Collingwood.</p>
<p>She tutored in Commerce at the University of Adelaide 1978-82. She lectured at the Light, Spencer Institutes of Technical and Further Education, South Australia, and in Alice Springs TAFE. She is a contributor to the <span style="font-style:italic">Yulara Times</span> when working as co-ordinator and counsellor at the Yulara Community Resource Centre in 1973-4. She was also a collective member of the Women's Spiritual Movement, South Australia and co-founder of Plum Farm Women's Land in 1980.</p>
<p>Other activitied she has been involved in include: co-ordinator of the Elizabeth West Community Food Co-op; co-ordinator of the Bowden-Brompton Community Centre (SA) ; board membership of the Women's Studies Resource Centre. And member of the YWCA Bush walking group.</p>
<p>Robin was on organizing collectives for feminist conferences including the Melbourne Womens Liberation conference in 1976, the seried of National Lesbian Feminist Conferences between1989-2000 and the Adelaide Women's Liberation Conference 1996.</p>
<p>Robin has published a book of poetry, <span style="font-style:italic"> Distilled Essence of Eagle</span> (1985). She has contributed to anthologies published by SA Country and City Women Writers and taught womens assertiveness, communication, creative writing at varied community centres.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00102b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement (1969 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00096b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive  (1984 - 2009)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-551695">
<relationEntry>
Eagle, Robin (19510722-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Eagle, Robin Ann ', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Eagle, Robin Ann </title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00107b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00108.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1969 - May 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement began at the University of Adelaide in 1968, with the women who were active in young labour, the anti-vietnam war campaign questing their frustration and roles in these groups that were male dominated. Anna Yeatman, Anne Summers and Julie Ellis are credited with starting the newsletters Sisterhood, and Body Political by late 1969 they produced Liberation, the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter which replaced Sisterhood. Their first protest was against the Miss Fresher competition, which gain media exposer to their ideas of women's liberation. Public meetings where called and the broader community involvement brought about the establishment of the Women's Liberation Movement housed at Bloor House. They provided an environment where ideas for supporting women'd rights were fostered. From this the Women's Liberation Movement in Adelaide was the catalyst for the establishment of the Women's Health Centre at Hindmarsh, The Rape Crisis Centre, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Abortion Action Campaign, St Peters Women's Community Centre, Women's Health Centers at Chrisities Beach and Elizabeth, lobbied for Women's Studies to be part of Tertiary education, women's representation in parliments, Working Women's Centre to Protect women's working rights, the Women's Peace Movement. Bloor House provided a space for women to express their personal political ideas and to get feedback and support. The Women's Liberation Movement moved from Bloor House to Eden St in Adelaide and then to Mary St, Hindmarsh were it was closed in 1989.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.323000013828278 m, 1021 </extent>
<physfacet>banners, minutes, correspondence, badges, posters, flyers, daybooks</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>