<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00840</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2010-03-18">2010-03-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Janet Butler</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2014-07-30">2014-07-30</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00840b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Dietrich</part>
<part localType="givenname">Laurene</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1951-12-06"> 6 Dec 1951</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Mildura, Victoria, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Community worker</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>After an early career in teaching, Laurene Dietrich moved into the area of community development, working on a number of projects which reflected her commitment to social justice and equity, particularly in regard to rural women. She was the first equal opportunity officer at the Bendigo campus of La Trobe University, and was employed to work on the organisation of the First International Women in Agriculture Conference

</abstract>
<p>In 1994 Laurene Dietrich, having worked to set up a student association at Ballarat School of Mines, was working at Department of Conservation and Natural Resources, setting up a photography competition for entries reflecting the work of women agricultural workers. She had met Anna Lottkowitz, of the Rural Women's Network, while organising International Women's Day celebrations, and at her suggestion, was employed to organise the flights and accommodation of women who came to speak at the First International Women in Agriculture Conference and for whom sponsorship had been found. She also organised their post-conference visits to Australian farms.  Prior to this, Laurene had researched and written a report on South Australian women's attitude to tertiary education for Roseworthy Agricultural College. She had also been the Project Worker employed by Ballarat Centre Against Sexual Assault for the 'Best Practice in Ararat' project, which aimed to enhance the knowledge and skills of health workers in confronting sexual assault, and worked with the disadvantaged schools program.</p>
<p>During the conference, Laurene took the informal photographs which grace many publications, and now form part of the archival record of the Conference. As a member of CVWiA, she did the same for the 1997 Bendigo Women on Farms Gathering.</p>
<p>Overseen by researcher Ruth Liepins, Laurene compiled the post conference evaluation, based on questionnaires filled out at the conference, and also mailed after three months. The evaluation, published in 1995 as <span style="font-style:italic">Agents for Change: Farming  for our Future</span>, had to be both readable to the attendees, and useful as research for the purposes of lobbying for change.</p>
<p>Since the conference, Laurene has been involved in a number of projects in the area of community development, social justice and equity, focussing on rural women.  In the late 90s she headed a Vic Health funded project in the small town of Macarthur, working with rural women on, amongst other projects, access to childcare.  In June 1998, with fellow Central Victorian Women in Agriculture member Joy Chambers, she convened a Link-up Conference at the YMCA in Melbourne, over the weekend of the Second International Conference in Washington, so that rural Victorian women could speak to their delegates in America. More recently she had been state co-ordinator of the Victorian Public Tenants Association. She is now resident in south-eastern Victoria, and is involved in revitalising the Women's Action Collective and increasing its appeal.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00832b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Central Victorian Women in Agriculture Inc. (1994? - 2006)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00488b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Event">
First International Women in Agriculture Conference (1994)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00727b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women on Farms Gatherings (1990 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-462586">
<relationEntry>
Dietrich, Laurene (19511206-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Dietrich, Laurene', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Dietrich, Laurene</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00840b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP005590.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: The Encyclopedia of Women and Leadership in Twentieth-Century Australia</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Smart, Judith and Swain, Shurlee (eds)</name>
<title render="italic">The Encyclopedia of Women and Leadership in Twentieth-Century Australia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2014</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/leaders"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00493.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Report: Agents For Change: Farming for our Future</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Dietrich, Laurene (ed)</name>
<title render="italic">Agents For Change: Farming for our Future</title>
<imprint>
<place>Eaglehawk, Victoria</place>
<publisher>Women in Agriculture 1994 International Conference Committee Inc.</publisher>
<date>1995</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Evaluation of the First International Women in Agriculture Conference, Melbourne, 1994</title>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/AWP004918.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Site Exhibition: Brilliant Ideas and Huge Visions: ABC Radio Australian Rural Women of the Year - 1994-1997</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Australian Women's Archives Project</name>
<title render="italic">Brilliant Ideas and Huge Visions: ABC Radio Australian Rural Women of the Year - 1994-1997</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Australian Women's Archives Project</publisher>
<date>2011</date>
</imprint>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/exhib/rwya/rwya-home.html"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002623.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Laurene Dietrich, 1990-1994 [manuscript]</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Laurene Dietrich, 1990-1994 [manuscript]</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc11.024</unitid>
<unitdate>1990 - 1994</unitdate>
<abstract>Comprises papers relating to Laurene Dietrich's role as a member of the organising committee for the first Women in Agriculture Conference, held in Melbourne, July 1994. The collection includes correspondence, reports, list of participants, minutes of meetings, copies of some of the papers presented at the conference, photographs, a questionnaire for particpants and news cuttings</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 boxes</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00836.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Correspondence and Report on Attitudes of South Australian Women to Tertiary Education by Laurene Dietrich</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>The University of Adelaide Archives</repository>
<unittitle>Correspondence and Report on Attitudes of South Australian Women to Tertiary Education by Laurene Dietrich</unittitle>
<unitid>118800279 Box Number 34 Series 1188</unitid>
<unitdate>1987 - 1995</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.99999995529652E-02 m, 1 File</extent>
<physfacet>Reports and annotated draft, copy of relevant talk.</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00502.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Mary Salce Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Mary Salce Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc10.145, MS Acc11.123</unitid>
<unitdate>1976 - 2007</unitdate>
<abstract>Minutes, press releases, press clippings, correspondece, reports, proposals, funding applications, video tapes, post conference proceedings and evaluations, lists of attendees, newsletters, brochures, photographs and programs relating to Mary Salce's early activism, the formation of the original Statewide Women in Agriculture organisation, the First International Women in Agricuture Conference, and subsequent international conferences,and the Foundation for Australian Agricultural Women.

NB - Papers have been recently acquired by the National Library of Australia. Contact repository for details.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.8 m</extent>
<physfacet>1.80 m. (7 boxes) + 1 fol. box + 1 fol. packet.</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00833.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Audrey Drechsler Papers</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia Manuscript Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Audrey Drechsler Papers</unittitle>
<unitid>MS Acc11.023</unitid>
<unitdate>1979 - 2009</unitdate>
<abstract>The papers reflect Audrey Drechsler's thirty years' involvement as an activist in the Women in Agriculture movement. They include rare papers relating to very early conferences, including two in 1979, and the 1994 First International Women in Agriculture Conference; registration forms for Australian Women in Agriculture Inc. skills workshops; Minutes, newletters, letters, flyers, planning documents, media clippings, mailing lists, questionnaire, report relating to Central Victorian Women in Agriculture; papers relating to attendance at seventeen annual Women on Farm Gatherings, and the Heritage Project, including programs, proceedings, registration forms, media clipping; booklet on stress management in country communities prepared by Women in Agriculture - Victorian Mallee Group.

These papers were recently accessed by the National Library of Australia. Please contact them for further details.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 box</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>