<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00216</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-06-22">2009-06-22</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Lee Butterworth</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00216b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Thoms</part>
<part localType="givenname">Patience Rosemary</part>
<part localType="honorific title">Order of the British Empire (O.B.E.) </part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="Preferred name"><part>Thoms, Pat</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1915-09-13">13 September 1915</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="2006-03-02">2 March 2006</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Death</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Brisbane, Queensland, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Journalist</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Business woman</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Patience Rosemary Thoms was elected as the eighth president of the International Federation of Business and Professional Women at the Eleventh International Congress (1968) in London, England and held that position until 1971. She was the first International President from Australia, and also the first from the Southern Hemisphere. She had previously served as Australian President from 1960-1964. She was the Women's News Editor of <span style="font-style:italic">The Courier Mail</span> for twenty years from 1956.

</abstract>
<p>As President of the International Federation of Business and Professional Women (IFBPW), Pat Thoms made it a goal to visit as many affiliates as possible to facilitate two-way communication. During her previous twenty-two years of membership, she had held many positions of leadership in both Brisbane Professional Women (BPW) Australia and the IFBPW and was well qualified for leading the organisation, founded in 1930, into its fortieth year.</p>
<p>Although she lived 13,000 miles from International Headquarters in London, Australia's geographical location meant that she had to pass over or through many countries in order to get to Headquarters. She therefore made it a point to visit as many affiliates as possible on her way to and from Executive Committee meetings. Logging over 200,000 miles during her term of office, President Thoms visited members in twenty-nine countries. The trip that was both the longest in distance and shortest in duration covered 29,000 miles in fifteen days! She wrote a history of the first 25 years of the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's clubs, 1947-1972.</p>
<p>On her retirement as the Women's News Editor of the <span style="font-style:italic">Courier Mail</span> in 1976 aged 60, she applied for admission to the Bachelor of Arts program in the School of Modern Asian Studies at Griffith University. She graduated in 1980. She worked part-time for the University as a public relations consultant from 1982 to 1986 before being elected to the University Council as a member of Convocation and an appointee of the Governor-in-Council.</p>
<p>In 1981 she became first chair of the new Brisbane College of Advanced Education Council. In 1988, she was elected deputy Chancellor of Griffith University and held the position until 1990. She was admitted to the degree of Doctor of the University in 1990. Griffith University awards the Patience Thoms Indigenous Australian (Honours/Postgraduate) Scholarship annually. The scholarships are designed to assist Indigenous students moving onto Honours and Graduate studies at the University.</p>
<p>Patience Thoms regarded herself as a feminist, "but not a radical one". In an interview with a female journalist in 1995, she recalled: "the changes over the years since 1946 when I first became associated with the business and professional women's organization are really quite extraordinary". "Today's feminists don't think it's changed enough, and it hasn't. There are many things that still need to be done."</p>
<p>Associated organisations:</p>
<list><item>Member of the Queensland Film Board of Review (1974-1985)</item>
<item>Member of Ethics Committee of the Australian Journalists' Association</item>
<item>Member of the National Drug Advisory Council</item>
<item>Member of the Council of Queensland Women</item></list>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477388">
<relationEntry>
Thoms, Patience Rosemary (19150913-20060302)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Thoms, Patience Rosemary', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Thoms, Patience Rosemary</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00216b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00213.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: The first 25 years, B.P.W. Australia: The History of the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Thoms, Patience R, comp</name>
<title render="italic">The first 25 years, B.P.W. Australia: The History of the Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs</title>
<imprint>
<place>Melbourne</place>
<publisher>Australian Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs</publisher>
<date>1972</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00214.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">The role of women over three centuries by Patience Thoms</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia</repository>
<unittitle>The role of women over three centuries by Patience Thoms</unittitle>
<unitid>Nq 610.71194 COL</unitid>
<unitdate>1976 - </unitdate>
<abstract>Typescript (Duplicate). Patricia Chomley oration ; 10th, 1976.   Delivered at the 27th annual meeting of College of Nursing, Australia, in the Brisbane Grammar School</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Book</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>