<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00063</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-12-18">2009-12-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kathleen Bambridge</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00063b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Rape Crisis Centre</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Adelaide Rape Crisis Centre</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Yarrow Place</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1976-09-06">6 September 1976</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Hindmarsh, South Australia, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>Location</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Level 2, Norwich Centre 55 King William Road, North Adelaide</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Feminist support service</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Social change</term>
</function>
<function>
<term>Educator</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>The Adelaide Rape Crisis Centre was formed as an outgrowth of the Hindmarsh Women's Community Centre, a free medical service for women. It became obvious after a short time that a separate service was needed, given the number of women reporting past rapes and the lack of available services. The founders of the Rape Crisis Centre had three main purposes: 1) to support women after the rape, 2) to change attitudes to rape and 3) to teach self defence. They organised the first 'Reclaim the Night March' in Adelaide. The group made a submission to the Mitchell Report on Rape and Other Sexual Offences.</abstract>
<p>The Centre was opened on 6 September 1976 with 28 trained women on roster for limited phone counselling. By 1980 they had 40 volunteers and 2 part time co ordinators. These workers and volunteers took on roles in counselling services, community education, administration, the Management Committee, Liason Committee and the sexual assult clinic. They trained other services who helped women and girls who had been raped or sexually assulted.</p>
<p>Initially the Rape Crisis Centre operated at Mary St, Hindmarsh. The service then moved to the Queen Elizabeth Hospital and on to North Adelaide where it became Yarrow Place. The centre has produced a newsletter since 1977 which is now online.</p>
<p>Some of the women involved include Heather Crosby, Myra Williams (Betschild), Silver Moon, Helen Oxenham, Jenny Cooke, Chris Beasley, Stephanie Key, Jill Miller, Jillian and Val Tidswell and Diana Kemp.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00039b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Moon, Silver (1952 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00078b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre  (1974 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-624384">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Rape Crisis Centre', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Rape Crisis Centre</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00063b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00062.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Rape Crisis Centre</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Rape Crisis Centre</unittitle>
<unitdate>1976 - </unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Rape Crisis Centre was formed after the Hindmarsh Women's Community Centre, a free medical service for women had operated for a short time, and the need for a separate service became apparent with the numbers of women reporting past and present rapes and the lack of services for wome and girls. The centre was modelled on the newly formed Sydney Rape Crisis Centre. They had three main purposes to support women after the rape, change attitudes to rape and to teach self defence. They organised the first Reclaim the Night March in Adelaide. The group made a submission to the Mitchell Report on Rape and Other Sexual Offences. It is now titled Yarrow Place.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>2 folders</extent>
<physfacet>Minutes, correspondence</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00108.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1969 - May 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement began at the University of Adelaide in 1968, with the women who were active in young labour, the anti-vietnam war campaign questing their frustration and roles in these groups that were male dominated. Anna Yeatman, Anne Summers and Julie Ellis are credited with starting the newsletters Sisterhood, and Body Political by late 1969 they produced Liberation, the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter which replaced Sisterhood. Their first protest was against the Miss Fresher competition, which gain media exposer to their ideas of women's liberation. Public meetings where called and the broader community involvement brought about the establishment of the Women's Liberation Movement housed at Bloor House. They provided an environment where ideas for supporting women'd rights were fostered. From this the Women's Liberation Movement in Adelaide was the catalyst for the establishment of the Women's Health Centre at Hindmarsh, The Rape Crisis Centre, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Abortion Action Campaign, St Peters Women's Community Centre, Women's Health Centers at Chrisities Beach and Elizabeth, lobbied for Women's Studies to be part of Tertiary education, women's representation in parliments, Working Women's Centre to Protect women's working rights, the Women's Peace Movement. Bloor House provided a space for women to express their personal political ideas and to get feedback and support. The Women's Liberation Movement moved from Bloor House to Eden St in Adelaide and then to Mary St, Hindmarsh were it was closed in 1989.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.323000013828278 m, 1021 </extent>
<physfacet>banners, minutes, correspondence, badges, posters, flyers, daybooks</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00075.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </unittitle>
<unitdate>1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first Women's Health Centre in South Australia. The Women's Liberation Movement recognised the need for a separate women's health centre from the number of health related calls and personal enquires. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. Because funding was through the state the feminist way of running the centre and the bureaucracy and its requirements often clashed. This was further complicated by the feminist groups involved in the centre. The Centre was run by a feminist collective. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre. The Health Centre became a teaching centre for women's health. The Centre produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. The conflict with the Health Department eventially lead to the withdrawal of funding. With the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier the continuing need for a Women's Health Centre was argued and the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. Hindmarsh Women's Health Centre continued with the Medicare payments to support other work of the centre. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.109999999403954 m, 80 </extent>
<physfacet>minutes, daybooks, film, posters, pamphlets, </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>