<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00401</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-06-22">2009-06-22</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Lee Butterworth</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00401b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Dare</part>
<part localType="givenname">Zara</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1886-01-01">1886</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1965-12-31">1965</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Policewoman</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Zara Dare was 45 years-old when she applied for a position as a Queensland police officer. She had previously worked in China for the Salvation Army and, upon returning to Australia, she was an organiser of the Woman's Christian Temperance Union. Zara and her colleague, Ellen O'Donnell, commenced at the Roma Street Police Station in 1931. Neither of the women was sworn in and therefore did not receive the same pay allowances and privileges (including superannuation) as male officers. Zara's work within the police force was restricted to looking after lost children, escorting female prisoners, and working with victims of domestic and sexual violence. Nine years after joining the police force, Zara retired to marry. It was not until 1965 that Queensland police women were officially sworn in and therefore entitled to some of the priveleges enjoyed by men.

</abstract>
<p>The National Council of Women of Queensland (NCWQ) in 1911 drew attention to the need for women and girls in Queensland to be better served in matters of crime. There were no female police officers in Australia at the time and the NCWQ called for women, experienced and educated in social work, to be given the status of police officers. The appointment of two female police in New South Wales in 1915 was not enough to encourage the Queensland Commissioner of Police William Cahill to follow suit. By 1917 Queensland was the only state without female police. Newspapers and community groups began asking why. The Queensland Country Women's Association (QCWA), the Roman Catholic Archbishop of Brisbane, James Duhig, the NCWQ and the Queensland Women's Electoral League (QWEL) all called for the appointment of women in policing.</p>
<p>It was not until Irene Longman was elected to State Parliament in 1929 that the opposition to female police began to be broken down. As past president of the NCWQ and a member of the QWEL, Irene made a submission to cabinet in 1930, outlining the necessity for women to handle sensitive cases such as children, girls and women who have been involved in sexual assault cases. Although the decision was not unanimous, Cabinet consented to the appointment of women in the police force.</p>
<p>Zara Dare, along with Ellen O'Donnell, accepted the offer of positions and the women were based at the Roma Street police station. When the time came to review their appointments and make them permanent, the Police commissioner William Ryan stated that they were well paid for the job they were doing, and although there was nothing under the <span style="font-style:italic">Police Act</span> 1898 to stop them from being sworn in, he considered that their swearing in would reduce the number of male police constables by two. Zara kept her job by agreeing not to be sworn in. She never received the pay allowances and privileges of her fellow police, nor superannuation.</p>
<p>The NCWQ continued to lobby to have Zara and Ellen made permanent, but Police Commissioner Ryan made it clear that if they were not satisfied, they were free to resign at any time. When Zara resigned from the police force to marry, the <span style="font-style:italic">Queensland Times</span> noted her departure with a small article, headlined "Policewoman Wanted". A women's police unit, attached to the Criminal Investigation Bureau (CIB), was established soon after Zara's resignation.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00393b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
O'Donnell, Ellen (1896 - 1963)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/AWE1112b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Woman's Christian Temperance Union of Queensland (1885 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-766094">
<relationEntry>
Dare, Zara (1886-1965)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Dare, Zara', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Dare, Zara</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00401b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00389.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book Section: Ellen O'Donnell and Zara Dare: Queensland's first policewomen</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Grant, Heather</name>
<title render="quoted">Ellen O'Donnell and Zara Dare: Queensland's first policewomen</title>
<imprint>
<place>Brisbane</place>
<publisher>State of Queensland</publisher>
<date>2005</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Great Queensland Women</title>
<name type="author">Office for Women, Queensland Government</name>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00397.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Journey to equality: an illustrated history of women in the Queensland Police</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Prenzler, Tim, Jones, Lisa, Ronken, Carol </name>
<title render="italic">Journey to equality: an illustrated history of women in the Queensland Police</title>
<imprint>
<place>Brisbane</place>
<publisher>Queensland Police Service</publisher>
<date>2001</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00400.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Zara Dare Staff File: AF4533</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>Queensland State Archives</repository>
<unittitle>Zara Dare Staff File: AF4533</unittitle>
<unitid>Series ID: 1108: Item ID: 567027</unitid>
<unitdate>18 December 1930 </unitdate>
<abstract>Police Service file</abstract>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>