<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00673</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-08-21">2009-08-21</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Ann-Mari Jordens</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2016-05-02">2016-05-02</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00673b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Bishop</part>
<part localType="givenname">Clare</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1945-06-26">26 June 1945</fromDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Place of Birth</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Sydney, New South Wales, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Public servant</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Clare Bishop graduated in catering and hotel management before joining the Department of Immigration in Canberra in 1970, serving in London 1971-74, Edinburgh in 1975-77 and New York 1977-80. After helping organize the Commonwealth Heads of Government meeting in Melbourne in 1981, she was sent to Cologne to process refugees from Poland, and to the Philippines to process spouse applications. From 1984-86 she was First Secretary in the Australian Embassy in Vietnam, then Consul in New York to 1990. From 1993 until her retirement in 2000, she was responsible for overhauling all the Department's forms.

</abstract>
<p>Clare Bishop was born in Sydney on 26 June 1945, daughter of neurophysiologist Sir Peter Orlebar Bishop and Hilary Louise neé Holmes, a former nurse. Educated in Sydney at Chatswood Primary School, Roseville College and Abbotsford Anglican School for Girls, she travelled in 1963 with her parents to Massachusetts. After briefly attending a secretarial school she worked first as a volunteer at the Harvard International Students Club, and then as a governess in Paris.</p>
<p>On her return to Sydney in 1964 she completed two years of an Arts degree at Sydney University before studying catering and hotel management at East Sydney Technical School. On graduating, she moved to Canberra and worked briefly in a hotel and an employment agency before joining the Professional Migration Section of the Department of Immigration in 1970. She was posted to London from 1971-74, then trained new staff in the Recruitment Section in Canberra, before being posted to Edinburgh in October 1975.</p>
<p>In 1977 she was cross-posted to New York, returning to Canberra in 1980 where she worked as Ministerial Correspondence Liaison Officer in the Legal and Parliamentary Branch. In 1981 she was seconded to the Department of Prime Minister and Cabinet to help organise the Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting in Melbourne. She was then sent to Cologne to process Special Humanitarian Entrants from Poland, to Berne, Switzerland, to process applications from chefs, and then to the Philippines to process women entering Australia on spouse visas. On returning to Canberra she worked as executive to the Australian Institute of Multicultural Affairs on its evaluation of the implementation of the Galbally Report.</p>
<p>From 1984 -86 she served as First Secretary in the Australian Embassy in Vietnam, then as Consul/ Principal Migration Officer in New York and Area Director in Chicago and Toronto to 1990. Following her return to Canberra she was Executive officer to the National Population Council and to the Conference of Commonwealth/State/Territory Ministers for Immigration, before becoming Departmental Liaison Officer in the office of the Minister for Immigration, Gerry Hand. From 1993 until her retirement in 2000, she was in charge of overhauling all the Department's forms. </p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477396">
<relationEntry>
Bishop, Clare (19450626-)
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Bishop, Clare', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Bishop, Clare</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00673b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/AWH002305.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Clare Bishop interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens in the Chief Migration Officers' oral history project</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>National Library of Australia, Oral History and Folklore Collection</repository>
<unittitle>Clare Bishop interviewed by Ann-Mari Jordens in the Chief Migration Officers' oral history project</unittitle>
<unitid>TRC 5930/16</unitid>
<abstract>Clare Bishop talks about her early life; her education; work experience in U.S.A. and France; her university and hotel and catering management studies; joining the Department of Immigration, Professional Migration Section; posting to London; pre-departure training; promoting migration in Britain; selecting British migrants; youth migration; training male interviewing officers; migrants' knowledge of Australia and their expectations; Canberra, Recruitment Officer (1974); appointment to Edinburgh, Belfast (1975); family sponsorship; living in Edinburgh, travelling in Scotland; posting to New York with responsibility for eastern Canada (1977); types of applicants, character checking; interviewing Canadian applicants for migration; Canberra, Legal and Parliamentary Branch as Ministerial Correspondence Officer; organising Commonwealth Heads of Government Meeting, Melbourne (1981); Canberra, Vietnamese unaccompanied refugee minors.

Bishop discusses her posting to Cologne, Germany, to process Polish refugees; processing chefs in Berne, Switzerland; brides in the Philippines; return to Canberra, to Australian Institute of Multicultural Affairs Secretariat, evaluation of the implementation of the Galbally report; Vietnam posting (1984-86), training for staff, accommodation, processing, travel, communications, interviewing, documentation; migrant sponsorship; American and Canadian migration processing arrangements in Vietnam; health and character checking; official visitors; air services; posting to New York (1986-90); staff, tourism, migration, temporary residents, student exchange, Chicago and Toronto posts; promoting business migration; Olympic Games bid; working in Washington Embassy compared with Vietnam; Canberra, Executive Branch (1990-2000), National Population Council; Departmental Liaison in the office of Minister Jerry Hand; her retirement (2000); Canberra School of Music.

Recorded May 8, 2009</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>4 Sound files</extent>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>