<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00078</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>revised</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Corporate Body</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-12-18">2009-12-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kathleen Bambridge</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00078b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>corporateBody</entityType>
<nameEntry><part>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="abrreviated name"><part>Welling Place</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType=""><part>Women's Community Health Centre</part>
</nameEntry>
<nameEntry localType="subsequent name"><part>Mary St</part>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><existDates>
<dateRange>
<fromDate standardDate="1974-01-01">1974</fromDate>
<toDate standardDate="1989-12-31">1989</toDate>
</dateRange>
</existDates>
<places>
<place>
<placeRole>Start Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Hindmarsh, South Australia, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
<place>
<placeRole>End Place</placeRole>
<placeEntry>Hindmarsh , South Australia, Australia</placeEntry>
</place>
</places>
<functions>
<function>
<term>Health service</term>
</function>
</functions>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first women's health centre in South Australia. The Women's Liberation Movement recognised the need for a separate women's health centre from the number of health related calls and personal enquiries it received and lobbied the government for assistance. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St, Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. The Health Centre became a teaching centre for women's health in late 1975 and produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre.

Funding came through the state government and as a result there were some clashes between the bureaucracy and the feminist executive over how the centre should be run. This was further complicated by the clashing politics of the various feminist groups involved in the centre, which was run by a feminist collective. Conflict with the State Health Department eventially lead to the withdrawal of funding.

After the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier, who argued the case for the need for specialised women's health services, the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 to make way for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre.</abstract>
<p>The work of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement of the 1970s called for a separate women's health education centre to inform women about basic gynaecology, reproductive health and psychological health. A group called Body Political put out a newsletter on women's health and presented a program 'Our Body Ourselves' on radio 5UV at Adelaide University. The submission for funding was made in 1974. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first women's health centre in South Australia. With the public funding of the Centre there was a struggle between what the feminist wanted to achieve and the South Australian Health Commision with its limiting rules. The feminists wanted to teach women about their health but because they were not an accreditied institution they had to be granted the right to teach. The Centre produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. They did become a teaching centre for women's health for a time. Because funding was through the state the feminist way of running the centre as a collective with members of the centre and the bureaucracy and its requirements often clashed. This was further complicated by the feminist groups involved in the centre. The conflict with the Health Department eventually led to the withdrawal of funding. With the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier the need of Women's Health Centre was argued and the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. Hindmarsh Women's Health Centre continued with the Medicare payments to support other work of the centre. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre. Some of the women involved include Margaret Mc Donald, Mary Nettle, Vicky Papadopolois, Karen Weir, Maria Radoslovich, Sylvia Kinder, Trish Leigh, Helen Bock and Silver Moon.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00096b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive  (1984 - 2009)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00064b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Kinder, Sylvia
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00039b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Moon, Silver (1952 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00063b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Rape Crisis Centre (1976 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00043b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
The Women's Advisory Office, South Australian Government (1976 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1477474">
<relationEntry></relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre ', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00078b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00076.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Pamphlet: A Piece of the Cake:  a celebration and herstory of metropolitan women's health centres in South Australia </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Radoslovich, Helen</name>
<title render="italic">A Piece of the Cake:  a celebration and herstory of metropolitan women's health centres in South Australia </title>
<imprint>
<place>Elizabeth SA</place>
<publisher>Combined Women's Health Centre</publisher>
<date>1994</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00075.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </unittitle>
<unitdate>1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first Women's Health Centre in South Australia. The Women's Liberation Movement recognised the need for a separate women's health centre from the number of health related calls and personal enquires. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. Because funding was through the state the feminist way of running the centre and the bureaucracy and its requirements often clashed. This was further complicated by the feminist groups involved in the centre. The Centre was run by a feminist collective. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre. The Health Centre became a teaching centre for women's health. The Centre produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. The conflict with the Health Department eventially lead to the withdrawal of funding. With the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier the continuing need for a Women's Health Centre was argued and the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. Hindmarsh Women's Health Centre continued with the Medicare payments to support other work of the centre. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.109999999403954 m, 80 </extent>
<physfacet>minutes, daybooks, film, posters, pamphlets, </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00108.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1969 - May 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement began at the University of Adelaide in 1968, with the women who were active in young labour, the anti-vietnam war campaign questing their frustration and roles in these groups that were male dominated. Anna Yeatman, Anne Summers and Julie Ellis are credited with starting the newsletters Sisterhood, and Body Political by late 1969 they produced Liberation, the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter which replaced Sisterhood. Their first protest was against the Miss Fresher competition, which gain media exposer to their ideas of women's liberation. Public meetings where called and the broader community involvement brought about the establishment of the Women's Liberation Movement housed at Bloor House. They provided an environment where ideas for supporting women'd rights were fostered. From this the Women's Liberation Movement in Adelaide was the catalyst for the establishment of the Women's Health Centre at Hindmarsh, The Rape Crisis Centre, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Abortion Action Campaign, St Peters Women's Community Centre, Women's Health Centers at Chrisities Beach and Elizabeth, lobbied for Women's Studies to be part of Tertiary education, women's representation in parliments, Working Women's Centre to Protect women's working rights, the Women's Peace Movement. Bloor House provided a space for women to express their personal political ideas and to get feedback and support. The Women's Liberation Movement moved from Bloor House to Eden St in Adelaide and then to Mary St, Hindmarsh were it was closed in 1989.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.323000013828278 m, 1021 </extent>
<physfacet>banners, minutes, correspondence, badges, posters, flyers, daybooks</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>