<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="shared/cpf.rng" type="xml"?>
<eac-cpf xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-33-4 http://eac.staatsbibliothek-berlin.de/schema/cpf.xsd">
<control>
<recordId>PR00064</recordId>
<maintenanceStatus>new</maintenanceStatus>
<maintenanceAgency>
<agencyCode>AU-VU:AWR</agencyCode>
<agencyName>The  Australian Women's Register</agencyName>
<descriptiveNote>
<p></p>
</descriptiveNote>
</maintenanceAgency>
<languageDeclaration>
<language languageCode="eng">English</language>
<script scriptCode="Latn">Latin</script>
</languageDeclaration>
<conventionDeclaration>
<abbreviation>AACR2</abbreviation>
<citation>Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules</citation>
</conventionDeclaration>
<localControl localType="typeOfEntity">
<term>Person</term>
</localControl>
<maintenanceHistory>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>created</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2009-12-18">2009-12-18</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent>Kathleen Bambridge</agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
<maintenanceEvent>
<eventType>updated</eventType>
<eventDateTime standardDateTime="2013-09-13">2013-09-13</eventDateTime>
<agentType>human</agentType>
<agent></agent>
<eventDescription></eventDescription>
</maintenanceEvent>
</maintenanceHistory>
</control>
<cpfDescription>
<identity><entityId>http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00064b.htm</entityId>
<entityType>person</entityType>
<nameEntry><part localType="familyname">Kinder</part>
<part localType="givenname">Sylvia</part>
<authorizedForm>AACR2</authorizedForm>
</nameEntry>
</identity>
<description><places>
</places>
<occupations>
<occupation>
<term>Teacher</term>
</occupation>
<occupation>
<term>Feminist</term>
</occupation>
</occupations>
<biogHist>
<abstract>Sylvia Kinder was active in both the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement and the Sydney Women's Liberation Movement. As a teacher she was involved with the South Australian Institute of Teachers (SAIT) which questioned sexist teaching practices within schools. She helped bring changes in education standards designed to reduce gender discrimination,  including the use of non sexist language in school and equal opportunities for girls. Sylvia was a member of the Australian Women's Education Coalition (South Australian Branch). She was involved in the establishment of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archives and the Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre. She was a member of International Women's Year National Advisory Committee 1974-1976. She wrote a book about the women's liberation movement in Adelaide.

</abstract>
<p>The need for a women's studies courses became apparent to Sylvia Kinder and other concerned teachers who, in response, set about establishing a women's library as part of the Women's Liberation Movement. Books and papers were donated and the Women's Studies Resource Centre was created. She taught women's studies at the Women's Studies Resource Centre. She was a collective member of <span style="font-style:italic">Liberation</span>, Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter. She served on the Status of Women's Standing Committee from 1974-1976. Sylvia addressed International Women's Day rallies or marches. She helped organise conferences including the Young Women's Festival and the Women in Labour Conference both held in Adelaide. She was also active in gay liberation in South Australia. Some of the other groups she was involved with included Women Behind Bars, Salisbury Women's Group Newsletter, Salisbury Women's Health Centre, National Women's Consultative Council, SAIT Professional Development Committee, International Women's Day Collective. Women's Theatre Group (South Australia). There is a collection of taped interviews with South Australian feminist including Pat Ronald, Liz Byard, Anna Yeatman, Judy Gillett, Betty Fisher, Connie Frazer, Deborah McCulloch, Jill Mathews, Sue Higgins (Sheridan) and Gail Tauscher. Sylvia Kinder wrote <span style="font-style:italic">Herstory</span> of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement 1969-1974.</p>

</biogHist>
</description>
<relations><cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00096b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive  (1984 - 2009)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00078b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre  (1974 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00102b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement (1969 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00094b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Corporate Body">
Women's Theatre Group (1975 - 1989)
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00042b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
McCulloch, Deborah Jane (1939 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="associative" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00039b.htm">
<relationEntry localType="Person">
Moon, Silver (1952 - )
</relationEntry>
</cpfRelation>
<cpfRelation cpfRelationType="identity" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://nla.gov.au/nla.party-1251732">
<relationEntry>
Kinder, Sylvia
</relationEntry>
<descriptiveNote><p>Trove</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</cpfRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="subjectOf">
<relationEntry localType="published">'Kinder, Sylvia', in <span style="font-style:italic">The  Australian Women's Register</span>, National Foundation for Australian Women and The University of Melbourne</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<title render="italic">Kinder, Sylvia</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>National Foundation for Australian Women</publisher>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">The  Australian Women's Register</title>
</bibseries>
<extptr linktype="simple" href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/biogs/PR00064b.htm"></extptr>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00066.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Book: Herstory of Adelaide Women's Liberation 1969-1974</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author">Kinder, Sylvia </name>
<title render="italic">Herstory of Adelaide Women's Liberation 1969-1974</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>Salisbury Education Centre</publisher>
<date>1980</date>
</imprint>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/bib/PR00054.htm">
<relationEntry localType="published">Newsletter: Liberation</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<bibref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<name type="author"></name>
<title render="italic">Liberation</title>
<imprint>
<place>Adelaide</place>
<publisher>Liberation</publisher>
<date>1970</date>
</imprint>
<bibseries>
<title render="italic">Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter</title>
<num type="volume">314</num>
</bibseries>
</bibref>
</objectXMLWrap>

<descriptiveNote>
<p>Source used to compile entry</p>
</descriptiveNote>
</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00818.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Address by Sylvia Kinder to Women's Studies Workshop, Adelaide </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Address by Sylvia Kinder to Women's Studies Workshop, Adelaide </unittitle>
<unitid>OH 242/2</unitid>
<unitdate>April 1979</unitdate>
<physdesc>
<extent></extent>
<physfacet>Audio tape</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="creatorOf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00065.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Papers of Sylvia Kinder</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Papers of Sylvia Kinder</unittitle>
<unitid>PRG 1500</unitid>
<unitdate>1970 - 1986</unitdate>
<abstract>Sylvia Kinder was active in the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement. As a teacher she was active with the South Australian Institute of Teachers (SAIT) questioning the sexist teaching practices within schools. She was active in changing education standards to include girls, the use of non sexist language in school and equal opportunities for girls. Sylvia was a member of the Australian Women's Education Coalition (SA Branch). She was involved in the establishment of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archives and the Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre. She was a member of International Women's Year National Advisory Committee 1974-1976. The need for a women's studies courses became apparent to Sylvia and other concerned teachers and set about setting up the a women's library as part of the Women's Liberation Movement. Books and papers where donated and the Women's Studies Resource Centre was created. She taught women's studies at the Women's Studies Resource Centre. She was A collective member of Liberation, Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter. She served on the Status of Women's Standing Committee from 1974-1976. Sylvia addressed International Women's Day rallies or marches. She helped organise conferences including the Young Women's Festival and the Women in Labour Conference both held in Adelaide. She was also active in gay liberation in South Australia. Some of the other groups she was involved in are Women Behind Bars, Salisbury Women's Group Newsletter, Salisbury Women's Health centre, National Women's Consultative Council, SAIT Professional Development Committee, International Women's Day Collective. Women's Theatre Group (South Australia). There is a collection of taped interviews with South Australian feminist including Pat Ronald, Liz Byard, Anna Yeatman, Judy Gillett, Betty Fisher, Connie Frazer, Debroah McCulloch, Jill Mathews, Sue Higgins (Sheridan) and Gail Tauscher. Sylvia Kinder wrote Herstory of the Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement 1969-1974.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.29999995231628 m, 86 badges, folders t shirts, minutes, printed papers,</extent>
<physfacet>Printed papers, lists, minutes, t shirts, badges, posters audio tapes</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00108.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement</unittitle>
<unitdate>November 1969 - May 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement began at the University of Adelaide in 1968, with the women who were active in young labour, the anti-vietnam war campaign questing their frustration and roles in these groups that were male dominated. Anna Yeatman, Anne Summers and Julie Ellis are credited with starting the newsletters Sisterhood, and Body Political by late 1969 they produced Liberation, the Adelaide Women's Liberation Newsletter which replaced Sisterhood. Their first protest was against the Miss Fresher competition, which gain media exposer to their ideas of women's liberation. Public meetings where called and the broader community involvement brought about the establishment of the Women's Liberation Movement housed at Bloor House. They provided an environment where ideas for supporting women'd rights were fostered. From this the Women's Liberation Movement in Adelaide was the catalyst for the establishment of the Women's Health Centre at Hindmarsh, The Rape Crisis Centre, Women's Studies Resource Centre, Abortion Action Campaign, St Peters Women's Community Centre, Women's Health Centers at Chrisities Beach and Elizabeth, lobbied for Women's Studies to be part of Tertiary education, women's representation in parliments, Working Women's Centre to Protect women's working rights, the Women's Peace Movement. Bloor House provided a space for women to express their personal political ideas and to get feedback and support. The Women's Liberation Movement moved from Bloor House to Eden St in Adelaide and then to Mary St, Hindmarsh were it was closed in 1989.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.323000013828278 m, 1021 </extent>
<physfacet>banners, minutes, correspondence, badges, posters, flyers, daybooks</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00095.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive</unittitle>
<unitdate>1984 - 1 March 2009</unitdate>
<abstract>The Adelaide Women's Liberation Movement Archive was established in 1984 by a concerned group of women who wanted to preserve the history of what was called the second wave of feminism. With the aid of the Community Employment Program and the feminist community memorabilla was collected along with the papers of a variety of groups and individuals. The material was collected from late 1969 through to 2008.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>30 m, 4000 </extent>
<physfacet>Posters, minutes correspondence, flyers, badges, banners, photographs, slides, video and audio tapes, film, daybooks, scrapbooks, financial</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00093.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Women's Theatre Group</relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Women's Theatre Group</unittitle>
<unitdate>1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>The Women's Theatre Group was active in Adelaide from 1975 to 1989. They wrote, produced, directed, scored, performed and built the stage for their productions. They performed cabaret and theatrical works. All women productions were a first in Adelaide. The women worked through a collective. They won the Adelaide Festival Centre best production award for 'Redheads Revenge' in 1978. The other plays and cabaret include 'Christobel in Paris' 1975, 'Caroline Chisel Show' 1976, 'International Women's Day Concert' and 'Chores 1' in 1977, 'Chores 2' and 'I want I want' 1979, 'Out of the Frying Pan' 1980, 'Onward to Glory' 1982, 'Margin to Mainstream' and 'Women and Work, Women and Paid Work' 1984, 'Sybil's Xmas Concert' 1985, and 1989 'Is this Seat Taken'. The group includes the Women in Education Theatre Group and the Feminist Theatre Group.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.899999976158142 m, 78 </extent>
<physfacet>scrips, photographys, reviews, songs, musical arrangements, audio and viseo recordings, flyers, posters, budgets, list of members, cast lists.</physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
<resourceRelation resourceRelationType="other" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://www.womenaustralia.info/archives/PR00075.htm">
<relationEntry localType="archival">Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </relationEntry>

<objectXMLWrap>
<archref xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9">
<repository>State Library of South Australia</repository>
<unittitle>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre </unittitle>
<unitdate>1975 - 1989</unitdate>
<abstract>Hindmarsh Women's Community Health Centre was the first Women's Health Centre in South Australia. The Women's Liberation Movement recognised the need for a separate women's health centre from the number of health related calls and personal enquires. Funding was granted in 1974 and 6 Mary St Hindmarsh was offically open in 1976. Because funding was through the state the feminist way of running the centre and the bureaucracy and its requirements often clashed. This was further complicated by the feminist groups involved in the centre. The Centre was run by a feminist collective. The Rape Crisis Centre evolved from the Health Centre. The Health Centre became a teaching centre for women's health. The Centre produced pamphlets on both general and gynaecological health. The conflict with the Health Department eventially lead to the withdrawal of funding. With the intervention of the Women's Adviser to the Premier the continuing need for a Women's Health Centre was argued and the centre was moved to North Adelaide and became Women's Health Statewide. Hindmarsh Women's Health Centre continued with the Medicare payments to support other work of the centre. The Centre then became known as the Welling Place, providing alternative health including a vegtable patch for the community. 6 Mary St was demolished in 1989 for the Adelaide Entertainment Centre.</abstract>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.109999999403954 m, 80 </extent>
<physfacet>minutes, daybooks, film, posters, pamphlets, </physfacet>
</physdesc>
</archref>
</objectXMLWrap>

</resourceRelation>
</relations>
</cpfDescription>
</eac-cpf>